<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../lifehistory.xsl" ?>
<history>
  <title>Where Toime is Koind</title>
  <reflink>https://dc.lib.unc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/03709/id/1148</reflink>
  <meta>
    <item>
      <key>Date</key>
      <val>1938-12-09</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Location</key>
      <val>Collington Island, North Carolina</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Occupations</key>
      <val>WPA worker</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Interviewee</key>
      <val>Norris Beasley (white; male)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Pseudonym</key>
      <val>Nelly Padgett</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Writer</key>
      <val>W. O. Saunders (white; male)</val>
    </item>
  </meta>
  <text>
    <p>Morris Ressley</p>
    <p>Collington Island, N. C.</p>
    <p>December 9, 1938</p>
    <p>W.O.S.</p>
    <p>William O. Saunders</p>
    <p>"WHERE TOIME IS KOIND"</p>
    <p/>
    <p>The shack in which he lived had once been a little houseboat;</p>
    <p>just a little flat bottom scow sixteen feet long by ten feet wide,</p>
    <p>with a house on it ten feet long, leaving three feet of the decking</p>
    <p>of the scow exposed at either end. It was his elder brother's </p>
    <p>home for some years. His brother, a man of simple wants, had eked</p>
    <p>out a living by fishing and hunting in the waters of Hoenoke and Currituck Sounds. </p>
    <p>Occasionally he furnished his services as a guide</p>
    <p>to fishing parties. His income was ample to keep him in tobacco,</p>
    <p>flour, sugar, coffee, the few staples he required, and provide him</p>
    <p>with an occasional pair of fisherman's boots, yarn socks, etc.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>And then a nor'easter that blew for days in the bay of Chickahawk </p>
    <p>in which he had anchored cast the little houseboat high on </p>
    <p>the marshes of Carlyle Island. When the wind lulled and the waters</p>
    <p>subsided old men like Padgett came out to survey the wreck of his</p>
    <p>abode. The little houseboat layed due east and west across the dirt </p>
    <p>road that skirted the bay near the northeast extremity of the island. Not a bad </p>
    <p>location for a lone widower who subsisted by fishing, hunting, and guide service.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>The old man looked up the owner of the property on which the cabined scow had </p>
    <p>drifted, obtained permission to let the scow</p>
    <p>remain there. And then the old man's thoughts turned to a young widow whom he had </p>
    <p>known on the isle of Ocracoke. He looked her up, courted her, married her and </p>
    <p>brought her to his new &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;. But first he had added another room to the </p>
    <p>houseboat.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>His bride seemed but a child mentally and hardly more than a child in years.</p>
    <p>Twice married before, the first time when she was only fourteen, she had two </p>
    <p>children by her former husbands and these she brought with her to the new home.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>Nolly Padgett, brother of Ike was getting old; he had been married three times and </p>
    <p>the last of his wives was dead; his children had grown up and married and made </p>
    <p>homes of their own. Holly came to visit his brother, looked upon the child wife </p>
    <p>and liked her, looked over the shack and decided another room could be added on </p>
    <p>the other end at little expense. He obtained some lumber and nails, built the new </p>
    <p>addition himself, and came to live with his brother.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>Old man Ike died in the spring of 1937.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"His widow wanted to stay on with me." said Nolly gloomily, "but that would have </p>
    <p>brought on right smart talk. She cried and cut up when her family took her away."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>But within three months Nolly had taken his brother's widow in matrimony. "It was </p>
    <p>my brother's dying wish," said Nolly: "The truth is -- and there ain't no way of </p>
    <p>fooling God up yonder who knows everything we're doing -- I loved her and she </p>
    <p>loved me before my brother died. My brother wasn't no count for a year before he </p>
    <p>took and died; he couldn't do nothin' for her. I could giver her what she wanted. </p>
    <p>I think my brother knew all the time what was going on, and I think he was glad </p>
    <p>because he loved her and it hurt him to see her suffer."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"But what are you going to so when you become no 'count?" the interviewer asked him.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I ain't crossing no bridges until I get to 'em," replied the old man. She's happy </p>
    <p>now and she's tamed down a lot as she's got older; and she don't have to have the </p>
    <p>lovin' she used to have."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"But isn't it risky business for an old man to marry a young girl?" the </p>
    <p>interviewer persisted.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Now I'll tell you," said the old man; "An old man should never marry anthing but </p>
    <p>a young woman. When a man begins to get along in years he's a grinder; now if he </p>
    <p>marries a grinder there ain't much satisfaction for wither of 'em; but if he </p>
    <p>marries a self-starter its easy to get a spark."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>Mrs. Padgett and the children were away from home at the time of the interview. </p>
    <p>The house was badly in disorder. Dirty dishes were piked on the kitchen table, </p>
    <p>children's clothes were scattered over the living room floor, a plate of fish </p>
    <p>bones from which the cat had eaten sat in the entry between the living room and kitchen.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>There was a doorway but no door between the living room and the adjoining bedroom. </p>
    <p>The bedroom contained a double bed with a partition of rough corrugated board </p>
    <p>extending from the foot of it to the ceiling. the obvious purpose of which was to </p>
    <p>shield it from the view of the child occupants who slept on cots in the end of the </p>
    <p>room. Here was no privacy. The bed covering had a grayish, dingy look. The family </p>
    <p>washing was done by boiling clothes in an iron pot in the yard and washed in a </p>
    <p>small tub that, when not in use, was shoved under the house. There was hardly room </p>
    <p>in the little kitchen for an ironing board. the little cast iron ship'u stove they </p>
    <p>cooked on looked like a toy stove.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>The premises generally were untidy. Two scrawny &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; grew by the front door </p>
    <p>stoop. A garden of collards and shallots seemed to be thriving in the black marsh </p>
    <p>soil near the house. In a pan improvised by hanging several thicknesses of a </p>
    <p>discarded fish net from four stakes, a half dozen &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; chickens pined.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Do you raise these &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; for sport?" the interviewer asked.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"No, don't exactly know how we come by 'em. They ain't nothin' on 'em to eat if we </p>
    <p>killed 'em, and if we turned 'em out they'd never come back alive. Somehow we just </p>
    <p>keep 'em. Still, I ain't one for wantin' to keep anything peened up. Maybe I'll </p>
    <p>sell 'em some say if somebody comes along and wants 'em.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Where is Mrs. Padgett?" the interviewer asked.</p>
    <p>"She's gone to the store in the woods up there to get some letters fired up. There </p>
    <p>was a woman and her husband from Chicago stopped here a year or two ago and took a </p>
    <p>fancy to her and the children, and they have been sending them presents ever </p>
    <p>since. She got a letter from 'em t'other day asking her what the children wanted </p>
    <p>for Christmas, and she's been so excited ever since that she can't rest until she </p>
    <p>gets a letter fixed up to send off to Chicago."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Do you see many automobiles from other states here on the island?" the interviewer asked.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Lots of 'em," the old man replied. "They seem to get turned around when they </p>
    <p>leave the paved road over on the beach and when they see a road leading this way </p>
    <p>they just follow that road until they get over that bridge you see there and hit </p>
    <p>this island. Then they stop here to ask where they're at. I have a lot of fun with 'em."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"A city feller with a big, shiny automobile drives up, blown his horn and I come </p>
    <p>out. He wants to know where this road goes! I sez to him, sez I, I've been livin' </p>
    <p>here for a long time and it ain't gone nowhere yet.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"And then he wants to know if this road will take him to Kitty Hawk?"</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"And I say it might take you there if it moved, but it ain't been in a notion to move since I've known it."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Well, after havin' my fun with 'em like that for a few minutes I tell 'em where </p>
    <p>they got in wrong and help 'em get going again. They come in here all hours of the </p>
    <p>night; I've had them wake me up honking their horns way after midnight. They think </p>
    <p>they have come to the jumping off place shore nuff. They're mighty grateful when I </p>
    <p>quit kiddin' 'em and tell 'em what they want to know. Sometimes they give me a </p>
    <p>piece of money, a drink of liquor or a cigar. They used to just about keep my wife </p>
    <p>in cigarettes until I broke her of smokin'."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Does your wife use tobacco in any form any more?" the interviewer asked.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Yea, I told her she could dip snuff. She likes liquor too, but I won't have none </p>
    <p>of that. Used to a lot of folks would drop in at night and bring liquor and play </p>
    <p>the phonograph until two o'clock in the morning. I got tired of that sort of </p>
    <p>foolishness and put my foot down on it. We've had it pretty quiet here ever since."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>The wind had shifted and blew chill over the bay.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>The old man got up and closed the door of the shack, filled his pipe from a fruit </p>
    <p>jat half full of plug cut tobacco and reflected upon life in general.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I ain't been feeling a bit well for the past week," he said. "I work on the WPA </p>
    <p>and I stopped at a store and bought a can of sausage one day last week. I noticed </p>
    <p>they were hard ad dry when I opened the can, but I was hungry and ate 'em. I came </p>
    <p>home that evenin' with pains in my stomach and thought I was going to die. Took a </p>
    <p>big dose of Black Draught and went to bed and I 'm still living, but I've been s </p>
    <p>mighty sick man. '&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;' I reckon."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Did you notice the can that the sausage came in? Did the top bulge and a little </p>
    <p>gas escape from it when you opened it?"</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Come to think of it, the top of that can was bulged out and it was sort of black </p>
    <p>instead of brassy inside when I opened it." Nolly is sixty-five years old and has </p>
    <p>lived much out of tinned cans in his day, but had never learned to identify a </p>
    <p>tinned can laden with possibilities of &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; poison, by its bulging top.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Livin' is easy around here. She (he always referred to his wife as she) and the </p>
    <p>children fished off the bridge yesterday evenin' and caught 'leven as pretty bass </p>
    <p>as you'd want to see. I've got a set there that I fish when the ducks and geese </p>
    <p>are flying around. There's lots of squirrels on the island too. I've got a good </p>
    <p>squirrel dog."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Our garden usually does right well, but the tide come up over it this spring and </p>
    <p>almost drowned out the collards. Didn't hurt the shallots though. Shallots can </p>
    <p>stand anything; all you got to do is stick a few of 'em down in the ground and the </p>
    <p>place will be run over with them before you know it. And they're the making of a </p>
    <p>fish stew. Put a rock fish in a pan with a little water, flour, salt, and pepper </p>
    <p>and a few shallots, and lay a few slices of salt port on it and put it in the </p>
    <p>oven, and you've got somethin' to make your hair curl."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>The old man went over to the little sheet iron heater that furnished the only heat </p>
    <p>for the three room shack in winter, lifted the lid and emptied the ashes from his pipe.</p>
    <p>"Let's have a little music," he said.</p>
    <p>Going over to a cabinet phonograph that stood in a corner, he fished out a double </p>
    <p>faced record, placed it on the disc, would up the spring meter and set the needle.</p>
    <p>"This is her favorite piece," he said, referring to his wife. "She played it over </p>
    <p>and over again when my brother died. The title of the piece was "We Can't Be </p>
    <p>Darlings Any More," a Montgomery Ward record played by Heiner's Mountaineers.</p>
    <p>As the last wail of the plaintive air ended, the old man arose with moist eyes and </p>
    <p>changed the record to the other side. "This is a right purty piece too," he said.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>The machine galloped off with "Tell Mother I'll Be There," sung by the same </p>
    <p>mountaineers in the accompanient of fiddle, banjo, guitar and mouth harp.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I paid $175 for that phonograph when times were better," he said. "Lately most of </p>
    <p>my records were worn out, so I sent off to Montgomery Ward and got twenty new </p>
    <p>records this summer."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>As the interviewer was about to leave, he looked up the road and saw the wife </p>
    <p>coming with two children, a boy and a girl trailing behind her. She walked with a </p>
    <p>brisk step. She was a smallish woman, in her early twenties. She wore a &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; print </p>
    <p>dress that fairly revealed the curves of her figure.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>The children were a bit shy, but the woman came up to her husband, leaned against </p>
    <p>him affectionately and looked the interviewer over with laughing, friendly eyes.</p>
    <p>Noting a five or six days growth of stubble on her old man's face, the interviewer </p>
    <p>asked Mrs. Padgett why she didn't make him shave?</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Lor' man, if oi did oi'd have to shave him moiself," she replied, speaking with </p>
    <p>the quaint brogue peculiar to many natives of the region.</p>
    <p>"How often do you shave him?" the interviewer asked.</p>
    <p>"Oi don't exactly know; let him go some toimes fer eight or noine days. Don't want </p>
    <p>him to look purty much of the toime, because oi don't want him to git to </p>
    <p>ballywhackin' around the neighborhood," she said, looking up into his grizzled </p>
    <p>face with a mischievous twinkle that carried with it a look of pride in the </p>
    <p>ownership of a spouse who was old enough to be her grandfather.</p>
    <p>The Padgetts have no quarrel with the world; self-pity is utterly foreign to them; </p>
    <p>used to hardships and simple living, they are not worried about owning things.</p>
    <p>"Better stay and have dinner with us," Mrs. Padgett said, as the interviewer moved </p>
    <p>to depart; "Oi ain't had time to cook anything today, but we got a mess of loima </p>
    <p>beans in the house an hit won't take no toime to scare up somethin' t'eat if you </p>
    <p>all kin put with our keind of livin'."</p>
  </text>
</history>
