<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../lifehistory.xsl" ?>
<history>
  <title>Nicholas P. Petrou</title>
  <reflink>https://dc.lib.unc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/03709/id/1094</reflink>
  <meta>
    <item>
      <key>Date</key>
      <val>1940-02-05</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Location</key>
      <val>Miami, Florida</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Occupations</key>
      <val>teacher</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Interviewee</key>
      <val>Nicholas Papa Petrou (greek; male)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Writer</key>
      <val>Cora Mae Taylor (white; female)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Reviser</key>
      <val>Mabel B. Francis (white; female)</val>
    </item>
  </meta>
  <text>
    <p>Socio-Etinic Study</p>
    <p>The Crooks in America</p>
    <p>Cora Lee Taylor</p>
    <p>February 5, 1940</p>
    <p>Mabel B. Francis</p>
    <p>Editor</p>
    <p>Miami, Florida.</p>
    <p>NICHOLAS P. PETROU</p>
    <p>134 Northeast Second Avenue</p>
    <p>Miami, Florida</p>
    <p>Master Nicholas Papa Petrou, age 40, is a hale appearing man with a ruddy complexion, dark hair and very bright dark open. His neat grooming and his happy, anger, confident expression distinguish him as a person of unusual intelligence and refinement.</p>
    <p>Master Papa Petrou conducts a church school for the Greek children from four to six one afternoon during the regular school year. The school is supported by the church, and although no distinct religious training is given, many moral lessons are taught in the reading classes through the simple stories in the text books. The aim of the school is to teach the pupils to read and write the Greek language as mental discipline, to make it easier for them to learn other foreign language as in high school, to aid them to secure positions where interpreters are needed, and to keep the children interested in the Greek church through their ability to understand the services.</p>
    <p>The text books are a ranged like American school readers with short stories and bright pictures of American children, games, and pots. The stories teach good health habits, such as baththing, brushing the tooth, taking proper sleep and exercise, also kindness to animals and playmates, abandoned to parents and habits of truthfulness.</p>
    <p>Mr. Petrou explained: "I very seldom use my titles when signing my name, except on my passports. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; the title of Master when I graduated from Normal school in Cyprus. My title, which was my birthright granted by the Greek Orthodox church because I am the son of a priest. My father having &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; ried before taking the vows of priesthood at &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, Cyprus. This custom which is generally observed by my church, is the other of point of difference between the Greek Orthodox and the Roman Catholic Church.</p>
    <p>"Except in the schoolroom where I am called Master." I am usually called 'Papa Petrou' and I usually, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; my name, Neal P. Petrou."</p>
    <p>"My father was a teacher and I had all the advantages of getting a good education. I finished school at an early age and then was seat to boarding school. My masters were appointed by the English Government. The English language was never difficult for me. I love it, only I find that I haven't a fluent tongue to speak it. I've studied for 15 years, but I still need a special teacher to help no express myself better. Our school was a very high-class school. We had to high a paper that we didn't dance, didn't drink a smoke and didn't do any of those things. Couldn't have stayed there, if we didn't leave (live) clean lives. If I didn't, the children would read it on me.</p>
    <p>"After I applied to the consul for permission to come to America. I had to wait three years before I was notified. My consul bought my ticket and told me just what to do. So I had no trouble comin over here. My position as teacher had hour, secured by the church in Roanoke. Virginia. I was paid for my teaching and loading the choice.</p>
    <p>"I thought I knew the English language very well, but I had plenty of trouble getting used to the American language, for I had only British English teachers. One of the first things I discovered was that Americans do not talk like my teachers talked, so I was afraid to use my English at first. I always carried with me my dictionary in my pocket and I made good use of it. My consul did not tell me how to get to Roanoke from New York. I hated to ask anyone for fear they would think me very ignorant.</p>
    <p>"I went to the station with my language, but what to do, I did not know. I stood there and around and there I saw some letters staring at me,  &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;. I sez to myself that word is In-for-ma-tion! What that word information could means I couldn't take my eyes off it. I see fellow go to that &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; I looked in my dictionary and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; was like a friend to help me. They told me where to buy my ticket and I thought I had all the information I needed.</p>
    <p>"I brought my ticket and understand the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; to tell me that the train would come at 10 hearty o'clock (10:30). I thought that was what &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; 10 o'clock &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, but I couldn't thing what 10 hearty could mean. I couldn't find it in my dictionary.</p>
    <p>"Ha! Ha! It is funny now when I think of it! Wall, I just sat there. I thought I'd ask &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; trading came in, if it would take me to  someone when the train came but no train and oh, it seemed so long to wait until 10 hearty! Ha! Ha!</p>
    <p>"I had the correct address of where I was to go in Roanoke, but I had no idea how I was going to find it.</p>
    <p>I had read about the English Bobbies, so I thought I'd know a policeman, if I saw one. Sure enough! I stopped up to a man in uniform and told him where I wanted to go.</p>
    <p>'Why don't you take a taxi?' he asked.</p>
    <p>"Taxi! Taxi! I wondered "what's that." &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; before I had the to look in my dictionary, I heard a driver calling:</p>
    <p>"Taxi! Taxi! This way for a taxi!"</p>
    <p>"I saw the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; a cab and reached by domination at last.</p>
    <p>"&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, I &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; to find a restaurant. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; have me a &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; card. I should see that it was printed in English bat I was afraid to try to say the words in a office, and besides there were so many words that I didn't know what they meant and I didn't want to take out my dictionary there before the waiter. So I just gave a quick &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; at the noun and said:</p>
    <p>"Hamau'aks!" (ham and eggs), "I didn't know what that was, but I remembered of hearing a &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and in New York that he went to a restaurant and made a meal of "hamau'aks" so I thought if he could eat it whatever it was. I could eat it once anyway.</p>
    <p>"All the time I was waiting I was wondering what is this that I ordered and I almost laughed when they brought me afga&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; kroas. (&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; xorine, (zoreno, of pig; kroas, meat. I sat there thinking:</p>
    <p>"Before you come to America you studied English, French and Latin. You graduated from boarding school in Greek and now you have a hard time learning American. It is so different from British English. Well, anyway I didn't make a big break that time.</p>
    <p>"Another time, I wanted a glass of milk. An I had been taught that it is more polite to speak in sentences, I asked:</p>
    <p>"Hav 'you meelk' The waitress couldn't understand me. I repeated over and over as plainly as I could: 'Hav' you meelk:' Finally she asked: 'What do you want?' O said: 'Moolk' She Laughed:</p>
    <p>'I get yuh.' We geot it.' Then everybody laughed.</p>
    <p>"My oh!" I thought, "that sounds like the German word for God.</p>
    <p>"I didn't know whether she was swearing or not. I asked a friend afterwards what she called &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; in America. He said: 'You don't talk American you talk British English. You must it say &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, say &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;. You See, I had &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; book taught to &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;.</p>
    <p>"I went to Cypress in 1935-54 to finish my normal training. Then I &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; my English degree of Master which means teacher. You say 'Master' and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; instead of teacher ever &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;.</p>
    <p>"When I came back, I stayed in New York for a little while and applied for a position as interpreter. They opened the book of &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, pointed to four lines and said: 'See if you can translate these four lines.' I said: 'I can't do that, but I'll begin at the first page and translate the whole book for you. I have taught that book and know every word. Then they said. 'you'll do.'</p>
    <p>From Roanoke, Virginia, I went from one place to another actually staying a year at a place, so before coming here I had taught in New Bedford, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and Watertown, Massachusetts, Newark, New Jersey, and Columbus, Ohio. I have book here since September, but it is hard to tell here I'll be next year. I like it in&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; better that any place I've been.</p>
    <p>"I've traveled quite a bit in Egypt, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, Italy, France, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;. Lived America. I went to school, connection to high school and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; times to night school. Once I taught la&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;. I am about ready &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; my second papers now.</p>
    <p>"My mother an &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; are living in Cyprus and also my three &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;- all married. We &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; system of as &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; crore. If we think &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; girl we are introduced &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, but we do &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; court for until we speak to both the mother and the father. He says: 'Would you like to have me for your son.' Then they ask all kinds of questions to find out if we have the characteristics they want their son to have and if they are satisfied, they say: 'Alright.'</p>
    <p>"Of course, I studied my theology, and my parents impressed on me that only ignorant people believed any of the myths. So nothing happened to me that made we believe in the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; school was a good school. They did not teach like they use to teach 200 years when they tried to rule by fear. I never taught that way. I never had to punish my pupils, only to say: 'Don't do that' .' But that was all I needed to say."</p>
    <p>He showed me an English text book that he studied in Cyprus. He knows every page by heart. It is a rather quaint English grammar explaining the parts of speech and sentence construction, and covering 90 pages. Many of the sentences are rather depression, as follow:</p>
    <p>"To help the poor &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; became his chief &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;."</p>
    <p>"To stock &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; by the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;</p>
    <p>For he felt that his soul was &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; its &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;.</p>
    <p>And his &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; could hear him &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and cry</p>
    <p>&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; to have told her that wicked lie."</p>
    <p>"She broke the cup."</p>
    <p>Lose dog &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; him?"</p>
    <p>"The boy beat the man in a game of checkers."</p>
    <p>"The healthy pity the sick."</p>
    <p>"Anger drove him will."</p>
    <p>"The fight struck him with horror."</p>
    <p>"He cannot tell what caused his fall."</p>
    <p>"And kind&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; cheered his drooping soul</p>
    <p>And slowly &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; his languid cheek.</p>
    <p>The big round tears were seen to roll,</p>
    <p>It told the things he could not speak."</p>
    <p>The Look &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; repeated many &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and previous, quotations from &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; follow.</p>
    <p>"Judor a screeching &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; tree</p>
    <p>The village &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; stands."</p>
    <p>"A Switch in &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; saves nine."</p>
    <p>"To do to others as I would</p>
    <p>That the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; do to me</p>
    <p>Will &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; honest, kind and, you</p>
    <p>An &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; to be.</p>
    <p>"People &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; in glass houses should not throw &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;."</p>
    <p>"To spend a little less than we &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; is we stones."</p>
    <p>The title page follows:</p>
    <p>The Primary Grammar</p>
    <p>An Elementary Grammar of the English Lanaguage for use of pupil in Egypt primary schools.</p>
    <p>by</p>
    <p>R.R. Smithurd</p>
    <p>Principal higher Schools of America</p>
    <p>Cairo, Egypt.</p>
    <p>London</p>
    <p>George Phillips and Son, Ltd.</p>
    <p>32 &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; Street</p>
    <p>19&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;.</p>
  </text>
</history>
