<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../lifehistory.xsl" ?>
<history>
  <title>Alexander Mitchell, Financier</title>
  <reflink>https://dc.lib.unc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/03709/id/1091</reflink>
  <meta>
    <item>
      <key>Location</key>
      <val>Jacksonville, Florida</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Occupations</key>
      <val>finacier</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Interviewee</key>
      <val>Alexander Mitchell III (white; male)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Writer</key>
      <val>Rose Shepherd (white; female)</val>
    </item>
  </meta>
  <text>
    <p>Mr. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; was cen&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; after banking hours in his &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; in the bend department of the Barnett National Bank. He is &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; man, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; four &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, rather stockily built &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; hair and quick-moving gray eyes, and is thirty-five, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;.</p>
    <p>&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; had indu&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; to receive his coat, which a &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; ever the back of a hear by office chair. He &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; his coat to the ton of the railing which farced of his &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; the lobby of the elders section of the bank, and inves&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; to come in and be seated.</p>
    <p>"I have been in this position five years, and before this was connecter with the office of Smith-Richardson and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, to the hotel supply trade.</p>
    <p>"I am &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; to say I know very little of my great-grand father, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; who was a financial power in the late 1860's in his &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; Wisconsin," said young Alexander Mitchell III. "He &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; great-grandmother are of English descent and Episcopalians. All family papers have been lost by one means or another and I have nothing to authenticate their arrival and settlement in &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;. However, his financial activation are a matter of record." Production a small paper-bo&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; from the top left-hand crawer &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; early &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; quickly to &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;.</p>
    <p>"Alexander Mitchell, organizer and first &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and stockholder of &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; Railroad; and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; (1869) of the Northwestern National &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; company.</p>
    <p>"I can give no first hand information &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;. For a long time I kept a newspaper clipping of a &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; the Villa by Harriet Belcher Stowe, but that, too &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and I do not know where I could now lay hands &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; it.</p>
    <p>Naturally, I feel r&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;tant in going into as a you &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; my immediate family. My father and mother &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; ago: I have always made my home with my mother &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; know practically nothing of the Mitchell family history.</p>
    <p>"My father David Mitchell I have not seen for considerably ever a &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; if he is at present in Jacksonville. However Mr. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;bridge Richardson, Mr. Francis P. Floming, Mr. J. Y. Wilson, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; to give some club as to his whereabouts."</p>
    <p>&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; hands played nervously with a pencil, and he evidently anxious to get back to the compilation of his report.</p>
    <p>"No, I do not know if I will ever attain to any suck reputation as my famous ancestor enjoyed in the financial world, but I am glad to have become associated with the oldest banking in&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;tion in Jacksonville, and I an &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;ostly trying to make good just as if I were the first Mitchell in the country, with no an&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;stral &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;ground or achievement to live up to.</p>
    <p>"A banker's life is not a bad of roses - it means long&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and hard work, just the come as any other vocation, with the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of responsibility for other people's finances. When &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; down at the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; at 2 p.m. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; the doors are closed, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; hours &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; for the employees; sometimes it &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; afternoon like &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; with &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; cream for into the night during special rushes or busy seasons.</p>
    <p>"I could not discuss my work, that would have to come from the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of my department." he said, clipping his sentences with the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of dismissal.</p>
    <p>"Always work? Well, I have a little recreation. I &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of swimming and I have just taken up golf - but I don't &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; I'll ever become a 'bug' about that. Not so much time to &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;.</p>
    <p>"My early teachers were in a private school, then I attended the Duval County public schools, later &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; from the University of Florida. Now, I an studying a special course in &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; by the American Institute of Banking, and other things in &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; to my work, that takes up a great many of my off hours.</p>
    <p>"Vote? Yes I vote, as a matter of course, but I am &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; I never make a ward politician." he laughed - "too many creeks and turns. Nationally, I like President Roosevelt's &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; believe in time will get finances, labor, and living &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of the American people on the up-and-up."</p>
  </text>
</history>
