<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../lifehistory.xsl" ?>
<history>
  <title>Dona Balmer Male</title>
  <reflink>https://dc.lib.unc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/03709/id/443</reflink>
  <meta>
    <item>
      <key>Date</key>
      <val>1939-01-10</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Location</key>
      <val>Pleasant Hill, North Carolina</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Occupations</key>
      <val>tenant farmer</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Community</key>
      <val>Crew Farm</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Interviewee</key>
      <val>Dona Balmer Male (white; female)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Writer</key>
      <val>Bernice Kelly Harris (white; female)</val>
    </item>
  </meta>
  <text>
    <p>Crew Farm </p>
    <p>Pleasant Hill, N. C. Jan. 10, 1939 B. K. H. </p>
    <p>DONA BALMER MALE, "WHITE </p>
    <p>"Come in if you can get in. We're tore up, wait in' to move. For two weeks I been packed up ready, hopin' every day </p>
    <p>Charlie would come in and say he has found us a place to move to. Looks like we ain't goin' to get no house this year. </p>
    <p>This un belongs to Mr. Winfield Crew; he's done give us orders to get out, but you can't move right out in the road </p>
    <p>'less you're put out like my sister was. Yeh, Mrs. Jordan is my sister; the law moved her things right out in the </p>
    <p>highway three years ago this March." Dona Balmer Male, without removing her soiled slat bonnet, sits in the corner of </p>
    <p>her dirty fireside. </p>
    <p>"I don't blame Mr. Crew nary bit, for we ain't done what we said we'd do. He ain't neither, but that don't free us. We </p>
    <p>come here last year with the understandin' we was to tend a few acres round the house on shares. Soon as crop time </p>
    <p>come, he said he'd have to plant grain here so some o' the rest o' the tenants could have the acreage, but he'd give me </p>
    <p>hoe work to do, and we could stay on here in the house for five dollars a month. I told him I'd do </p>
    <p>5679 </p>
    <p/>
    <p>it. He never give me a day's work the whole year. Every penny I made was three dollars and sixty cent. I give him that. </p>
    <p>If I hadn't been in the horspital from June to August I would o' made more some way or 'nother. </p>
    <p>"Before Christmas, Mr. Crew come and said he hadn't been here to ask us for the rent, for he knowed we didn't have </p>
    <p>it; we was welcome to the five dollars a month we had promised to pay, but he needed his house this comin' year for </p>
    <p>somebody else, and we'd have to get us another place. Even if he did give the rent to us, I don't feel right about it when </p>
    <p>I bargained to pay five dollars a month </p>
    <p>"One thing that's ail the country right now is rentin' land to the governor. Everywhere Charlie goes to look a farm, they </p>
    <p>tell him he's got too big a force. It use to be you didn't have enough force for 'em. When my daddy sharecropped in his </p>
    <p>life-time, they was fourteen of we younguns to work, and we use to make good crops too I'm tellin' you. Now they say </p>
    <p>it pays better to rent the land out to the governor, and they don't want sharecroppers with more'n two or three hands; </p>
    <p>big fam'lies is a drag and dead expense since the cotton acreage has been cut. </p>
    <p>"They's nine of us, 'sides my brother there in the corner. He's named Jim Balmer, after my daddy. Up to the </p>
    <p/>
    <p>-3- </p>
    <p>time he got disable to work he had a job on the road, but now he's too old and afflicted. He's blind and he's got- </p>
    <p>other trouble. I took him here with me. to look after him best I could. They's seven younguns-David Lee, seventeen; </p>
    <p>Thomas Jefferson, sixteen; Charlie, fourteen; Louise, 'leben; Alvin, nine; my two twins, William Henry and Clayra </p>
    <p>Virginia, seven apiece. One died when he was a baby. </p>
    <p>"All but the two oldest is in school to-day. David Lee knocked off in the third grade, and Thomas Jefferson in the </p>
    <p>second. Looked like Thomas Jefferson was the backwards child I ever seen. When he use to set down at night and try </p>
    <p>to read his lesson over, looked like he'd go all to pieces 'cause he couldn't get it. He'd slam his book shut and get out in </p>
    <p>the air. None never got past the fou'th grade. **otise is in the fou'th now, and Clayra Virginia and William Henry in </p>
    <p>the second. I'm the one wants to see the chil'en go to school. I sees the need of it. Charlie never went but three years; I </p>
    <p>had to stop in the fou'th reader. It was a pore chance to get to school when I growed up; it was too far to walk, and </p>
    <p>they wa'n't no time neither. The truck comes by and hauls these younguns now the seben miles to the Seaboard school. </p>
    <p>"The main reason they ain't been reg'lar is 'cause </p>
    <p>- - </p>
    <p>5681 </p>
    <p/>
    <p>they ain't had nothin' to wear. This summer I went to the Roanoke Rapids Horspital and had a bad operation. When I </p>
    <p>got home in August the doctors told me to lie around five weeks, not to lift nothin' or do no work. Soon as I could, I </p>
    <p>went to the kitchen to help Louise out. I could set at the stove, keep a fire goin', and 'tend to what was on the stove. </p>
    <p>Louise does hate cookin'. Some nights when I'd tell her it was time to make a fire to fix supper, she'd say it hadn't </p>
    <p>seemed like five minutes since she come out'n the cook room. Soon as I could half way take holt, she'd run to the </p>
    <p>woods and stay hid till supper was cooked. Louise done mighty well to be only just 'leben though. She cooked and </p>
    <p>washed and tended to the house the whole time I was gone. She could wash the everyday rags so they'd pass, but the </p>
    <p>step-out clothes was all lyin' here dirty and nobody to wash and iron 'em for the younguns to wear to school. So 'fore I </p>
    <p>got out'n the bed good, I had 'em bring me a cup tin o' water where I could set down and wash out a few pieces at the </p>
    <p>time. Then I set still and let 'em bring me a hot iron so I could fix enough clothes to start some of 'em to school. I </p>
    <p>couldn't have my younguns goin'to school dirty. They didn't have changin' clothes, that's the truth, till two of the </p>
    <p>teachers, Miss Long and Miss G-arriss, got the welfare to bring 'em 'nough </p>
    <p/>
    <p>to wear to school. </p>
    <p>"Miss Garriss is a good creetur. She's been givin' me one of her old dresses and some shoes every winter till this; she </p>
    <p>hain't sent nothin' yet. These shoes I got on is gettin' old now, but if I oan get a little strip o' leather to patch the </p>
    <p>bottoms with they'll go me another twelve months. This dress she give me I kept long as I could for step-out, but it's </p>
    <p>drawed up and faded so from the tub I had to let the hem out; they wa'n't no white thread in the house how come I to </p>
    <p>tack it up with black. It's too little round the waist now. You can see I'm swelled up; look here under my jacket. This </p>
    <p>knot that goes from my stomach clear down to my side has been here every since my operation. My sister thinks I'd </p>
    <p>ought to go back to the horspital and have a X-ray to see what it is, but I think it's my kidneys swelled up. </p>
    <p>"I ain't tellin' you no lie; it's the truth if I'm settin' here: we ain't got nothin' I Like I told the welfare when she come to </p>
    <p>see me, if you don't believe me search the house. We got three beds; three sleeps in two of 'em and four in the other. </p>
    <p>They's just two rooms, 'sides the log kitchen there at the back. That old bureau, the trunk, the chest in the hall, these </p>
    <p>chairs we're settin' on-it ain't much of a load when our stuff's movedt </p>
    <p>5683 </p>
    <p>-5- </p>
    <p/>
    <p>-? </p>
    <p>-7- </p>
    <p>give you some thin' feat sometimes. So I'm bound to say the governor has done some good. We get a little somethin' </p>
    <p>now. Last time Charlie got his slip from the relief he was allowed a sack o' flour, three pounds o' butter, a box o' </p>
    <p>prunes, and raisins. It helps, but it don't go fur enough, not with ten to feed. Jim gets seven dollars and a half from the </p>
    <p>old age pension a month. That come from the governor too, I didn't vote for him. I ain't never voted in my forty three </p>
    <p>years. I don't believe in it, not for women. It's out o' their place. Charlie ain't voted in two year. Last spring Mr. Crew </p>
    <p>come by here in his car huntin' for Charlie to go to Pleasant Hill with him and vote for Mr. Horace Ellis against Mr. </p>
    <p>Stephenson. He picked up the boys and rode round right smart lookin' for Charlie. 'Tain't no use for pore folks to vote </p>
    <p>nohow; money's goin' to carry it. My vote </p>
    <p>weighs as heavy as the rich man's? It may, but things is always worked out the way the money man says. The pore </p>
    <p>man's vote don't get him nothin'. </p>
    <p>"I don't even go to church, much less to vote. I'm ashamed to tell it, but I ain't been but once in thirteen year. That was </p>
    <p>one night last year when the meetin' was goin' on at Bethel. Charlie and all the younguns that's old enough belongs at </p>
    <p>Bethel, but I'm still a member at </p>
    <p>i)B85 </p>
    <p/>
    <p>Elam I reckon. The younguns walks the four mile to Bethel, hut the last time they come home at sunset so broke down </p>
    <p>they ain't tried it since. The reason I quit church was 'cause I didn't have nothin' fittin' to wear. </p>
    <p>"One reason we never had nothin' is 'cause so many folks we've worked for ain't treated us right. When me and Charlie </p>
    <p>got married eighteen years ago, Charlie sold out his share o' his daddy's farm, six or eight acres, to his brother Andrew. </p>
    <p>Andrew promised him if he ever wanted it back he'd sell it to him dollar for dollar. Now he says Charlie shouldn't </p>
    <p>have it for twice what he sold it for. My own daddy never owned any land, but he stayed on one place 47 years. After </p>
    <p>we was married we commenced sharecroppin' for William Cook over at G-umberry. We had six acres planted in </p>
    <p>cotton, and that year we made a bale to the acre. When the crop was in, Cook taken every one o' them six bales and </p>
    <p>left us without ary single thing. Mr. Zeno at Gumberry told Charlie he wouldn't stand for it, he'd go to law. I begged </p>
    <p>Charlie to, but he wouldn't say a hummin' word I </p>
    <p>"Then we moved to Mr. Matt's place, Dr. Stephenson's son. While we was there we got everything that was due us. </p>
    <p>Mr. Matt is dead, but I can speak my word for him; </p>
    <p>5686 </p>
    <p/>
    <p>-9- </p>
    <p>he was a good fair and square man to deal with. From Mr. </p>
    <p>Matt's we went to L. C. Cook's, William Cook's brother. </p>
    <p>Like Mr. Matt he was a fair man. He was mean to his self </p>
    <p>and to his fam'ly, but he shore paid his debts. If he </p>
    <p>owed you five cent he'd walk to your house to bring it to </p>
    <p>you. I picked cotton for him, two hund'ed and fifty and </p>
    <p>three hun'ded pounds a day along then and every Sad-d'y </p>
    <p>here come Mr. Cook to pay off in full. He's dead, but he </p>
    <p>shore was a honest man when he was livin' </p>
    <p>"Next we moved to Mr. Will Massey's. He's dead now </p>
    <p>too, but I can't speak no good word for him. We tended a </p>
    <p>one-horse like we had been doin' at the other places. All </p>
    <p>the summer we kept the farm in good shape and laid it by </p>
    <p>nice. Mr. Massey told us when we went there if we'd clean </p>
    <p>up a new ground we could have what we'd make on it the </p>
    <p>first year, and he'd give us five dollars. We dug up roots, </p>
    <p>busted up stumps, broke up the ground, and made one more </p>
    <p>big crop o' corn on that piece o' cleared land I Then Mr. </p>
    <p>Massey come down to our house and forbid us to touch the </p>
    <p>corn. The five dollars I wa'n't 'spectin' nohow, but I </p>
    <p>told Charlie the corn was mine, and I was goin' to take </p>
    <p>my sack and fill it up with roas'in'years I didn't care </p>
    <p>what Will Massey said I Do you know Charlie wouldn't le'me </p>
    <p>-get nary year? </p>
    <p>56S7 </p>
    <p/>
    <p>-10- </p>
    <p>"While we was waitin' for the cotton to open so we could house the crop, Mr. Massey's cotton opened and they started </p>
    <p>pickin'. Ours was slow a-openin', and Mr. Massey saw a way he could get us out o' our crop. He accused us o' not </p>
    <p>tendin' to our farm. So he had Sheriff J'yner come over and serve papers on us to make us move out. Sheriff said </p>
    <p>looked like we had done everything we could unless we had picked off the green bolls, and it was a mean trick to </p>
    <p>order us off, he thought. But we had to move out in September and leave all we had worked for a whole year, and I </p>
    <p>mean worked. I told Mr. Massey if he didn't mind I'd live to see the day when he'd tote his little bucket to the store for </p>
    <p>two pounds o' lard and a little piece o' meat, just like I had to do. He admitted he had treated us wrong, but he said </p>
    <p>folks had treated him wrong too. I told him that wa'n't no reason for takin' it out on us. You know I lived to see the day </p>
    <p>that Mr. Massey had to tote his little bucket to the store for a pound or two o'lard just like I had to do I I thought about </p>
    <p>what I told him, and I reckon he did too. </p>
    <p>"We moved to the Shaw place, but we couldn't stay </p>
    <p>-</p>
    <p>there. It was ha'nted. One day while I was in the hall, </p>
    <p>5688 </p>
    <p/>
    <p>-11- </p>
    <p>I heard somethin' fall like a sack o' corn from the ceilin' </p>
    <p>of the room where my baby was asleep. It woke her up and </p>
    <p>she started cryin1. I went in to see what in the world </p>
    <p>had fell. They wa'n't a thing out o' place. Then I heard </p>
    <p>-somethin' like a sack o' corn bein' drug along the floor. </p>
    <p>I grabbed the baby, run out in the yard, and wouldn't go </p>
    <p>back till Charlie come home. One night we wanted a drink </p>
    <p>o' water, and Charlie said he'd go to the well and draw </p>
    <p>a bucket o' fresh. I asked him if he wanted me to go </p>
    <p>with him. He said naw, he wa'n't afraid. I noticed he </p>
    <p>wa'n't gone long. Next mornin' he told me when he got </p>
    <p>to the well a man without a sign of head stepped up close </p>
    <p>to him. Others has seen that headless man. Nights when </p>
    <p>we'd lie down we'd hear somethin' out on the back porch </p>
    <p>go 'Oo-oo-oo-oo-oo I Oo-oo-oo-oo-oot' A colored woman </p>
    <p>who lived there 'fore we did told us it was her husband, </p>
    <p>that he made a fuss 2&amp;gt;ike that when he died on our back </p>
    <p>porch. We couldn't stay there. </p>
    <p>"Next we sharecropped with Mr. Walter Hancock, a good </p>
    <p>man. When we was there we got everything we was due. </p>
    <p>From there we went to the Woodruff house, which folks says </p>
    <p>is ha'nted. One night we made a pallet in the hall, but </p>
    <p/>
    <p>-1Pbefore </p>
    <p>we went to sleep they was a funny fuss in one of the rooms; sounded like somebody openin' a squeakin' door. I </p>
    <p>told Charlie to get up; we was goin1 over that house 'fore I was willin' to close my eyes. Not a thing was out o' place. </p>
    <p>Soon as we lay down again that same squeaky noise started. We never aaw nothin' while we stayed at the Woodruff </p>
    <p>place, but we heard plenty. </p>
    <p>"The last man we sharecropped for was Mr. Eugene Vasse*. He furnished us $15 a month from the time we </p>
    <p>started the crop till July. Then he cut off, and all we </p>
    <p>had to live on was what we could work out by the day. We went ahead and housed the crop, and Mr. Vasser sold it. </p>
    <p>We asked him for a statement of how we stood; he refused to tell us. We kept on after him about settlin' up with us till </p>
    <p>we got him fretted, and he ordered us off the place. We kept stayin' on, waitin' for a settlement. Then he had a writ </p>
    <p>served on Charlie to appear in magistrate's court. Charlie knew 'twa'n't no use to go, and didn't, but the law sent him </p>
    <p>word to get out in seven days. Since then we've lived 'bout and 'bout. I couldn't say how many times we've moved- </p>
    <p>right smart I know. Last year we come here to farm with Mr. Crew, but got knocked out o' that. So this makes five </p>
    <p>year we ain't farmed none." </p>
    <p>suee </p>
    <p/>
    <p>In the pause while Dona adjusts the dirty slat bonnet on her head, Charlie Male drawls in a flat monotone his estimate </p>
    <p>of mankind, Charlie-with thin reddish hair, watery blue eyes, a pasty face devoid of animation- states his case as a </p>
    <p>matter of fact, without resentment. </p>
    <p>"I've had dealings with a lot o'men. Two thirds of 'em is crooked. They's a few good men, but in business most of 'em </p>
    <p>takes advantage. After we lost out a-share-croppin' five year ago, I begin to cut pulk wood all th'ugh the country. It's </p>
    <p>the hardest work in the world. If you get anything done it means you got to go to the woods early and stay late, </p>
    <p>'specially when the days shortens. I've cut more pulk wood than any man in the state. I reckon I've walked more miles </p>
    <p>than any man. They use to call me the fastest walker in the country, but gradually I've slowed down some. I had to </p>
    <p>buy me a bicycle to get about on. We never had no car. </p>
    <p>"Me and the boys makes about five dollars a week cuttin' pulk wood. Durin' November and December we cut for </p>
    <p>Eugene Yasser here close to Jack Swamp. We told him 'stead o' payin' us by the week we wanted it all in a lump sum </p>
    <p>just 'fore Christmas. We knowed if it come in by dribbles it'd get away from us, and we wanted some clothes and a </p>
    <p>little money to spend for Christmas. Just </p>
    <p/>
    <p>-14- </p>
    <p>before Christmas, we went to Mr. Vasser and asked him to square up; he owed us |J5* He said he wa'n't goinf to pay </p>
    <p>us; he never give no reason. So it meant two months o' hard work come to nothin'." </p>
    <p>"It meant we had not nary thing for Christmas Day but a hoe-cake o' corn bread, that's what it meant I" Dona </p>
    <p>exclaims. "And it meant my baby had to wake up Christmas mornin' and find no Santy Claus here. Clayra Virginia </p>
    <p>come home from school on Friday and said Santy Claus come to their room that evenin' and told 'em he'd bring all the </p>
    <p>little girls and boys whatever they was mint to ask for. She asked Santy for a big doll and a tricycle? I told Clayra </p>
    <p>Virginia you had to pay Santy for him to come to see you. 'No, you don't, mammy,' she said, 'He told us all we had to </p>
    <p>do was ask for what we wanted.' </p>
    <p>"One of the younguns got this little Santy Claus," Dona reaches to the mantel for a miniature plaster paris Santa with </p>
    <p>an empty bag, "off'n the Christmas tree one year at school. Clayra Virginia wanted it took off'n the mantel-piece and </p>
    <p>hid, 'cause one of the boys told her if sure-'nough Santy come and saw another one here he'd go back and not leave </p>
    <p>nothin'. 'Mammy,' she said to me 'fore she went to sleep, 'don't forget to hide that </p>
    <p>5692 </p>
    <p/>
    <p>-15- </p>
    <p>Santy on the mantel.' </p>
    <p>"Next mornin' when she woke up she looked all around the room for a doll and tricycle. She really thought it was goin' </p>
    <p>to be here. I couldn't help water comin' in my eyes when I saw how put out she was. </p>
    <p>"It takes every bit o' what Charlie can make cuttin' wood to go on the table. Most time it means just bread, no meat. </p>
    <p>Charlie sowed a few turnips, but he didn't have nothin' to 'nurse 'em with; so the turnips failed this year. If I hadn't </p>
    <p>been sick, I'd o' scraped me up some 'nure from somewhere, if out'n the road. I always raise a gyarden when I'm up </p>
    <p>and about. This summer 'fore I went to the horspital my butter bean vines was mighty green and pretty. I'd hear folks </p>
    <p>passin' 'iong the road say: 'Look a-yonder. She ain't had a bug on her vines this year, and they've pure eat mine up. </p>
    <p>That's what I call luck.' I wanted to hollder back: 'Yen, if you'd had as many backaches as I've had, your vines'd be </p>
    <p>green too.' I had bugs all right, but I kept 'em picked off; I had to, 'cause I didn't have no pizen to put on the vines like </p>
    <p>other folks. </p>
    <p>"We got a few chickens still, no pigs, no cow-I wouldn't have a cow, not for my part. When I was in the </p>
    <p>. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>horspital, Dr. Jarman would ask me every day if I was i'arin' all right. Finally I told him I was gettin' plenty o' vittles, </p>
    <p>but I couldn't eat 'em unless they left out the butter and milk. He turned to the nurse and told her to see to it that I had </p>
    <p>vittles fixed the way I liked it. Next day the stuff still had milk and butter in it. Some of the others told me they'd </p>
    <p>raise the devil if they was me, but I said I didn't go to the horspital to have no argue with 'em. I can't stand milk and </p>
    <p>butter on nothin'. The younguns likes it all right if they could get it. Charlie does buy 'em a can o' milk sometimes. </p>
    <p>"Even my collards failed me this year, the first year I been without greens to boil. Some days when we get burned up </p>
    <p>with bread, I go up to the collard patch and hunt around till I find some collard stalks and a few buds and green leaves; </p>
    <p>then I come home and make us a pot o' soup. 1 told 'em all the other day the hogs wouldn't pick over what I found to </p>
    <p>make a meal out fn. They's a sayin': 'Little goat, if you are able, Please bring me my little table.' I tell 'em my gyarden </p>
    <p>has well been the little goat here. </p>
    <p>"The boys thought they would have 'em a little extry money for Christmas; so they caught 'em four 'possums </p>
    <p/>
    <p>and sent the skins to a fur house up north. A check come for twenty cent, five cent a 'possum, and now nobody won't </p>
    <p>cash that check. They're dryin' more 'possum skins now, but it shore is disheartenin' at five cent apiece. </p>
    <p>"Ne'er mind! When the lizard crawls again I'll be with 'eml" ^ona laughs, and her face is transformed by the sudden </p>
    <p>animation and spirit. "When it's warm enough for lizards and snakes to crawl I'll get out and start atain too. I ain't </p>
    <p>afraid o'work. Hard work is my pleasure. Mr. Hancock told me one time I was tougher'n any mule that brayed, don't I'd </p>
    <p>done been under the clods. I've done some o' every kind o' work a man ever done except ditchin'. I've cut pulk wood, </p>
    <p>I've busted middles-I admit I never could run rows, but after they is laid off I can plow good as a man-I've cut and </p>
    <p>penned cord wood, hoed, picked cotton, shook peas, cleaned up new ground, shrubbed land-you can't name nothin' I </p>
    <p>ain't done some of. </p>
    <p>"If you had come last summer 'fore I got sick you wouldn't believe this is the same place. I had pretty flowers growin' </p>
    <p>in the yard. Folks would pass by and say it was the prettiest yard along the road. It ain't been swept but once since </p>
    <p>June. We're leavin' the house </p>
    <p/>
    <p>-18- </p>
    <p>and yard in bad shape for the next ones that moves in here, but that's the way we found it. Where we go we'll find a </p>
    <p>mess; so I just well to save myself to clean up there. No since in breakin' myself down on this old house, weak as I </p>
    <p>still am from my operation. Some of 'em said soon as I come from the horspital I would kill myself workin', but I told </p>
    <p>'em naw, 1 was goin' to set on it. And I have tried to favor myself all I could. </p>
    <p>"These cracks in the floor gets so cold sometimes I stuffs rags in 'em to keep my feet from freezin'. I don't want no </p>
    <p>pneumonia here. Except for my operation, we've had right good health lately. Thomas Jefferson use to have fits, but he </p>
    <p>outgrowed 'em. My two twins had some kind o' spells-what'd the doctor call 'em, Charlie? Yen, that's right, </p>
    <p>conjustions. I think it was spasms. They'd get stiff as a board when the fits'd take 'em and then limp as a dish rag. I </p>
    <p>set with Clayra Virginia on one arm and William Henry on the other a many a night till my arms would ache off </p>
    <p>near'bout. Last one William Henry had was here last summer. Dr. Vick come once and give 'em some big white tablets </p>
    <p>to swallow without any water. He said soon as I saw a fit comin' on to make 'em swallow a pill, dry. But I was afraid </p>
    <p>it would choke my babies; so I melted the tablets </p>
    <p>5696 </p>
    <p/>
    <p>-6- </p>
    <p>I'm tellin' it just like it is: we ain't got nothin'." </p>
    <p>The two iron beds are covered with dirty guilts Ragged old coats are stretched over the lower sashes of the windows. </p>
    <p>The floor, in which big cracks admit damp air from under the house, is stained with grease spots and snuff-dipping. </p>
    <p>Flies swarm around two green 'possum hides that hang in the hall. A stench of unwashed bodies, tobacco juice burned </p>
    <p>on dog-irons, rats' nests, squalor is over all. </p>
    <p>"Back yonder when the dispression was on, we was in a wus' fix than we is now. We didn't have a rag o' clothes, </p>
    <p>nothin' to eat, no mattress to sleep on. I went in the fields, got hay grass, and covered it with gayno bags for us to lie </p>
    <p>on. Mrs. Ramsey was the welfare then, and she was one good woman. When she come and saw the fix we was in, she </p>
    <p>brought us mattresses, bed quilts, clothes, and boxes o' food. My two little twins was babies then, and she fitted them </p>
    <p>out in nice clothes. I hated it when she lost her job; looked like nobody couldn't done no better than Mrs. Ramsey. </p>
    <p>"Do pray don't get Hoover back in I It was 'eat and wear if you can' when he was there. I don't know nothin' 'bout the </p>
    <p>man that's in now; he may be all right; he does </p>
    <p>r - </p>
    <p>584 </p>
    <p/>
    <p>-19- </p>
    <p>in some water and let 'em take it that way. 'TwAi't nothin' but asfidity nohow. We don't have the doctor here. They's </p>
    <p>nothin' to pay with; so what's the use to send for him? All we can do when we get sick is to tough it out best we can. </p>
    <p>I've really suffered for the doctor since I come back from the horspital, more'n once. </p>
    <p>"We don't go nowheres. The boys hunts and gets to a picture show once 'n awhile. I been to one in my life and liked it </p>
    <p>fine. Hard work is my pleasure. I go to see my sisters sometimes, but they're scattered round so bad it's unconvenient </p>
    <p>for me to get to 'em often. Louise stays over in Halifax County, the one that married June Harlow. Louise couldn't stay </p>
    <p>with her first husband. June had been a-courtin' of her some time when she fell in love with another feller and married </p>
    <p>hinu June said to her the day she was married: 'All right, you can ride gaily to-day, but before a year's gone you'll be </p>
    <p>brought back to your daddy's door.' Shore 'nough she was. 'Twa'n't long after she was married she taken bad off. </p>
    <p>Nothin' they done wa'n't no good. Finally she got so low they put her bed on a wagon and brought her back to her </p>
    <p>daddy's, just like June said. </p>
    <p>"One day June Harlow come in to see Louise and told </p>
    <p>5637 </p>
    <p/>
    <p>-20- </p>
    <p>her if she'd marry him she would shore get well. Louise said she'd do anything to get her health back. June went in the </p>
    <p>field, dug up nine little marvels, and brought 'em in to Louise. 'Here's the conjure,' he told her. 'This is what's been </p>
    <p>your trouble. Somebody buried these little marvels, and you never would o' got no better if I hadn't found 'em.' She </p>
    <p>married him after she saw she couldn't live with her other husband. </p>
    <p>"My brother's wife was conjured one time too. A woman come to her house to borry some meal. While my brother's </p>
    <p>wife was out gettin' the meal, the woman slipped some wads o' paper in between the slats of her bonnet. My brother's </p>
    <p>wife got bad off and had to go to a conjure doctor. He told her where to find the conjure and warned her never to borry </p>
    <p>or lend anything to that woman no more. Tou know if it hadn't been so, the doctor wouldn't known nothin' 'bout that </p>
    <p>wad o' paper in the bonnet." </p>
    <p>"They's a feller down the road-Alvin Garrison's his </p>
    <p>name- that's in a terrible shape right now from bein' </p>
    <p> conjured," Charlie asserts mildly. "Isaac Mayo, a </p>
    <p>colored man, had a spite at old man Garrison some years </p>
    <p>ago and conjured Alvin. He got wild, tore his clothes </p>
    <p>off'n hisself, and was in a rage. One day when Isaac </p>
    <p>come to shave Mr. Garrison, he patted Alvin on the head </p>
    <p>[&amp;gt;B!&amp;gt;8 </p>
    <p/>
    <p>-21- </p>
    <p>and said: 'You been tearin' your clothes and ragin' long enough now.' Alvin got all right for awhile. Since then Isaac </p>
    <p>has conjured him again and put him back right where he was. Alvin is so wild they aimed to take him to the insane </p>
    <p>asylum in Raleigh yesterday, but they didn't get off. I believe in conjurin'; they is such a thing." </p>
    <p>Dona follows the visitor into the front yard and confides: "I didn't tell you in there, but they took all my female organs </p>
    <p>out at the Rapids this summer. I got in the horspital th'ugh my son James; he was born five years before I was </p>
    <p>married. James works in the mill, and he paid for my operation* </p>
    <p>"This yard looks like the buzzards has had it, but you wait: When the lizard crawls again, I'll come out J" </p>
    <p>LE </p>
    <p/>
    <p>5699 </p>
    <p/>
  </text>
</history>
