<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../lifehistory.xsl" ?>
<history>
  <title>Greek Food</title>
  <reflink>https://dc.lib.unc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/03709/id/1106</reflink>
  <meta>
    <item>
      <key>Date</key>
      <val>1939-09-26</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Location</key>
      <val>Charlotte, North Carolina</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Writer</key>
      <val>Frank B. Rupert (white; male)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Reviser</key>
      <val>Dudley W. Crawford (white; male)</val>
    </item>
  </meta>
  <text>
    <p>September 26, 1939</p>
    <p>Charlotte Greek Study</p>
    <p>Frank B. Rupert, Writer</p>
    <p>Dudley W. Crawford, Reviser</p>
    <p>GREEK FOOD</p>
    <p>While the average Greek restaurant in Charlotte wisely eaters to the taste of their American patrons, serving steaks; ham, prepared in various styles; per-colated coffee, even has and eggs, and sandwiches; they give free rein to their native appetites in their homes and other places where their own people are to partake.</p>
    <p>Barbecue lamb Is perhaps the favorite dish. Baked chicken with a rich sauce called Kapasa, is a close second choice Kapama is a combination of tomato and much seasoning. The chicken is simmered or smothered under cover until tender, and the Kapama used often with the addition of various vegetables.</p>
    <p>American lard and substitute compounds are not regarded favorably; the native Greek cook uses only butter and olive oil in the preparation of their very special dishes, the oil being imported.</p>
    <p>Cheese is very popular and a variety called Feta, made of goat's milk, is most frequently used in a Greek household.</p>
    <p>Combination salads, anchovies and ripe olives find conspicuous place on the daily menu and even spaghetti, cooked tender in salt water and served with a side dish of grated Parmesian cheese, is a general favorite.</p>
    <p>The usual hot and zesty seasoning found in most Greek food preparations give it a characteristic all of its own, and Greek cooks are Justly proud of this oulinary ability.</p>
    <p>The coffee must be ground to a powder and boiled until a certain amount of rich sediment settles in the bottom of the cup, and with this is served, for unexpected company, a small and delicious rich cake called Kouramble.</p>
    <p>Wines of many varieties are a conspicuous adjunct of every meat Mastioa and Retsina are light wines for lunch and supper, (the Mastioa requiring a goodly portion of water mixed with it.)</p>
    <p>And a favorite with the men guests is always Metaxas, a cognac brandy of rich and tasty quality.</p>
    <p>Loaf bread is very important too. Long loaves shaped pumpernickel but made of wheat instead of rye are out in thick slices and piled high on the bread dish.</p>
    <p>Foods most preferred by the Greeks may be termed, rich, substantial and tasty; served in combinations which assure a well balanced diet.</p>
  </text>
</history>
