<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../lifehistory.xsl" ?>
<history>
  <title>Facing Ahead</title>
  <reflink>https://dc.lib.unc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/03709/id/519</reflink>
  <meta>
    <item>
      <key>Date</key>
      <val>1939-08-29</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Location</key>
      <val>Carrboro, North Carolina</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Occupations</key>
      <val>mechanic</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Interviewee</key>
      <val>Anthony Gibbs (white; male)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Writer</key>
      <val>William O. Foster (white; male)</val>
    </item>
  </meta>
  <text>
    <p>Carrboro, North Carolina</p>
    <p>August 29, 1939</p>
    <p>William O.Foster</p>
    <p/>
    <p>Anthony Gibbs</p>
    <p>Facing Ahead</p>
    <p/>
    <p/>
    <p>" I don't know anything but mechanics," Anthony Gibbs told me.</p>
    <p>We were standing in his garage on the main street in Carrboro , North Carolina.</p>
    <p>His garage is an L-shaped hull, with a long room extending back from the street</p>
    <p>and a shorter addition at the rear. The tin roof radiated the heat of the summer</p>
    <p>sun and one window and two doo double doors offered the only ventillation.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Have a seat over there on the keg. It's the best chair I've got. I've got some</p>
    <p>idle time while my assistant finishes a job out in front. We don't keep chairs</p>
    <p>here because if we did there would be a crowd of loafers here all the time. This</p>
    <p>is a work place and not a social club. Don't get me wrong. You are a writin' man</p>
    <p>and if you can help the rich and the eddicated folks to understand the condition</p>
    <p>of us pore , ignorant fellows I ought to give you a little of my time. You are</p>
    <p>the fust writin' man that ever steeped in here.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I'm glad to howdy with my friends who drop in friendly like. And my customers</p>
    <p>are ever more welcome. But the loafers around town hang out at the barber shops</p>
    <p>and the filling-stations. Lots of my customers prefer to loaf in them places</p>
    <p>while I am working on their cars. They get places to sit there and listen over</p>
    <p>the radio or mingle with the crowds. Lots of my customers stay at the Standard</p>
    <p>filling-station across the street and then they feel like they love to buy gas</p>
    <p>over there. I'd rather they passed the time of day down at the barber-shop across</p>
    <p>the rail road tracks because then man or I could sell them gas too. I bet you'll</p>
    <p>think I'm Scotch but a feller has to live as well as let live. I'm really not very</p>
    <p>greedy. I never hope to git rich. Don't want to be rich. Jist want enough to keep</p>
    <p>off of poverty's row.* I've seen so much poverty around this town that I have to</p>
    <p>think I might be dependent on charity when I can't work. I jist want my share of</p>
    <p>the business.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I'll bet you never seed a mechanic working like I do at the age of 64. But I'm</p>
    <p>going strong and expect to work ten or fifteen years more. Factories won't hire</p>
    <p>a man over forty and they takes every opportunity to ease out their older workers.</p>
    <p>Don't see how anybody can fire me 'cause I owns my own business. My assistant is</p>
    <p>only thirty but he says I can do as much work as he can."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Tell me about your boyhood and family."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Well, I wuz born on the farm a few miles from here. In them days there was a</p>
    <p>lot of work to be done. Everybody had big families and my brothers were about</p>
    <p>all sisters. There wuz twelve of us children and ten of them wuz girls. I came</p>
    <p>along in the middle and my brother wuz the baby. They put me to work so early I</p>
    <p>can't remember when I started. With all them girls on his hands Dad had to hustle</p>
    <p>and make me hustle too.</p>
    <p>" Did I go to school ? Wall, yes and no; mostly no. I remember Dad buying me a</p>
    <p>slate and pencil and sending me along with the girls when I was six. I got</p>
    <p>exposed to eddication along with measles, whoopin' cough, mumps, scarlet fever,</p>
    <p>I got a little out of my sums but they tried to keep me off of that 'till I could</p>
    <p>learn my a, b, c's and learn to read and spell. I tried a little but I wuzn't</p>
    <p>interested. Did you ever try to do anything you wuzn't interested in ? It's a</p>
    <p>uphill proposition to be sure. I'd play hooky and never show up most of the time.</p>
    <p>Other days I'd stay out on the playground when they called 'books.' The teacher</p>
    <p>made me stay in so's I'd study; and she told Dad too. Dad whipped me but nothin'</p>
    <p>did no good and I can't read yet. I didn't seem to have no incline in the</p>
    <p>direction of books. Don't know whether I could have learned or not but Miss</p>
    <p>Venable, my old teacher, said says that anybody who could can tear a car down</p>
    <p>and put it back together could learn books if he tried. But I figgers that if a</p>
    <p>little boy is as sot against books as I wuz , his thinker is jist weak on that</p>
    <p>side. O , I reckon I could er learned a little mite but it would likely have</p>
    <p>taken me twice as long to pass a grade as it took others. I jist won't cut out</p>
    <p>for a book-man. I think with my hand and fingers. My mind all runs to figgerin'</p>
    <p>on how to make things go. Anyhow the teacher told my folks that they could lead</p>
    <p>a horse to water but couldn't make him drink and that they had best take me home.</p>
    <p>Dad tried to keep me there longer. Said he never learned readin' and writin' and</p>
    <p>he was determined that all his kids would succeed where he failed. He said to</p>
    <p>me, 'Boy, unless you can read what's in books and papers yore mind will be</p>
    <p>pretty nigh a blank and if you don't go to school now you will be so big you'll</p>
    <p>be ashamed to go; I'm a goin' to put some sense into yore head if I have to beat</p>
    <p>it into you.' He meant it too. He pourd it on hard. But I jist got stiff and</p>
    <p>laid down. His switch hurt but I couldn't cry. I jist lay there and shook. Ma</p>
    <p>got so sorry for me she held Dad's arm and begged him to let up. Finally he</p>
    <p>said, 'All right boy; you can quit school but I'll see that you regret it 'cause</p>
    <p> im a goin' to make you git up at four and work till dark, 'cept when it rains.</p>
    <p> You got to work in the house and out of the house. If you don't want to be a</p>
    <p> larnin' man you can be a workin' man. Boy, you'r goin' g to work and im tellin'</p>
    <p> you.'</p>
    <p/>
    <p>" He made me work all right but he softened up a little after he cooled off and</p>
    <p>after he saw how sleepy and tired I got. He let me sleep 'till sun up and I got</p>
    <p>to play some in the afternoons. In fact Ma bossed me most of the time when I wuz</p>
    <p>a little fellow. I helped her wash dished, churn and bring in wood. But as I</p>
    <p>began to grow bigger Dad gradually put me to work with him. I did the chores,</p>
    <p>then chopped and at twelve I began to plow.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I began to handle tools a little at ten and by the time I was thirteen Dad saw</p>
    <p>I had a gift. He encouraged me and got me a workshop and tools of different</p>
    <p>kinds. When I was fifteen he said, 'Boy you hve paid for those tools over and</p>
    <p>over by your use of 'em . I'm goin to let you do all the repair work on the</p>
    <p>place, Hit'll save me money.'</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"That jist suited me, I wuz strong and didn't mind field work but I was tickled</p>
    <p>to death when I got into my shop. By the time I was eighteen, the neigbors wuz</p>
    <p>bringin' me their work. I charged them jist what Dad would er paid for some one</p>
    <p>to go to the field and work by the hour in my place. Dad said I should have</p>
    <p>charged them twice as much but I told him that I wanted to keep 'em er comin' so</p>
    <p>I could keep busy most of the time 'er doin' what I loved ter do.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Finally" at last when I wuz twenty-one I told Dad I wuz goin' to strike out for</p>
    <p>myself and keep all I made. I'd been givin' him all I made. He would take me</p>
    <p>to town and git my clothes and he give me the small amount of spendin' money</p>
    <p>that the young fellers usually had in them days. He said, "Boy, you is yore own</p>
    <p>man now and you can do as you please. I know you will want to go to some town</p>
    <p>where people can find you easy like. But this house is yore house as often as</p>
    <p>you like to come back. I know you will do hard, honest work and charge fair.</p>
    <p>Watch yore credit or they'll git you down shore as you live. Be a good boy.</p>
    <p>Run with a good bunch. Go to church. You can't read yore Bible but take it along</p>
    <p>to look at so it will remind you to pray. You don't know nothing, so don't talk</p>
    <p>too much. Many a feller has kept himself out of trouble by jist sayin' nothing.</p>
    <p>Mind yore own business and let others mind their'n . when it's time to talk</p>
    <p>think straight and say it right out.'</p>
    <p/>
    <p>Dad warn't no preacher but as I look back on it at sixty-four them was good</p>
    <p>words of advice. I knew Dad as a level-headed, Christian man and I tried to</p>
    <p>foller the path he pointed to. I knew he had his hands full even if he had</p>
    <p>paid for his little farm. So when I started my shop in Chapel Hill, I did all</p>
    <p>his work free. I jist charged him what I had to buy to fix his repairs. I also</p>
    <p>helped him buy machinery and send him money. Dad and Mom is both dead now and</p>
    <p>it warms me up a heap to remember that I acted to 'em like a true son.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I had met Sarah Martin and had fallen desperately in love with her. We both</p>
    <p>joined the Methodist church and I took her to every service 'cept prayer</p>
    <p>meetin'. I wuz for marryin' right now but she said, "Anthony, you musn't rush</p>
    <p>me off er my feet. I likes you a heap but my folks say we ought ter wait 'till</p>
    <p>we knows eachother better.' I guess her folks must er looked me up or else they</p>
    <p>saw I wuz a stiddy worker and wuz makin' good. Anyhow after six months they let</p>
    <p>up and we got married.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I've got eight children now. They came in stair-step fashion, one every year</p>
    <p>and a half to two and a half years. You writin' people from Chapel Hill talk a</p>
    <p>lot about spacin' of children and limiting the number; but we never knew there</p>
    <p>was sich a critter as birth-control. We jist let nature take her course. It's</p>
    <p>hard on the mothers and I reckon that's how come so many men married twice and</p>
    <p>selected sich young wives. And havin' so many of them may possibly 'count for</p>
    <p>the fact that so many children died when they were little. I guess though that</p>
    <p>the doctors know more about children now. I'm shore there ain't so many second</p>
    <p>marriages now. I'll bet there is more widows today than widdowers. I wuz lucky</p>
    <p>in that my wife was strong. We lost one baby from dyptheria but the rest came</p>
    <p>through and their mother is hale and hearty. My wife and I say we don't believe</p>
    <p>in birth-control. Still we ain't urging our children to have babies every two</p>
    <p>years; holdin' down the birth-rate seems to make our grand-children strong and</p>
    <p>their families can do more. For a few than they can for fer a great crowd.</p>
    <p>Our daughters and ours sons' wives certainly have an easier time and get more</p>
    <p>out of life than wife did. I reckon I better let theses younger couples decide</p>
    <p>for themselves how many children they want; I don't know much about it and they</p>
    <p>don't ask my idea no how. My children and grand-children all live close enough</p>
    <p>to come to see us often.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"We moved out here to Carrboro about the time the auto came along. It wuz</p>
    <p>cheaper to live out here. I tore down the first model T Ford that come to these</p>
    <p> parts. I wuz crazy to get my hands on that new fangled machine. The boys told</p>
    <p> me I'd better not mess with something I couldn't handle. That made me boil. I</p>
    <p> said, 'Fellers , I am smart enough to repair and put together any machine that</p>
    <p> I take apart; I may not be smart enough to build 'em but I can repair anything</p>
    <p> that another man builds.' Well, I convinced 'em . I soon had that car running</p>
    <p> like a top.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"As cars grew more common, I gave up my general repair work and for years I've</p>
    <p>been nothing but an automobile mechanic. My assistant keeps the books and I</p>
    <p>know how to make change. I s'pose it seems queer to you white collar folks that</p>
    <p>I prefer to be under this hot roof in a greasy pair of overalls to sitting in an</p>
    <p>office. But there isn't any music as sweet to me as listenin' to my tools</p>
    <p>hammering on some old stubborn car and forcing it ter run again. I've made good</p>
    <p>here in a small way. I do a little credit business but most of 'em pays up so I</p>
    <p>won't drop 'em . I own this business and four houses in Carrboro. I've stuck to</p>
    <p>my anvil. My work stands up. And I don't overcharge. If it takes only ten</p>
    <p>minutes to fix a car I don't charge a cent. I've got a lot of friends in</p>
    <p>Carrboro and the whole county around here.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I'm a plain man but I'm sober. I pay my debts. I go to church every service. I</p>
    <p>attend most of the programs put on for the public like parent-teachers,</p>
    <p>Children's Day in the churches, and graduatin' programs. I bought liberty bonds</p>
    <p>in the Wold War and I may be buying them again in a few weeks if the war starts up.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I'm a voter too. I'm a New Deal Democrat. I don't like the President's beer</p>
    <p>parties but he's the people's friend. The banks are safe and it looks like he's</p>
    <p>stopped depressions. He is trying to keep Europe from war and if it comes he'll</p>
    <p>keep us out. I'm glad I'm an American. God has been good to me and I've just</p>
    <p>gotten started. I'm not facing back. I'm looking forward to better days. "</p>
    <p/>
    <p/>
    <p>Facing Ahead - N.C. - Good 180</p>
    <p/>
    <p>Auto-mechanic, age 64 - owns his own shop - employs one assistant - Also owns</p>
    <p>four houses - born on farm - refused at early age to go to school - never</p>
    <p>learned to read - began to do repair work at ten - has never done anything else</p>
    <p>- eigh children - doesn't believe in birth control - keeps up - seems to be a</p>
    <p>good, right thinking American - believes in New Deal government - Doesn't want</p>
    <p>to get rich - looking ahead.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>Comment - Interesting for the light it sheds on educational matters - it</p>
    <p>presents a good plea for vocational training for the boy who will not or can</p>
    <p>not learn - </p>
  </text>
</history>
