<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../lifehistory.xsl" ?>
<history>
  <title>Contracting the Mails</title>
  <reflink>https://dc.lib.unc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/03709/id/318</reflink>
  <meta>
    <item>
      <key>Date</key>
      <val>1939-02-08</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Location</key>
      <val>New Bern, North Carolina</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Occupations</key>
      <val>mail carrier</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Interviewee</key>
      <val>Thermond Bennett (white; male)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Writer</key>
      <val>Mary M. Philips (white; female)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Reviser</key>
      <val>Edwin Massengill (white; male)</val>
    </item>
  </meta>
  <text>
    <p>Date of first writing: February 8, 1939</p>
    <p>Person interviewed: Thermond Bennett</p>
    <p>Address: New Bern, N. C.</p>
    <p>Occupation: Mail Carrier</p>
    <p>Writer: Mary M. Phillips, New Bern, N. C.</p>
    <p>Reviser: Edwin Massengill</p>
    <p>No. of words: About 3,000</p>
    <p/>
    <p>CONTRACTING THE MAILS	</p>
    <p/>
    <p>For three years now I have carried the mail, and</p>
    <p>I have to go six days a week, rain or shine. I still say,</p>
    <p>however, that it is the easiest job I ever had. I hope that</p>
    <p>before my time runs out a law will be passed making it a</p>
    <p>permanent job instead of a contract going to the lowest</p>
    <p>bidder every four years. It is funny now, but I didn't</p>
    <p>want the job when I first got the chance of it. I had</p>
    <p>always stayed around my home town, and I had always been</p>
    <p>able to get a job of some kind.</p>
    <p>I took the place of a friend of mine who quit</p>
    <p>because of trouble with his wife. You see, he was running</p>
    <p>around with another man's wife, and his wife just pulled</p>
    <p>out. Then he give up his job. I made a bid for the contract</p>
    <p>and got it. I had to raise a sixteen thousand dollar bond,</p>
    <p>but that was not so much trouble.</p>
    <p>Before it come time to take the job, our boy was</p>
    <p>born. The baby was not well and just lived twenty-seven days.</p>
    <p>We were both hurt mighty bad, but I got along better than</p>
    <p>my wife did, as I could get out and work and forget about it.</p>
    <p>My contract had called for ninety miles but when</p>
    <p>we got here we found that it was nearer ninety-two miles.</p>
    <p>I stayed a week to help I Perey, the fellow I got to help me,</p>
    <p>learn the route and post offices. At that time there was</p>
    <p>eleven stops but two were cut off in a little while after I</p>
    <p>got the job. Some of these post offices were in stores;</p>
    <p>some, in filling stations; and some, in separate buildings.</p>
    <p>After I thought that Perey knowed the offices all right I</p>
    <p>went back to work on my old lumber truck. That was work</p>
    <p>that I knowed something about and liked.</p>
    <p>My daddy was a farmer and made a good living, but</p>
    <p>we never had much money. He didn't own his land and moved</p>
    <p>around so much that Mama used to tell him that every time</p>
    <p>the chickens heard a wagon they would set down in the yard</p>
    <p>and cross their legs to be tied.</p>
    <p>I was the oldest one of the crop, and there was a</p>
    <p>big crowd of we children. The one next to me was a boy, too,</p>
    <p>and he married my wife's sister. They have parted and gone</p>
    <p>back together so many times that I can't remember the number.</p>
    <p>They have three children now. I wish they would give me the</p>
    <p>oldest boy, for I love him better than anything I ever saw,</p>
    <p>I do believe. I reckon he loves me as much as I do him, and</p>
    <p>he'd stay with me, too, if they would let him. My brother</p>
    <p>works with the WPA.</p>
    <p>My oldest sister works in a beauty shop, and the</p>
    <p>next girl works in a hosiery mill. She must make good money</p>
    <p>for she wears pretty clothes, but she always says that she</p>
    <p>don't have any money to give Mama to help the other girls.</p>
    <p>My other sister keeps house for a man in my home town. She</p>
    <p>would be pretty if she won't so fat. She's not got a bit of</p>
    <p>shape. The next one stays home and helps with the work. She</p>
    <p>can plow as good as a man, and she had rather work in the</p>
    <p>field than in the house. She is about to get married now.</p>
    <p>The youngest girl is going to school, and she says she is</p>
    <p>going to leave just as soon as she finishes school. The</p>
    <p>youngest child is a boy. That youngun has been humored and</p>
    <p>petted so much that he is rotten. He gets anything he wants</p>
    <p>and does just like he pleases.</p>
    <p>I can't say anything about other people being</p>
    <p>mischievous as many scrapes as I got in. The pupils in</p>
    <p>school called me "Little Caesar" because I was such a bully.</p>
    <p>It was mostly bluff, but it didn't make any difference as</p>
    <p>long as it worked. In the wintertime we would roll up</p>
    <p>snowballs and, I mean, it really snows up in them hills.</p>
    <p>These balls would be as big as a barn and would be filled</p>
    <p>with sticks and rocks. Then long after the snow had</p>
    <p>melted everywhere else these piles of snow would be standing</p>
    <p>in the schoolyard.</p>
    <p>I had a little trouble in school once which I have</p>
    <p>never forgotten. I hit a boy in the head with a rock and the</p>
    <p>teacher wanted to whip me. I told her I'd hit her if she</p>
    <p>tried it and went home, but my dad sent me back the next</p>
    <p>day.</p>
    <p>I always have liked to drive, trucks or cars, it</p>
    <p>didn't make no difference, and I started to drive when I</p>
    <p>was about twelve years old. At that time an old doctor had</p>
    <p>the only car in the whole county, and it was the only one</p>
    <p>I had seen. He kept it in the barn, for people didn't have</p>
    <p>garages then. I stayed with his son one Saturday night, and</p>
    <p>when we got up next morning he had gone off on horseback and</p>
    <p>left work for us to go up on the mountain and salt the cattle.</p>
    <p>We pushed the car out of the barn, for neither one</p>
    <p>of us had ever driv any and we didn't want to tear the</p>
    <p>barn down. After we got the car in the yard we started to</p>
    <p>cranking on it. It seemed like we cranked three days, but</p>
    <p>by and by we got it started. Up the mountain we went, and we</p>
    <p>got along fine, from then on, I driv right much for the old</p>
    <p>man, every chance I got.</p>
    <p>I finished high school when I was eighteen. I</p>
    <p>reckon the teachers just got tired of having me around, so</p>
    <p>they let me pass. I sure didn't know enough to quit school.</p>
    <p>An soon as I got through school, one of the richest</p>
    <p>men in the county give me a job in his hardware store. Papa</p>
    <p>wanted me to help him on the farm, but I felt like I had to</p>
    <p>be out where I could see different people. I worked there for</p>
    <p>a long time--two years or more--then I was put on a truck. I</p>
    <p>went to all the surrounding towns, getting things to be used</p>
    <p>in the store and hauling different articles from one place to</p>
    <p>another.</p>
    <p>T don't see how I have managed to drive as long as</p>
    <p>I have and as fast as I always do without getting killed or</p>
    <p>killing somebody. One day I was driving a big International</p>
    <p>truck loaded with lumber. I went around a curve and sailed</p>
    <p>right into a whole herd of cattle. Cows and lumber was</p>
    <p>scrambled all over the road and all over the running board and</p>
    <p>even up on the hood. Three of the cows got killed, and one</p>
    <p>get a leg broke and had to be shot. In a little while the</p>
    <p>man that owned the cows come up. He had a fit; he ripped</p>
    <p>and cussed. He swore that he would sue the company I worked</p>
    <p>for. He knowed better than that for there is a law up there</p>
    <p>that say that the person walking in front and behind of a</p>
    <p>herd of cattle must wave a red flag. The man just lost his</p>
    <p>cows, for he was too stingy to hire any help. Anyway, it</p>
    <p>cost me nearly $100 to fix the truck. I have certainly had</p>
    <p>a lot of narrow escapes. </p>
    <p>Now, all our time won't spent in drinking and</p>
    <p>hunting for something to drink when I was young. We had a</p>
    <p>lot of fun. Most everybody in the mountains could fiddle,</p>
    <p>pick a banjo or a guitar, or blow a harp. Crowds would get</p>
    <p>together and would play and sing pretty near all night. It</p>
    <p>won't no trouble to get up a dance, and the old folks could</p>
    <p>dance as good as the young people. I have been to a square</p>
    <p>dance and got home just in time to change my clothes and get</p>
    <p>to work. I didn't mind it then. We used to have bakes up</p>
    <p>on the Mountain. For a long time they were stag parties</p>
    <p>and wild parties. Now all the women go the same as the men.</p>
    <p>There was three or four years when I went around</p>
    <p>with every girl in that part of the country. It won't nothing</p>
    <p>to see three in a crowd that I had been to see. I was getting</p>
    <p>on about twenty-four when I happened to see my wife at a dance</p>
    <p>one night. Oh, I had been seeing her all my life, but that</p>
    <p>was the first night I ever noticed her. I danced with her</p>
    <p>and asked to take her home. She wouldn't let me, for she</p>
    <p>had come with another boy. I went up there the next day,</p>
    <p>though, and she went to ride with me. I quit going with</p>
    <p>any other girl. I went to see her regular, but she went with</p>
    <p>everybody she wanted to. I even give her a ring and she</p>
    <p>didn't quit. On Sunday night before we got married the next</p>
    <p>Saturday she told me that she had the toothache, and she was</p>
    <p>cutting up so that I went home. The very next day I found</p>
    <p>out that she went to ride with another fellow right after I</p>
    <p>left.</p>
    <p>It was the next week that we decided to get married.</p>
    <p>When I got up to the house, her mammy was crying</p>
    <p>and so was she. She asked me if I had asked her daddy if he</p>
    <p>cared. I hadn't, and she told me that she wouldn't leave unless</p>
    <p>he said it was all right. I didn't ask him but just told her</p>
    <p>it was all right. We went to Virginia to get married, for we</p>
    <p>didn't want folks there to know about it. Newly married people</p>
    <p>got serenaded too bad. When we got back, the women from all</p>
    <p>around the town had come in and cooked up a big dinner.</p>
    <p>I didn't know that my folks didn't want me to get</p>
    <p>married, but they didn't speak to me or her either for over</p>
    <p>a month. We stayed with her daddy for two weeks, then we</p>
    <p>went on our honeymoon. We spent two weeks on that.</p>
    <p>I soon went out to hunt for a house. A man told</p>
    <p>me that we could live in his house free just to have somebody</p>
    <p>there to keep it up. I went down and bought a bed, a dresser,</p>
    <p>a safe, a table to eat on, a cabinet to keep the dishes in, a</p>
    <p>cook stove, and some chairs. The store sent the things up</p>
    <p>to the house and I hunted up some dishes and cooking things,</p>
    <p>When I went to supper I asked my wife if she didn't want to</p>
    <p>go home. She thought I meant to her daddy's, and she said she</p>
    <p>did. I went back to the store and got some rations and</p>
    <p>knives, forks and spoons, and went to our house. I built</p>
    <p>a fire in the fireplace and then went after her. She was</p>
    <p>some kind of surprised when she found out that it was where</p>
    <p>we were to live. We stayed there that night and from then on.</p>
    <p>Mama soon got to speaking and we lived all right. We lived</p>
    <p>cheap, too. Our groceries didn't cost but about $2 a week.</p>
    <p>We had a cow and a garden and they helped, but now it takes</p>
    <p>about all I can make to pay for food. It sure makes a</p>
    <p>difference when you run a bill. Folks back home don't know</p>
    <p>what a grocery bill is. If they want anything and don't have</p>
    <p>the money handy they do without, but now we say, "Charge it."</p>
    <p>I played on the ball team in the summertime. I</p>
    <p>had been married only about two years when I got my face</p>
    <p>busted with a wild ball. The pitcher musta been trying to</p>
    <p>mash my face for the ball hit me square on the jaw. It broke</p>
    <p>the jawbone and cut my south and eye. The doctor didn't do</p>
    <p>much good in his treatment for I will always be scarred up.</p>
    <p>I didn't stop playing ball for long, though. It is still</p>
    <p>my favorite game, but I don't play much now.</p>
    <p>The next year my aunt's husband wrote and asked if</p>
    <p>I didn't want to go North to work. He was in charge of the</p>
    <p>line work of the telephone company, and he said I could get</p>
    <p>a good job. Well, we packed our clothes and left. We stayed</p>
    <p>four months and then had to go back home because my wife's</p>
    <p>mother was took sick.</p>
    <p>We didn't go back, for I got a job driving a truck.</p>
    <p>Getting a job never worried me. I have already had two offers</p>
    <p>of jobs when this mail route job is finished. After I got on</p>
    <p>the truck I was on the road all the time. That caused my wife</p>
    <p>to stay home by herself, but some of our people was there</p>
    <p>about every day. She was smart and stayed busy with the</p>
    <p>chickens and cows and garden. She canned everything she</p>
    <p>could get in a jar.</p>
    <p>We folks were not stingy but we were saving; we</p>
    <p>eat good and we didn't go in debt for food. There has been</p>
    <p>many a night when we didn't have a thing for supper but corn</p>
    <p>bread cooked with soda and buttermilk and sweet milk. We</p>
    <p>raised all the chickens we could use, and we got all the eggs</p>
    <p>we needed. Vegetables were plentiful. The women learned</p>
    <p>how to can most anything. They could can fresh meat and</p>
    <p>when the can was opened it was hard to tell it from fresh-killed meat. </p>
    <p>We really lived at home then, but now our</p>
    <p>grocery bill gets higher every pay day.</p>
    <p>At first my wife was satisfied with two new dresses</p>
    <p>a year, now she's got to have a new one every few days. Her</p>
    <p>shoes has got to match and I knowed her when she went barefooted,</p>
    <p>except on Sunday. I bought an electric refrigerator</p>
    <p>not long ago, and it would be mighty hard to do without</p>
    <p>running water now, even if I was raised to carry water from</p>
    <p>a spring down the hill, a quarter of a mile from the house.</p>
    <p>My helper hadn't been down here but a few weeks</p>
    <p>when the postal inspector come down and told him that the</p>
    <p>contract would either have to be in his name or I would have</p>
    <p>to live here. He sent for me and I come down. I didn't</p>
    <p>want to lose the contract, so he quit and I took the job.</p>
    <p>From then until November, I boarded. I wrote home and had</p>
    <p>me a trailer built so my expenses wouldn't be so high. When</p>
    <p>the trailer was finished I went up there and got it and my</p>
    <p>wife. She raised the devil for she didn't want to leave</p>
    <p>"mommy". That's one time I won an argument; she come back</p>
    <p>with me. We packed the things we would need in the trailer</p>
    <p>and stored the rest at her aunt's. I was sorry for her when we</p>
    <p>first got here. She didn't know a soul and I had to be gone</p>
    <p>all day. I carried her with me when ever she would go but</p>
    <p>that was a long tiresome ride. She cried all the time at</p>
    <p>first. Then when I thought I would have to send her back she</p>
    <p>met some women and did not get so lonesome.</p>
    <p>That trailer was big enough for a year or two, but</p>
    <p>then the most things got wrong with it; it was too hot; it</p>
    <p>was too crowded; it was too dark; and Lord knows what else.</p>
    <p>It come out after awhile. She wanted an apartment so she could</p>
    <p>have more company. I put her off and she went home and stayed</p>
    <p>three months. When she come back I was ready to rent two</p>
    <p>apartments. She got out and found one and was nearly moved</p>
    <p>when I got in from carrying the mail. Her friends had helped.</p>
    <p>It was better, for we got a nice screened porch which was so</p>
    <p>cool.</p>
    <p>She got along better then and wasn't so homesick.</p>
    <p>Then I bought her a car to ride around in and everything was</p>
    <p>fine. I don't know what she'll want next. I bought a breakfast</p>
    <p>room suite and a living room suite. We are looking for another</p>
    <p>baby in a few weeks now and she told me a few nights ago that she</p>
    <p>had to have a crib a bassinet, and a carriage. Babies are</p>
    <p>sure expensive in a town, Her friends give her a stork shower</p>
    <p>not long ago, and she got enough things for three babies but</p>
    <p>she still buys,</p>
    <p>I am a member of the city fire department, and I</p>
    <p>have to stay at the fire house a lot when I'm in town. She</p>
    <p>don't like that at all. She expects me to sit right at</p>
    <p>home with her, but I've just got to get out after staying</p>
    <p>in that trunk all day. I have sent for one of my sisters</p>
    <p>to come and stay till the baby comes. After that gets here,</p>
    <p>she'll be so busy she'll be glad for me to leave.</p>
    <p>I will hate just as bad to leave here as I hated</p>
    <p>to come. I have a lot of friends here, and I like the fishing</p>
    <p>and crabbing. We can't have such sports in the hills. I</p>
    <p>will miss the people I meet on the mail route. I take</p>
    <p>passengers with me for all the sacks are locked. But I</p>
    <p>can't charge anybody for riding. I would buy license, but</p>
    <p>another man already has the franchise for the run. I meet</p>
    <p>up with all kinds of people. One of my regular passengers</p>
    <p>is a man who goes down with a bag or parched peanuts and sells</p>
    <p>them on the road. He makes his living that way.</p>
    <p>I have had to quit hauling people. The man that</p>
    <p>had the franchise was afraid that I was getting too much of</p>
    <p>his money, so he reported me to the traffic control board.</p>
    <p>I can still haul my family, and nobody knows how big a family</p>
    <p>I have. It gets bigger every day, especially with pretty</p>
    <p>girls,</p>
    <p>I just have a little better than a year left to stay</p>
    <p>here. It will be hard to go back to the mountains to live, but</p>
    <p>I reckon I can if I have to. Here's hoping that I will be</p>
    <p>able to be the low bidder again, even if I have to take less</p>
    <p>money.</p>
  </text>
</history>
