<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../lifehistory.xsl" ?>
<history>
  <title>Mrs. Esther P. Demos</title>
  <reflink>https://dc.lib.unc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/03709/id/1104</reflink>
  <meta>
    <item>
      <key>Date</key>
      <val>1940-02-06</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Location</key>
      <val>Miami, Florida</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Interviewee</key>
      <val>Esther P. Demos (greek; female)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Writer</key>
      <val>Cora Mae Taylor (white; female)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Reviser</key>
      <val>Mabel B. Francis (white; female)</val>
    </item>
  </meta>
  <text>
    <p>Socio-Ethnic Study</p>
    <p>The Creeks in America</p>
    <p>Cora Mae Taylor</p>
    <p>February 6, 1940.</p>
    <p>Mabel B. Francis Editor</p>
    <p>MRS. ESTHER P. DEMOS</p>
    <p>023 Southwest Fourth Street</p>
    <p>Miami, Florida</p>
    <p>Mrs. Esther Peter Demos, age 33, is a tall matronly &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; with shrewd brown eyes and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; brown hair, a very friendly and approachable person. She were a raspberry colored shirt and a &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; silk &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; dered blouse.</p>
    <p>Mr. and Mrs. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and live in large groom concrete block &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; conveniently located on a bus line, - only a block from Ada Merritt School. There is a profusion of flowers and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; in front of the house which is bordered with a neatly trimed border of artillery plant and a number of large author force on both sides of the ontranco to the screened porch. Green canvas awings cushioned wicker set. At one end of the porch there is also a now twin-bed &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; coach.</p>
    <p>Inside the house, and is impressed 1th the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; borate over-stuffed in blue breaded velvet &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; piano, cabinet radio, Venetion blinds, rare explore and hand embroidered &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; on the walls of the combined living room and dining room. The table is spread with a dainty pilot lace cover and there is a &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; beffet occupying a prominent place near the telephone.'</p>
    <p>The walls are finished in rough plaster, heavily enameled in mottled orange and lemon, while the bathroom and kitchen are equipped with all modern conveniences. There are four bedrooms and in the roar of the house there is a two-room cottage which the boys use for a studio when there are guests or when it becomes too noisy in the front home."</p>
    <p>As the appointment had been made by telephone, Mrs. Domos talked freely without the aid of questions:</p>
    <p>"We have lived in Miami for 14 years. My husband is one of the owners and managers of Topps's Market, 500 N. River Drive. I am a member of the Eastern Star of Carol Cablos and for a while I was one of the officers.</p>
    <p>"We have four boys and one girl. Peter, Sr., the oldest, age 80, graduated from Miami High School in 1836, but how he is a student in the University of Miami specializing in engineering in the class of 1948. James Peter, age 18, has a paper route. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, age 16, is attending, Miami Senior High School. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; age nine, is in the fourth grade at Riverside School. This is Dorothon &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, only 19 months old.</p>
    <p>"My father was one of four brothers who as pioneers built a village near &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; Laconia. The name means clear water. The reason they were attracted to this place was because there was a very cold spring there fod from a rock in the mountain. Their &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, or settlement consisted of a church and mall cemetery. Then brother built a beautiful castle and as their children married, other houses were built. The village was beautifully landscaped-with gardens, flowers, fruits and trees. We were able to support a priest who divided his time between our season and his own church at &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;. Our church was named at Nicholas in honor of my grandfather and only our own relatives were buried in the cemetery. As our cemetery was large enough for all. I do not think that any of the bones have ever been removed from the graves.</p>
    <p>"I was ten years old in 1912, when I came to America with my mother to join the others of our family who lived in Manchester, new Hampshire. I was too young to work in the factory all the time. So I was sent to school and only worked in the ask &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; factory during vacation.</p>
    <p>"I thought it was so strange when I went to school and road all the Creek myths that my grandmother used to toll me. I used to say: "My grandmother never wrote this book. Now did they get held of my grandmother's stories." I never supposed anybody also ever know them.</p>
    <p>"I didn't finish High School, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; I not the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; I wanted &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; It was&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;</p>
    <p>"My oldest sister was married and lived in &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; loston, south Carolina. When they came to New York to visit my cousin before coming on to Manchester, they brought three &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; nice &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; along with then from New York. They all tried to got nominated with me, but if didn't take me long to select the one I liked best.</p>
    <p>"My sister called no aside and asked no which one I wanted and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; the called Mr. Domos aside and told him that I had &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; him. He was very happy, because he felt the same way about it. So you see, that was as good as an engagement. He promised to correspondent and got married &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; years later when I would have finished High School, but we changed our &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and got married in tem months. I could have had a big wedding, but I did not want it."</p>
    <p>Mr. Domos is a strong looking, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of an athletic type while his shiny black hair, stiff heavy eye brows and broad &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; emphasize his dark, snappy eyes get in deep sockets. He was freshly shaved and definitions in appearance, his loving attentions to his wife and baby just us to was &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; for &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; revealed &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; at &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of the home.</p>
    <p>"My cousin &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; but along with her husband. Before their &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, they were so attached to each other and for a while alter &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; married until &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; them &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; apart. There was a woman who as jealous of my cousin and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;n't want them to be happy.</p>
    <p>"All at ones, they discovered that they &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; not bear each other. They could sit in a room together and cry and cry and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; ever now happy they used to be. They tried to find out what was the matter with them. Finally the husband &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;:</p>
    <p>"I believe that &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;oalous woman has done this. Do you suppose she has worked on use"</p>
    <p>"They watched her and found &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; what she had done. I don't round or what it was, but &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;cross she told lies about then. Anyhow, they were able to &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; what she had done and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; as happy an over.</p>
    <p>"When we lived in Manchester. I heard so many stories of the Evil Eye and with craft that I was afraid to turn around or go into a dark room. I was so narvour and fearful ever the stories that my mother &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; my father and brothers to lot no hear any &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of then. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; after I was married and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; tell the stories that I know never &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; would get an &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; as ever. So I made up &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; that my children &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; out them.</p>
    <p>"How, this really happened in Greece when my father was a your &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;. There was a young &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; said: 'I don't believe any of your &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; stuff, I am not afraid to go to a comotery at midnight and I'll prove it to you.'</p>
    <p>"So it was agreed that he should take a &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, sward and thrust it up to the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; on a grave and core back home again. Then in the morning they would go to the comotery and find the award as he had left it.</p>
    <p>"The victim were a tunic shirt that spread ever the grave as he &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; over and thrust the award through the skirt, not knowing that to had &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; himself to the grave.</p>
    <p>"So it happened, that when he started to go back home, he felt something pulling and holding him fast. He was so frightened that he died on the spot and his scoffers grieved ever their folly, when they fo&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; him the next &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and could see that he had made a desperate struggle to free himself from the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;."</p>
    <p>&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; (Garlic Sance)</p>
    <p>If you want it strong, take a whole section of a large garlic onion and a level teaspoonful of salt with a wooden paddle in a wondon bowl. Mix and a use the garlic into a palp. Add a boiled potato, or if you do not what it to taste so strong, take about three pieces of bread soaked in water and mix with olive oil. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; all together until it is about the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;. Add a cup of &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; until it is white.</p>
    <p>Use as a &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; on broiled Fish or any &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;. It is also used in place of may &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, or as a &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;olish ever boiled boats.</p>
  </text>
</history>
