<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../lifehistory.xsl" ?>
<history>
  <title>Cotton in the Blood</title>
  <reflink>https://dc.lib.unc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/03709/id/682</reflink>
  <meta>
    <item>
      <key>Date</key>
      <val>1939-01-23</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Location</key>
      <val>Gastonia, North Carolina</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Occupations</key>
      <val>cotton man; hotel manager</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Interviewee</key>
      <val>Wade Hampton Taylor (white; male)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Pseudonym</key>
      <val>Miles Thronton</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Writer</key>
      <val>John H. Abner (white; male)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Reviser</key>
      <val>George L. Andrews (white; male)</val>
    </item>
  </meta>
  <text>
    <p>Names changed.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>Date of first writing: Jan. 23rd, 1939</p>
    <p>Name: Wade Hampton Taylor</p>
    <p>Address: Textile Hotel</p>
    <p>Place: Gastonia, N. C.</p>
    <p>Occupation: Hotel Manager and cotton man</p>
    <p>Name of writer: John H. Abner, Gastonia, N. C.</p>
    <p>Revisers George L. Andrews</p>
    <p/>
    <p>Cotton in the Blood</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Good old Memphis," said Miles Thornton, manager of</p>
    <p>the Textile Hotel, of Beaumont, V. C. "She's a grand</p>
    <p>old lady, on a mighty big river. Her streets teem with</p>
    <p>life, and the river teems with catfish. And there the</p>
    <p>darky snares those catfish. With hook and line, and</p>
    <p>with trap and basket, he snares the catfish; and then</p>
    <p>he fries them brown. And the nostrils of the white man</p>
    <p>twitch and wobble, for the aroma of the fried cat is</p>
    <p>pleasant.</p>
    <p>"Good old Memphis. She is the mother of Jazz, and</p>
    <p>from Jazz came Swing, for as Mr. Mercer says: 'They just</p>
    <p>cut the tempo down and then they really went to town.'</p>
    <p>Yes, and it was Memphis Town. There are those who would</p>
    <p>give the credit for Jazz to New Orleans, but I say Memphis.</p>
    <p>Memphis is the mother of Jazz. Who has not heard The</p>
    <p>Memphis Blues? Memphis is a good old town. Steamboat</p>
    <p>Bill has swaggered along her waterfront, and Casey Jones</p>
    <p>has tooted his whistle in her yard. 'But Ol' Man River,</p>
    <p>he jes keeps rollin' along.' Yes. Memphis is the mother</p>
    <p>of Jazz, but Ol' Man River is her daddy. In the days of</p>
    <p>her youth he fed her on tough meat. That was necessary</p>
    <p>that she grow big and strong; for she was to become the</p>
    <p>handmaiden of King Cotton. And she did! She's the biggest</p>
    <p>inland cotton market in the world, and ten trunk line</p>
    <p>railroads thread her streets and alleys. And more hardwood</p>
    <p>lumbar is shipped from Memphis than from any other point</p>
    <p>in the world.</p>
    <p>"I was born in Memphis, July 24th, 1883, and I lived</p>
    <p>there for thirty-nine years. I've been away for a long</p>
    <p>time, but I still love the old town. I love the hustle</p>
    <p>and bustle of the riverfront. I can still hear the tooting</p>
    <p>of the steamboats; and I used to like to watch the darky</p>
    <p>roustabouts wrestle bales of cotton. There's a trick, a</p>
    <p>swing, a balance, in the way they handle a bale of cotton.</p>
    <p>To watch them truck and push the bales about you'd think</p>
    <p>that the bales were light, but they weigh around five</p>
    <p>hundred pounds. But a good roustabout can take one hand</p>
    <p>and rock a five hundred pound bale of cotton onto a truck</p>
    <p>as though it was a feather pillow.</p>
    <p>"At age six I started to school, and I went to</p>
    <p>school until I was about fifteen or sixteen years old. I</p>
    <p>finished the eighth grade and then quit. I could have had</p>
    <p>a better education, but I tired of school. Schools were</p>
    <p>not so common at that time, and when I quit school it was</p>
    <p>my intention to go to medical college when I got older.</p>
    <p>My father was a physician. I wanted to follow in his</p>
    <p>footsteps. So I quit school when I was about sixteen,</p>
    <p>and started going around with my father on his medical</p>
    <p>calls. Often we'd leave home early in the morning and be</p>
    <p>away until dark. If we were in town we might come home</p>
    <p>to dinner, but sometimes we'd be way out in the country.</p>
    <p>Then we would take dinner with some of our friends. The</p>
    <p>old style doctor was often more than a physician. He was</p>
    <p>also friend and counselor; and was welcome anywhere. My</p>
    <p>father practiced in town and country both. He used a horse</p>
    <p>and buggy most of the time; especially in town; but when</p>
    <p>the country roads were bad he would ride horseback.</p>
    <p>"It was customary at that time for every doctor to</p>
    <p>carry a supply of simple drugs and medicines with him on</p>
    <p>his calls. A patient might live ten miles in the country</p>
    <p>and be unable to get to a drug store. While he could be</p>
    <p>very sick, his illness might be easily remedied; and the</p>
    <p>country doctor would diagnose, prescribe, and then fill</p>
    <p>his prescription, right there at the patient's home.</p>
    <p>Money, lives, and time were saved by that system; and</p>
    <p>it seems to me that it was a better system than we have</p>
    <p>today. Now if a man has a bad cold and calls a doctor,</p>
    <p>the doctor's likely to write him three or four prescriptions,</p>
    <p>and the druggist is likely to charge him three or four</p>
    <p>dollars, yet, in all the four prescriptions there may not</p>
    <p>be fifteen cents worth of drugs. Some of our doctors and</p>
    <p>druggists are little better than racketeers. The price</p>
    <p>of medicine should be kept low, so that the poor could</p>
    <p>buy it. Personally, I'd rather risk my life with one of</p>
    <p>the old style , family doctors, than with one of these hard-eyed,</p>
    <p>white-coated sharks, that now carve upon humanity.</p>
    <p>The old style family doctor, who was so common thirty or</p>
    <p>forty years ago, had sympathy for his patients. He regarded</p>
    <p>them as human beings, entitled to human treatment. Many</p>
    <p>of today's doctors and surgeons impress me as lacking in</p>
    <p>sympathy. They seem to look upon their patients as germs;</p>
    <p>something to be cut up and destroyed. I've known my</p>
    <p>father to weep with the family because a member of that</p>
    <p>family died. Can you imagine one of these hard-eyed sharks,</p>
    <p>weeping because he lost a patient? I cannot. It is all</p>
    <p>in the day's work to him, and he'd probably fall back on</p>
    <p>that ghastly joke. 'The operation was successful, but</p>
    <p>the patient died.'</p>
    <p>"It seems to me that our modern doctors are not</p>
    <p>taught to relieve suffering, but to cause suffering.</p>
    <p>From the time they start in medical school they're taught</p>
    <p>to cut and kill. They cut up cats, rats, frogs, birds,</p>
    <p>rabbits, and other small life, watching their sufferings</p>
    <p>and death struggles with calculating eyes. Then they</p>
    <p>graduate, and come out from college, well prepared to cut</p>
    <p>up human beings in the same way.</p>
    <p>"But this is the age of cruelty. Look at the bombings</p>
    <p>in Spain and China. I just don't see how one human being</p>
    <p>can fly over a town and drop those shrieking bombs on</p>
    <p>helpless women and children. And I don't believe that</p>
    <p>any man who does such hellishness will ever know peace.</p>
    <p>The screams of those mutilated women and children will</p>
    <p>ring in his ears for the balance of his life . In the dark</p>
    <p>night he'll wake, in a cold sweat, and find that invisible</p>
    <p>devils are grappling with his very entrails! He'll have</p>
    <p>evil dreams, and see evil visions, and evil voices will</p>
    <p>lead him ever onward to his doom. And his end will be</p>
    <p>according to his evil, for the wages of sin is death.</p>
    <p>But perhaps we should make allowances here; because any</p>
    <p>man who'd deliberately mutilate and murder helpless women</p>
    <p>and children is bad off somewhere. There is something</p>
    <p>wrong with his head, and there is something wrong with his</p>
    <p>heart. By the laws of civilization he should be classed</p>
    <p>as a monstrous murderer, as well as a coward. He does</p>
    <p>not fight. He could not be called a combatant. He just</p>
    <p>flies high in the air, over defenseless cities, and drops</p>
    <p>bombs on women and children. That is not war. That is</p>
    <p>murder. War is fighting; and most of this hellish bombing</p>
    <p>has happened to cities which had no air defense whatever.</p>
    <p>"Then look at the oppression of the Jews in Germany</p>
    <p>and Italy.. The Jews are not charged with any crime. They</p>
    <p>are oppressed merely because they're Jews. It would be a</p>
    <p>blessing to both the German and Italian people if someone</p>
    <p>shot their leaders. Both Hitler and Mussolini should be</p>
    <p>killed as quickly as possible; and as mercilessly as</p>
    <p>poisonous snakes. Both are mad, and unless they're stopped</p>
    <p>they'll lead their people into a terrible war. And it may</p>
    <p>spread all over the world. All these things are an indication</p>
    <p>of the truth that humanity is threatened with insanity.</p>
    <p>It begins to look as if civilization was dying out; and</p>
    <p>as if we were going back into the dark ages. But no. That</p>
    <p>won't do. The dark ages were more humane than we of today.</p>
    <p>"I think that the passing of the old style doctor is</p>
    <p>a tragedy; especially to the very poor. Nowadays, the</p>
    <p>very poor are practically deprived of medical attention,</p>
    <p>because the cost is prohibitive. Before a doctor can tell</p>
    <p>that a man is constipated, he must make an X-ray picture;</p>
    <p>cost, ten to one hundred dollars; according to the patient's</p>
    <p>bank roll. The old style, family doctor, could tell that</p>
    <p>by looking at the tongue. Then he gave a dose of calomel</p>
    <p>and salts, cost of treatment and visit, one to five dollars,</p>
    <p>according to how far he had to drive. Science tells us</p>
    <p>now that the patient sometimes had appendicitis, and that</p>
    <p>the purgative was bad for him; and sometimes even killed</p>
    <p>him. But I don't know about that. Science has set afloat</p>
    <p>many rumors, and most of those rumors are calculated to</p>
    <p>add dollars to his store. Also, Science has remained</p>
    <p>strangely silent as to how many of his patients died under</p>
    <p>the operation; and as to how many sound appendixes he</p>
    <p>has removed.</p>
    <p>"My father also owned several farms which he let out</p>
    <p>to tenants, sometimes white families, and sometimes colored.</p>
    <p>Most everyone liked my father. He was naturally a kind</p>
    <p>man, as well as a good doctor. He had a good practice and</p>
    <p>earned good money, but he did not become grasping. He</p>
    <p>treated his tenants well, and they stayed with him, year</p>
    <p>after year. His tenants would have no doctor but him!</p>
    <p>"When my father made his rounds in town I'd go along</p>
    <p>with him and drive the horse. When he rode horseback into</p>
    <p>the country I'd also ride along with him. I was personally</p>
    <p>acquainted with many of the families where he visited,</p>
    <p>and would often go into the house with him. I was learning</p>
    <p>what I could, for later I was expecting to attend medical</p>
    <p>college and learn to be a doctor myself. From these</p>
    <p>visits, and from asking questions of my father, I became</p>
    <p>familiar with such drugs and mixtures as he commonly carried.</p>
    <p>Calomel, salts, Dobell's Solution, Dover's Powder, I. Q.</p>
    <p>and S., and such things, he carried in his saddle bags,</p>
    <p>along with his instruments; and I came to know such</p>
    <p>things as he carried, and for what he used them.</p>
    <p>"When I was about seventeen years old my father went</p>
    <p>to Philadelphia to take a three weeks' course. I cannot</p>
    <p>recall just what it was, but no doubt it was some new</p>
    <p>process or treatment. Before leaving my father put his</p>
    <p>practice in the hands of Doctor Buford, a brother physician.</p>
    <p>He also left word with the family to send anyone who came</p>
    <p>for him to Doctor Buford.</p>
    <p>"A day or so after my father left I was sitting on</p>
    <p>the front porch reading. A colored boy rode up and inquired</p>
    <p>for my father. I knew the boy. He was a member of one of</p>
    <p>my father's tenant families, and was riding one of our mules.</p>
    <p>He did not tell me what he wanted and I told him that father</p>
    <p>had gone to Philadelphia. I also told him that if he wanted</p>
    <p>a doctor he should go for Doctor Buford.</p>
    <p>"The boy rode away and I continued reading. In about</p>
    <p>an hour he was back, and he told me that his father had</p>
    <p>sent him after me. I told him to go and saddle my father's</p>
    <p>mare; he knew which horse my father rode. The boy</p>
    <p>saddled the mare and I rode along with him to his home.</p>
    <p>There I found a member of the family sick in bed; a girl</p>
    <p>about fifteen years old. I told the father of the girl</p>
    <p>that he should summon Doctor Buford but he would not hear</p>
    <p>to that.</p>
    <p>"'Nawsuh, Mr. Miles,' he said. "We ain't gwine hab</p>
    <p>no strange doctor. Ef yo Paw's gone off you doctor dat</p>
    <p>gal yoself. She's plum sick.'</p>
    <p>"Well, my father's instruments and drugs were in the</p>
    <p>saddle bags. I got them out and felt the girl's pulse.</p>
    <p>Her pulse was rapid, and she had a temperature of 102.</p>
    <p>It looked like a touch of malaria, but I was not sure, and</p>
    <p>I did not want to take any chances. I mixed some quinine,</p>
    <p>Dover's Powder, and calomel together, and filled several</p>
    <p>No. one capsules. I gave the girl one and instructed her</p>
    <p>mother to continue giving the capsules, three hours apart.</p>
    <p>Then I went out to the well to examine the water. I had</p>
    <p>the darky draw a bucket of water. It was none too clear,</p>
    <p>and it had a bad taste. I did not drink any of the water,</p>
    <p>but I rinsed my mouth with it as I had seen my father do.</p>
    <p>I told the Negro that the water was impure, and that</p>
    <p>he must clean the well out at once. There was a good</p>
    <p>spring some distance from the house, and I told him to</p>
    <p>get his drinking water from the spring until he had got</p>
    <p>the well cleaned out.</p>
    <p>"'Yassuh, Mr. Miles, sho will,' he said.</p>
    <p>"I told him also that I'd be riding out that way the</p>
    <p>next day, and that I'd stop by and see how the girl was</p>
    <p>getting along. I charged him two dollars for the visit</p>
    <p>and he paid me then.</p>
    <p>"The next day I rode up to the house and stopped.</p>
    <p>The girl had eaten a hearty breakfast, and was sitting up.</p>
    <p>Her temperature and pulse were normal, and she seemed well</p>
    <p>on the road to recovery. I judged that she did not need</p>
    <p>any more medicine; and as I had just stopped by I made</p>
    <p>no charge for that trip. I told them that I'd look in</p>
    <p>the next day.</p>
    <p>"The next day I stopped by and the girl was well!</p>
    <p>She was out in the field, hoeing cotton* T%at was on</p>
    <p>Friday, and on Sunday the family went to church. Negro</p>
    <p>like, they spread the news of the girl's miraculous</p>
    <p>recovery, along with the information that I had taken</p>
    <p>over my father's practice; and that I was an expert</p>
    <p>judge of drinking water. This news spread among the Negroes,</p>
    <p>and there was an epidemic of well cleaning. They also</p>
    <p>spread my fame as a physician and during the next few days</p>
    <p>I had several calls. I earned about thirty dollars from</p>
    <p>my medical practice, and all my patients lived.</p>
    <p>"I did not write my father what I was doing, because</p>
    <p>I knew that he'd order me to stop it. I was having a</p>
    <p>wonderful time posing as a physician; but of course, I</p>
    <p>took no chances. I gave nothing except ordinary remedies;</p>
    <p>and I had already resolved to call in Doctor Buford if</p>
    <p>any complications developed. But everything went so well</p>
    <p>with my patients that I did not need to call on him. When</p>
    <p>my father came back from Philadelphia I told him what I</p>
    <p>had been doing. He was quite shocked.</p>
    <p>"'Did anybody die?' he queried.</p>
    <p>"'Oh, no,' I said. 'They are all up, well, and going</p>
    <p>about.''</p>
    <p>"'Well son.' he said. 'you don't realize the enormity</p>
    <p>of your offense. You've been practicing medicine without</p>
    <p>a license.'</p>
    <p>"Soon after that, boy like, I lost interest in the</p>
    <p>medical profession. I got interested in old King Cotton.</p>
    <p>My uncle McSpadden, owned a warehouse, and he gave me a</p>
    <p>job in it. There I learned the cotton business. Memphis</p>
    <p>was a boom town at that time, and cotton was king. There</p>
    <p>was great activity in cotton, and in lumber and shipping.</p>
    <p>The whole country was growing and building, and Memphis</p>
    <p>shipped cotton and lumber all over the world.</p>
    <p>"I liked the warehouse business. I worked with my</p>
    <p>uncle for ten years. I learned all I could about cotton,</p>
    <p>and my uncle made me his assistant. At the end of ten</p>
    <p>years he closed out his warehouse business; and I went</p>
    <p>to work for Brooks, Neely, and Finley; as supervisor</p>
    <p>of weighing and examination. Sometimes cotton is kept</p>
    <p>stored in a warehouse for a long time. Then, before it</p>
    <p>can be shipped out, it must be re-weighed and examined</p>
    <p>for condition.</p>
    <p>"Along about that time I went up to Louisville to</p>
    <p>see the Kentucky Derby. I enjoyed myself immensely. I</p>
    <p>liked the colorful crowds and I enjoyed the races too.</p>
    <p>From that time on I was a Derby fan, and I saw the Derby</p>
    <p>run for twelve successive seasons.</p>
    <p>"I worked for Brooks, Neely, and Finley for six</p>
    <p>years. I made pretty good money, and I saved a part of</p>
    <p>it. I had no one to look after but myself. I've never</p>
    <p>married. I guess I am a confirmed bachelor. After six</p>
    <p>years with Brooks, Neely, and Finley, I had saved quite a</p>
    <p>bit of money, so I decided to go in business for myself.</p>
    <p>"My uncle McSpadden, for whom I had formerly worked,</p>
    <p>was also looking around for an opening in the cotton</p>
    <p>business. Once a cotton man always a cotton man. I</p>
    <p>reckon cotton gets in the blood. Anyway, that is an</p>
    <p>old saying. The born cotton man loves cotton. He talks</p>
    <p>cotton, thinks cotton, and believes in cotton. He may</p>
    <p>be bullish or he say be bearish, but he believes in</p>
    <p>cotton, one way or the other. He's most likely to think</p>
    <p>that cotton is either going up or down.</p>
    <p>"My uncle McSpadden wanted to get back into the</p>
    <p>cotton business, so we formed a partnership under the</p>
    <p>firm name of Thornton &amp; McSpadden. We represented fourteen</p>
    <p>cotton buying firms, and we made money. Our partnership</p>
    <p>lasted four years.</p>
    <p>"In 1922 I got an offer from the California, Arizona,</p>
    <p>Mexico Cotton Association, to come to California. For</p>
    <p>some reason cotton men didn't like to stay in California,</p>
    <p>and they had difficulty in keeping a good cotton man.</p>
    <p>Consequently, they made me such a good offer that I felt</p>
    <p>that I should accept it. I disliked to leave Memphis</p>
    <p>and all my friends, but business is business. I sold</p>
    <p>out my share of the partnership to my uncle, and went</p>
    <p>out to California in 1922.</p>
    <p>"There I was inspector, or chief examiner, of all the</p>
    <p>cotton handled by the Association. I examined and checked</p>
    <p>the weights; both at gins and warehouses. It was not</p>
    <p>such an easy job as it might seem to be. I had to travel</p>
    <p>the San Joaquin, Palo Alto, and Imperial Valleys in</p>
    <p>California; and the Great Salt Elver Valley in Arizona.</p>
    <p>I also had to cross the line into Old Mexico. The Company</p>
    <p>furnished me a car and chauffeur because I had so many</p>
    <p>long jumps. It was 1,200 miles across my territory,</p>
    <p>and 1,200 miles back. I was paid a good salary, but</p>
    <p>I earned it. I had to weigh and examine every bale of</p>
    <p>cotton before it could be snipped out. My headquarters</p>
    <p>were in Los Angeles. I worked for the Association eight</p>
    <p>years.</p>
    <p>"In 1929 the depression hit us, as well as everyone</p>
    <p>else. In 1930 I came here to Beaumont, and went to work</p>
    <p>for my brother, W. I. Thornton, who was also in the cotton</p>
    <p>business. I worked for him five years, but most of that</p>
    <p>time Old King Cotton was sick. Sometimes I fear that he</p>
    <p>is on his last legs; and if that be the case, I don't</p>
    <p>know what we in the South will do. We've raised cotton</p>
    <p>so long that it would probably take an economic upheaval</p>
    <p>to jar us from our rut; and it might be that a new</p>
    <p>generation would have to come along before we could change</p>
    <p>our cropping system. I guess we got cotton in the blood,</p>
    <p>and maybe on the brain. Still, we hope. Old King Cotton</p>
    <p>has been sick many times, but he has always recovered. Let</p>
    <p>us hope that new uses for cotton will be discovered, and</p>
    <p>that he'll get well. There's no fiber that hangs and</p>
    <p>drapes so well as cotton. It is a clean, vegetable fiber,</p>
    <p>and is as far ahead of these synthetic fibers as day is</p>
    <p>of night. Cotton is soft and clinging, but these</p>
    <p>synthetic fibers are hard and glistery. They are also</p>
    <p>heavy, and they do not drape. They droop, that's it!</p>
    <p>They droop. Go out into the street and look in the show</p>
    <p>windows. Find one of those rayon dresses hanging there,</p>
    <p>and look how it droops. Then feel its weight and harshness.</p>
    <p>I declare I can't see why women buy the things. And silk,</p>
    <p>now? Silk is only the scum of a worm. It stands to</p>
    <p>reason that silk is nasty. Who would want to clothe</p>
    <p>themselves in the scum of a worm? Yes. Silk is only</p>
    <p>the scum of a worm, and these synthetic fibers are the</p>
    <p>scum of science. They're nasty, and they stink. But</p>
    <p>cotton is clean and sweet, for cotton is the fibers of</p>
    <p>GOD! Sometimes I think that if our cotton manufacturers</p>
    <p>had had any get-up and imagination that they would not</p>
    <p>have set idly, and let these false fibers replace cotton.</p>
    <p>So you see I'm naturally a cotton man. I'm now an innkeeper</p>
    <p>but not from choice.</p>
    <p>"I came here to the Textile Hotel in 1935, and I've</p>
    <p>been here ever since. While I like the hotel business</p>
    <p>all right, I am naturally a cotton man."</p>
    <p>Mr. Thornton had been looking through the drawer</p>
    <p>of a small table. He took out a stack of newspaper</p>
    <p>clippings and handed them to me. "Do you want to know</p>
    <p>anything about my hobbies?" he asked.</p>
    <p>"Oh yes," I said, "and about your politics and church</p>
    <p>preference"</p>
    <p>"Well," he continued, "I've always been a Democrat.</p>
    <p>I have never joined a church, but I lean toward the</p>
    <p>Methodists. My father and mother were both church</p>
    <p>members, and I was raised in the Methodist faith."</p>
    <p>I looked through the newspaper clippings. They</p>
    <p>told of his prowess as a billiard expert. I copied the</p>
    <p>following from one of the clippings.</p>
    <p>"Miles Thornton defeated M. B. Hooper, 3O to 7, in</p>
    <p>the first match at three cushion billiards. Thornton</p>
    <p>completed his three matches with a perfect score of 150.</p>
    <p>"Won 3. Lost 0. Per cent 1.000"</p>
    <p>"Pretty good," I commented. "You seem to have shook</p>
    <p>a mean cue. Is there anything else that you have thought</p>
    <p>of? Anything else to tell?"</p>
    <p>"No," he said, "I guess that's all. I've told the</p>
    <p>story right down to date."</p>
    <p>So I thanked Mr. Thornton for his story and took my</p>
    <p>leave. I was unable to find a suitable room when I first</p>
    <p>came to Beaumont, so I spent a week at the Textile Hotel.</p>
    <p>Mr. Thornton is a jolly fellow, about fifty-five years,</p>
    <p>always smiling, and seems to have the regular 'glad hand'</p>
    <p>of the natural hotel manager.</p>
    <p>However, Mr. Thornton did not seem to be proud of</p>
    <p>his managership. On the contrary, he seemed to be somewhat</p>
    <p>ashamed of it. The Textile Hotel is a small, cheap,</p>
    <p>lodging place, of about thirty rooms; patronized mostly</p>
    <p>by working people. It has two wings. All the rooms</p>
    <p>have running water, but only one wing has heat. Rooms</p>
    <p>on that side are three fifty per week, and unheated rooms</p>
    <p>are three dollars per week. In the very nature of things</p>
    <p>the place could not bring in much money; and as in this</p>
    <p>country a man is judged almost solely by the amount of</p>
    <p>money he earns, or gets possessions of, it is only natural</p>
    <p>that Mr. Thornton should not be proud of his job.</p>
    <p>But he looks after the place well, and tries to make</p>
    <p>his guests feel at home. There's a small radio in the</p>
    <p>lobby, and guests are at liberty to play the radio. There's</p>
    <p>also a small table, marked off in squares, for checkers.</p>
    <p>Guests are at liberty to play checkers, and games of cards,</p>
    <p>on that table.</p>
    <p>On Christmas Eve, while I was out to supper, Mr.</p>
    <p>Thornton slipped a Christmas Card under my door, on which</p>
    <p>ha had inscribed a suitable sentiment, in a full round</p>
    <p>hand, which had an astonishing resemblance to that of</p>
    <p>the old time penmanship teachers, who were once so common</p>
    <p>in the south; traveling about from place to place; and</p>
    <p>teaching both young and old to wield the pen; which at</p>
    <p>that time was said to be mightier than the word. I much</p>
    <p>admired the penmanship, and thanked Mr. Thornton for the</p>
    <p>card, and wished him a Merry Christmas.</p>
  </text>
</history>
