<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../lifehistory.xsl" ?>
<history>
  <title>Ed and Mary Jackson</title>
  <reflink>https://dc.lib.unc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/03709/id/460</reflink>
  <meta>
    <item>
      <key>Date</key>
      <val>1938-09-27</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Location</key>
      <val>Chapel Hill, North Carolina</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Occupations</key>
      <val>mill worker</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Interviewee</key>
      <val>Ed Jackson (white; male); Mary Jackson (white; female)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Writer</key>
      <val>William O. Foster (white; male)</val>
    </item>
  </meta>
  <text>
    <p>Orange County</p>
    <p>Chapel Hill, N.C.</p>
    <p>9/27/38</p>
    <p>William O. Foster</p>
    <p/>
    <p>Ed and Mary Jackson</p>
    <p/>
    <p>Four miles south and east of Chapel Hill, N.C. is</p>
    <p>the farm home of Ed Jackson and his wife, Mary Jackson.</p>
    <p>They cultivate a small farm on shares on a dirt road</p>
    <p>which &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; US highway No. 15 a mile and a half</p>
    <p>south of Chapel Hill and runs east through the</p>
    <p>Mt. Carmel section</p>
    <p/>
    <p>Ed Jackson is only forty-five years old but</p>
    <p>his shoulders are beginning to stoop,</p>
    <p>his black hair is turning gray, and three front teeth are missing. Ed says his grandfather</p>
    <p>came to the United States from Wales. Since they came to America his people</p>
    <p>have always been tenants, and the only time</p>
    <p>he was free from this type of work was a period of six years</p>
    <p>when he worked at a cotton mill in Carrboro. Even</p>
    <p>while he was in the mill, his wife and the children</p>
    <p>ran the farm. He and a friend shared the expense of commuting. He thought this mill work plan threw too</p>
    <p>much work and responsibility on his wife and</p>
    <p>he gave it up. He said with a</p>
    <p>sigh, "I miss my pay-envelope but we</p>
    <p>ain't going to starve on the farm. I guess I'll</p>
    <p>stick to the farm."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>Mary Jackson is only forty but she looks older</p>
    <p>than her husbnd. She too is stooped and lines are</p>
    <p>appearing in her face. She walks and talks as though</p>
    <p>she is tired. On each of my visits to the home she had</p>
    <p>just come in from her work, grading tobacco. Her</p>
    <p>gray cotton dress was too old and faded to be called a</p>
    <p>house dress and she called it, by way of apology,</p>
    <p>"my work clothes". He folks were</p>
    <p>"just Americans" and farmers always. The school she</p>
    <p>attended as a girl only lasted four months in the year.</p>
    <p>As she put it, "I began going</p>
    <p>with Ed when I was fifteen and</p>
    <p>four months later we ran off from school and got married.</p>
    <p>I was too young to have any sense and hadn't had</p>
    <p>much fun. I reckon I deserve to have a hard time."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>She was one of nine children</p>
    <p>and has five of her own. "Three of my young uns got</p>
    <p>married when they wasn't much older than I</p>
    <p>was. I still have two at home. Sally, there, is seventeen.</p>
    <p>She stayed out of school three years after she finished the seventh</p>
    <p>grade and vowed she wasn't going back</p>
    <p>because she didn't like school." Sally</p>
    <p>broke in on our talk, smiling at me with sparkling black,</p>
    <p>eyes, and said, "But I'm at it again; I'm in the</p>
    <p>eigth grade and I'm having a good time." Buddie</p>
    <p>is fourteen and is in the seventh grade of the Chapel</p>
    <p>Hill School.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I do my house work and work on the farm like a</p>
    <p>man," Mary said. In busy times, I'm up at daylight and by</p>
    <p>dark I'm too sleepy to read. Rain is</p>
    <p>some times a blessing. 'More rain, more rest' The children</p>
    <p>do all they can after school, on Saturdays and in the summer,</p>
    <p>but they don't get tired like me."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>The Jacksons have the only log house in the</p>
    <p>immediate neighborhood. In fact, tow log houses</p>
    <p>three feet apart have been connected and the two give scant</p>
    <p>space for the family. The house is close to the road and</p>
    <p>the shade trees are at the barn. The yard is sandy and</p>
    <p>there is not a flower or a shrub in sight. The house is</p>
    <p>daubbed with white mud and is not ceiled, but</p>
    <p>has been screened. Jackson</p>
    <p>said there are five rooms, but Mary said there are</p>
    <p>only four. I don't know how come there ain't five",</p>
    <p>Jackson countered. I quickly</p>
    <p>showed my admiration for the table which held</p>
    <p>the children's school books and some magazines.</p>
    <p>This table was about ten feet by two and a half</p>
    <p>feet, fairly new and already of much better</p>
    <p>materials than anything in the house. "I got that</p>
    <p>from a friend in town", Mary explained. The front</p>
    <p>room in which we were sitting is a bed room.</p>
    <p>The double bed looks substantial with its plain, iron</p>
    <p>frame. The floor made of rough pine is bare. The</p>
    <p>windows boast of no ornament other than the faded,</p>
    <p>torn shades. There were two dresses in the</p>
    <p>room. The only decorations on the walls were three</p>
    <p>enlarged pictures of relatives and the head of a deer. A double-barrelled</p>
    <p>shot-gun hung on pegs in one corner.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>The kitchen is back of the bed-room. Wood piled</p>
    <p>half way to the low ceiling as used for fuel.</p>
    <p>The table is covered with bright red oil-cloth.</p>
    <p>A new, checkered linoleum covers half of the floor.</p>
    <p>A hound dog and a collie</p>
    <p>kept their eyes closed while I walked</p>
    <p>over them on entering the kitchen.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>A narrow hall leads to the two bed-rooms</p>
    <p>in the other section of the house. Each of these rooms</p>
    <p>has a double bed. Sally has the front room and</p>
    <p>the other is claimed by Buddie.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>This house has recently gotten electric lights.</p>
    <p>The University of North Carolina runs its lines</p>
    <p>only as far as this house. Other families east of</p>
    <p>the Jacksons have signed up for lights but at</p>
    <p>present the university is unable to serve them. An</p>
    <p>electric iron is the only electric appliance,</p>
    <p>but if they have a better crop</p>
    <p>and better prices next year they will get either</p>
    <p>a washing-machine or a "Kelvinator" like the</p>
    <p>nearest neighbor has.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>I took from the long steady table a copy of</p>
    <p>The Southern Planter. Sally, seeing my interest,</p>
    <p>handed me The Country Home and The Biblical</p>
    <p>Recorder. They also take the Durham Morning Herald.</p>
    <p>The only books in the house are two Bibles and some</p>
    <p>school-books.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>The Jacksons cultivate 3.6 acres of tobacco; and,</p>
    <p>since they do not find it profitable to raise cotton,</p>
    <p>tobacco is their money crop. The Tobacco crop last year</p>
    <p>brought Jackson $450.00 but the excess of rain and</p>
    <p>poor prices this year will cut the return on this</p>
    <p>crop. Jackson furnishes a third of the fertilizer for the corn</p>
    <p>and a fourth for the tobacco and recieves a like proportion of the yeild.</p>
    <p>Nineteen acres of the corn will furnish the family</p>
    <p>its meal and in large measure feed the two mules,</p>
    <p>3 hogs and large flock of chickens. The overhead and</p>
    <p>garden furnish this year ninety quarts of peaches,</p>
    <p>forty quarts of berries, and sixty quarts of vegetables.</p>
    <p>Jackson will sell this year vegetables for five</p>
    <p>dollars and eggs for twenty dollars. He borrows</p>
    <p>money from a friend at six percent interest in</p>
    <p>securing his part of the fertilizer. The</p>
    <p>land-owner has not been called on to furnish pantry</p>
    <p>supplies or advance money for any purpose. He</p>
    <p>has an old car, but cannot afford to run it.</p>
    <p>His family rides to the Mt. Carmel</p>
    <p>Baptist church with the neighbors; and when this is not</p>
    <p>convenient, they walk to church. Fortunately,</p>
    <p>the Jacksons have had very little illness and</p>
    <p>very little money has gone towards doctor's bills.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>Jackson always votes the straight "Roosevelt ticket"</p>
    <p>as a pleasure and a duty. Mrs. Jackson votes only from</p>
    <p>a sense of duty. They think the country is prospering</p>
    <p>under the New Deal more than in other</p>
    <p>years. "I get my share from the owner", Jackson</p>
    <p>says, "but neither of us gets what's compung to us.</p>
    <p>If us farmers would stick together like the merchants</p>
    <p>do, we could get more for our stuff."" Although he has</p>
    <p>no complaints against the landowner, he has</p>
    <p>moved on the average every third year, "hoping to do</p>
    <p>better at the next place". He has done a lot of</p>
    <p>thinking about owning a farm but has not yet</p>
    <p>seen a way to ownership.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>Jackson hunts and fishes in his leisure time. On</p>
    <p>Saturday afternoons the family walks or rides with a</p>
    <p>neighbor into Chapel Hill. Sally is "going steady</p>
    <p>with Bill Young", the son of a neighboring farmer. Bill</p>
    <p>occasionally gets the use of his father's car and they</p>
    <p>go "gallavanting" around the country to churches, fairs,</p>
    <p>ball-games and movies. Sally lives too far</p>
    <p>from Chapel Hill to take part in the social life of</p>
    <p>the High School and must leave for home in the</p>
    <p>school bus promptly after school is out.</p>
  </text>
</history>
