<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../lifehistory.xsl" ?>
<history>
  <title>John Reese and Morris Moore</title>
  <reflink>https://dc.lib.unc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/03709/id/1086</reflink>
  <meta>
    <item>
      <key>Date</key>
      <val>1939-05-19</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Location</key>
      <val>Jacksonville, Florida</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Occupations</key>
      <val>farmer</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Community</key>
      <val>Yukon</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Interviewee</key>
      <val>John Reese (black; male); Morris Moore (black; male)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Writer</key>
      <val>Rose Shepherd (white; female)</val>
    </item>
  </meta>
  <text>
    <p>John Reese (colored, 59 farmer</p>
    <p>Morris Reese (colored, 77 Farmer</p>
    <p>Mulberry Grove Plantation Yukon, Florida.</p>
    <p>Rose Shepherd, Writer</p>
    <p>JOHN REESE and MORRIS MOORE</p>
    <p>These men were interviewed together in regard to their remembrances of life on the A. M. Rood "Mulberry Grove Plantation," and early history of the Yukon section.</p>
    <p>REESE: "I am the son of Joe Reese, the youngest of ten children. Our home was at Black Point, on the exact spot where Dr. C. W. Zaring has lately built his house. I am &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; years old and have lived all my life in this section. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; 'big house' where the Reed family lived faced the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;. Johns River, about three hundred feet from the water. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;t back of it was the smokehouse made of tabby-oyster&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;l and lime-and the brick kitchen where the cooking was done. All food was prepared here, put on big trays, and carried along the brick walk to the big house, where it was &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;ved. The lower part of the old kitchen is still standing.</p>
    <p>"The old road which went by the side of the first rail road tracks, went past the old plantation and my father's home, connecting Ortega and Orange Park. In some places the road was two miles from the river, in others only about half a mile. This old road to Orange Park is considerably &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of here (Woods' Garage and filling station on the Yukon Highway).</p>
    <p>"When I could first remember, there were two rows of oaks, overlapping overhear, which made a shady walk from the plantation house to the dock at the river. Those trees were set out after emancipation by a negro man. John Be&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, a fisherman, who made his living catching fish in the river and selling them to settlers of the section. There were a few mulberry trees standing in scattered sections around the house - big trees.</p>
    <p>"I would say about 900 of the 1,400 acres of the plantation was in cultivation. No cotton was raised in my time &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;t everything else that could be planted and grown on a farm was raised at mulberry Grove-corn, sugarcane, peas, beans, cats, potatoes- both sweet and white - cabbage, all kinds of garden vegetables. Mr. Rood had a big strawberry &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and there were fruit trees - pears, plums and peaches - and a big orange grove surrounded the house and lay to the east between the house and the river. Oranges were picked, crated, and shipped out on the river steamboats in considerable quantities. Always around fifty men were hired to take care of the extra work at this section. There were no slaves-everybody was paid by the day- field hands and heavy work. 50 aday, and lighter work 40.</p>
    <p>"The negroes all bought homes in the neighborhood, and being employees of Mr. Rood they had a good chance of paying for the land bought from him.</p>
    <p>"My father, Joe Reese, bought 20 acres on Black paint - the exact spot n&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;rivatoly owned by Mr. Baring. After my mother and father &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, some of us children always lived in the old house. We all worked for Mr. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;. When I was a little shaver and up to the time I was 15 years old I ran errands and out firewood and carried it to the kitchen, for cooking, and to the big house for the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and hurting stoves.</p>
    <p>"In 1910 I went over to Ortega to work for &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; who was laying out the old Sadler point plantation in building lots, cutting streets and putting in sidewalks. I worked there twelve years, thon in 1922 went to Philadelphia, doing and john for three years. I got homesick for my brothers and sisters. They seemed to know it, and played a trick on go to get me back home - told me the roof was falling in on father's old house. I rushed home to found everything in good shape, and they laughed at the joke, but I guess they wanted to see mo as bad as I did them. So I was back to stay, and an never going away again.</p>
    <p>"I bought my own place, sixty acres, and built me house - you can see it right on the corner yonder on the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; side of the road. I get work around. And I raise my own vegetables and chickens, and get along all right. I have never fussed or fought, and have never been in any trouble.</p>
    <p>"I do not know how they come to name this place 'Yukon." It had been called that ever since the Atlantic Coast nine Railroad was put through here."</p>
    <p>At this time MORRIE REESE &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;</p>
    <p>"This here section was &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; called Black point, bat the railroad people wanted a &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; name - a word with four letters. So they just took 'Yukon.' No, I don't know why - they just wanted a short &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;.</p>
    <p>"The first postmaster was J. J. knight. No lives in green cove springs. No has been in the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; but he's all right now. He has a brother and sister living at &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, and if you can't &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; him, they'll tell you where he is.</p>
    <p>"I was born at Sadier's point (Ortega) in 1862. My &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; refugeed to &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, Florida, during the war between the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, and I was a babe in arms at that time.</p>
    <p>The old Sadler house was on the point of at. Johns after, where the big brick house now is (The George &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;) when Mr. Stockton took ever the plantation - it was five thousand acres - the original home which was a big frame house, was taken down.</p>
    <p>"We case back in 1869, and is and my folks have been in this section ever since. We have always worked for ourselves.</p>
    <p>"I remember Mr. Reed and the old Road plantation of Mulberry Grove. A man by the name of C. D. Brigham came down from the north and bought 500 acres of it. He raised lots and lows of sugarcane and corn. I do not remember when or who he left. He put in a sawmill after he took over the place &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; he always raised large lots of hogs, too.</p>
    <p>"His house was on the road to the docks. He was hope in the 1870's and stayed about ten years. The land &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; bought was originally a part of the old Mulberry Grove Plantation. The land was along the river, and did not come up to this road."</p>
    <p>REESE: "Where were the old slave quarters? Well, they were a row of house on a road back of the big house - about twenty-five family houses - and it was just like a little town, with a street in the middle and houses on each side, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; all built long before the war.</p>
    <p>"The Reeds were all good to us, it was a nice place, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of work, and plenty to oat - it was the nicest place I've ever worked.</p>
    <p>"Reed Person, Mr. Reed's grandson, was such older than - he was my foreman, when I worked in the fields."</p>
    <p>MOORE: Mr. A. M. reed was a small man, rather stout Reed Pearson was about age.</p>
    <p>REESE: "The church is in the same place it has always &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, just beyond the road here. In times of slavery, the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; people did not have the privileges they do now. There were morning prayers in the big house in the dining room, but the time of our won churches came later.</p>
    <p>"&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; you hears negro hymns and spirituals - here is one I like:</p>
    <p>"I heard the voice &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; saying,</p>
    <p>'Come unto Me and rest,'</p>
    <p>Soldier of the cross</p>
    <p>In the fountain of the Lamb.' "</p>
    <p>"In certain times of the spring and summer we used to have all-day "sings," but these have gene out of style in Florida, although they still have them in Georgia.</p>
    <p>"When we were youngsters we used to have great running baseball and catball.</p>
    <p>"No, we did not ho swimming - I was nearly grown before I learned to swim. Why? Alligators! You see my father's house was between two creeks - the nearest one about two hundred yards away - and they were always alive with alligators. They seemed to have some regard for elder people but for the little children, it just wouldn't do to lot from not too close to the water's edge - they'd be snapped &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; in a second. I remember their dreadful rearing at night - was awfully seared of them. Some of us older boys used to throw good sized logs at them - bigger around than my arm, and their terrible jaws would clamp down and crush them in two in a split second.</p>
    <p>"My father was in a colored regiment during the war, and after it was ever he brought his old army musket home. The alligators were terrible about catching father's hogs. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; he would hear a hog again &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; either of &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; crocks, he would grab the old musket and light out in the direction of the noise, and bang away with the gun, often killing the alligator with the hog in its mouth. Some of them &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;oaid be ten or twelve f&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; long. You don't see big &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, like you used to.</p>
    <p>"When we used to join the river, we would bring the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; up and empty the catfish on the bank - &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; body would eat catfish in those days, sometimes there would be ten &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of them, and the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; would climb up on the banks and have a feast. I have seen them, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; big once, by the dozen, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; catfish.</p>
    <p>"In the old days there were door and wildcats in &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; woods, and the teens were so bad and there were so &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; them you could hardly raise corn or watermelons. They would &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; off the green corn and nibble it, like somebody going in rings around a &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;!</p>
    <p>"And watermelons - they would pick a nice ripe one, dig a hole through the rind, but in their saw and scrape out the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; heart and eat it by the handful. If it was a big one around and dig in from the other. When we say a melon the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; had 'Plugged,' we just left it alone, as we know it was &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; but an empty shell. Did they thump it? I don't know, but I do know that no &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; ever dug into a green watermelon."</p>
    <p>MOORE: "They used to be the moistest snakes - moccasins &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, blacksnakes - they need to be so bad you could hardly walk for them along the creeks. One morning I was coming to work about six o'clock and had to &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; - I saw a lot of &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; counted twenty-five snakes stacked up on that leg. He, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; my mind and went they up the creek and crossed on another leg.</p>
    <p>"&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, I don't remember having &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; either in this section or Mandarin. But I do remember General Grant on the steamboat Water &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; coming up the river past the plantation - it was a side-wheeler, the stern-wheel are came afterwards.</p>
    <p>"&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;at did he look like. He looked all right - he was a rather small, red-headed man.</p>
    <p>"I also remember the John Sylvester. The last time I went up the river to Palatka, I went on this boat."</p>
    <p>"The Vigilant succeeded the John Sylvester on this &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;. It was the largest of the propeller type boats - &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; screw just like the Clyde Line ships. And fast; My, she &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; eat through the water! She could out-race the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; Sylvester. Then there was the city of Jacksonville - &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; but not so fast, and the Southern Belle.</p>
    <p>"Sometimes the City of Jacksonville would come up the river and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; up at Mr. Reed's docks, and they would have the grand parties, with dancing on the boat. They always had &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; orchestras.</p>
    <p>"A lot of the produce from the plantation was shipped in Jacksonville or Sanford, and we had to put out a flag to &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; stop to take on this freight.</p>
    <p>"One of our delights, too, was the sailboat and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; races on the river, at &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; when we were not busy. Each fun, and such &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, and he the white folks would bet!</p>
    <p>"Mr. Rood had ton rules and eight horses which he used to plow the ground for farming. When there were the carriage horses which were not used in the fields, and a few others for riding purposes. About fifty man were kept busy at the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of the season. All were hired by the day, and lived in the settlement around Black Point.</p>
    <p>"My father, Joe Reese, had bargained for his twenty-fore home place and had paid a good deal on it. When the war &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; along. He joined the union forces, and after the coss&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of the war, he came back and started in just where he &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; off, planting his own garden, raising hogs, chickens, and turkeys, and we also had a cow. Mother used to buy goods by the yard and made our clothing an best she could. And we all worked and earned money and sent to Jacksonville for our shoes, coats, and caps. We went to school at Yukon.</p>
    <p>"There were a lot of pecan trees around Mr. Rood's come of the old trunks still standing. They had the nicest &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;uts - but they are like everything else, you have to culture whom if you went them to boar good.</p>
    <p>"The sugar-house was up near the old 160-acre out field. This had a furnace with big &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; where the cane juice was boiled boiled down into syrup or molasses, as we know it, and some of the big vats were left to evaporate into sugar. They used to make sugar by the barrel and sell it. It was brown sugar, of course, as they know nothing about refining it.</p>
    <p>"The dairy house &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; other way, in a line with the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;house and laundry. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; the milk was kept, and to &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; for charming.</p>
    <p>"Mr. Reed usually kept about &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;hundred head of castle in the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; - that was &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; live hundred &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; ration. He had lots of cows, and sold castle for &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; slaughtered some for use on the fa&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; The meat which could not be taken care of immediately was &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;smoked. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;ogs butchered and the neat &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; down."</p>
    <p>"I remember they did make some attempt we know &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; The grain was thrashed out &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; made on of a round stamp with the center burned out, and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; with a heavy wooden pestle. No, I don't know how &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; bread from rice flour."</p>
    <p>"My mother used to gather herbs and room to doctor the family. There was a great deal of &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; I never remember her using the palmetto berries, but she did have what was called Jerusalem Oak - a wood that grows wild in the fields - and Black Root - both of which &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; steeped and made into teas for curing fever. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; -bean leaves to cool the head, tying tge &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; around the head of a fever patient. Another &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; 'life-overlasting' because it was always green, was dead or fevers. But after patent medicines came in those old home remedical &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; used.</p>
    <p>"We need to &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; the river in bears, the overland nearly everybody &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;by &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;on."</p>
    <p>"I used to like to hunt in the early days. There was plenty of wild game - &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, bears, duels, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; You could shoot into a flock of wild down of the river and kill ton or twelve with &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of backshot.</p>
    <p>"The last time I want bear hunting &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; men and a passel of dogs, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; by ten o'clock that right we had cornered and killed two bears - measuring seven feet from tip to tip.</p>
    <p>"I saw one of then &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; for me, about forty feet away - I happened to be away from the crowd - and I sure aimed good, for I know it was either my life or his. He &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; once or twice after I shot him. There's one thing about killing a bear - you've act to kill him dead, because if he's only wounded, if &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; him had, and he'll tear up a human being or a dog that gets within his reach.</p>
    <p>"One of the men who shot the other one, it fell, he &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; ever, but the bear got up and started after him, and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; had to skin up a small tree in a hurry. And it's a good thing he picked a small tree. Because if he'd taken a big one, the bear would have &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; right up after him. Yes, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; a wounded bear is a &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; follow.</p>
    <p>The one I killed, I had to get down on my hands and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; I located him, and crawl along, the brush was so &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;I would have been scared, but I know I could depend upon my gun.</p>
    <p>"We divided up the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;took the kind log of the one I killed, but I do &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; neat - it has the&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; - so I &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of my &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;</p>
    <p>"Just after the War Neatly of deer were in this section.</p>
    <p>"I have a well at my piece, in Ortega, which was dug fifty years ago, and I've been drinking out of it was &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; It's just about the best water in the world.</p>
    <p>"The first artesian well I know of was drilled &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; house at Mulberry Grove. I do not remember about the date.</p>
    <p>"I remember when I was a young boy an old wild &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; when raised a flock of thirty young ones right in our world.</p>
    <p>"The parakeets, young green and yellow birds, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; to come in great flocks around Christmas time. They would &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; in the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;naberry trees and feast on the clusters of berries &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; were bare - usually stayings day or so, that &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; off up the St. Johns River. Some said &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; around Key most.</p>
    <p>"I do not remember every seeing any passenger &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;</p>
    <p>"Yes, I remember fishing when the big mullet use to run is schools in the river. One time I caught three &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; another time we counted seven hundred and ten.</p>
    <p>"He, we could not touch a catfish - they were Alligator food. I think that belief was founded on some teaching of the old &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;. I have heard it said - 'Don't out &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;fish without a scale.' But since the preachers preach from the New &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; it's all right - you can cat frogs, catfish, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; rattle&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;</p>
    <p>&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and bread baked over live scale brushes, cat on the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;."</p>
    <p>Asked if they would accept a treat or a cold drink, both men politely declined; also refused tobacco or cigarettes, but did finally take &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;tip.</p>
    <p>"I never &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; to sacks of the tobacco. For drink Liquor, and I don't &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; track with &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;</p>
    <p>"I remember one time when I was about ten, sure did, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; home from the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; school - it was &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; when one of the elder boys &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; few minutes &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; the trees &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;.</p>
    <p>&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; began to go round &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; when I finally get t&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; staggered into the house, and my old mummy &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;while, whatever is &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and I says, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; sick boy." I had already lost my dinner.</p>
    <p>&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; throbbing, and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; as a loon. Mummy &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; out and got some big coal&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; leaves oral bound them around &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and I get myself to bed, when I finally caught &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; some around. It was two o'clock the next morning &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; I was going in live.</p>
    <p>&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; a few years later - &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;chow of tobacco, and them &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; me reel, too. No, I guess me and tobacco just don't mis."</p>
    <p>&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, being more familiar wit, the location of the old Mulberry Grove &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; asked if us &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;</p>
    <p>&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; road build &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;zaring around the old place.</p>
    <p>More of the running of the old brick within where the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and carried to the big house further in across &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; for the river.</p>
    <p>"Up on the ridge there are some of the old &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; hence was off to the right, and the suagr&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of the slave quarters - the other did &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; is new. The stable &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;house.</p>
    <p>&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;trees were all along &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; by the river, and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; grew in the woods here by the&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;</p>
    <p>The other foundation &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; in the old smokehouse. My Yashor lived up there at Black Point, and after he mother died, some of the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;have always lived there.</p>
    <p>" We will show you the old &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; Park-Road." (We were &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; to the highway). &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;been ploughed ever, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; the here where the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; trucks have been &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; to Rood's &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; well, the old Orange Park &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; ont right along &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; side of the railroad right-&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;</p>
    <p>Years ago we used &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; all this section &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; would raise several &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; a year. It was much &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; then, and the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; would grow tall and tassle, which ot &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; nowadays, a used to have new sweet potatoes in May.</p>
    <p>&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;things grow. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; then there was not a &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; how - the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; cut down and there is he &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;</p>
    <p>"The smokehouse &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;places was built after the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; it was before my time, but I have a brother &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;he remembers it. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; Rood Pearson &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; years elder than he - they &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and I have heard Mr. Rood Pearson say he remembers &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; smokehouse being built when he was little boy.</p>
    <p>"I will try to get &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; to write &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; we used to sing."</p>
    <p>By this time we had reached his small homestead and asked to get out, rather then go on to the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; at taken where the interview was began, and was most ready and willing to give any other information decided.</p>
  </text>
</history>
