<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../lifehistory.xsl" ?>
<history>
  <title>Miss Sallie's Cook</title>
  <reflink>https://dc.lib.unc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/03709/id/1116</reflink>
  <meta>
    <item>
      <key>Date</key>
      <val>1939-03-02</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Location</key>
      <val>Columbia, South Carolina</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Occupations</key>
      <val>cook</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Interviewee</key>
      <val>Annie Squire (black; female)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Writer</key>
      <val>Verner Lea (white; female)</val>
    </item>
  </meta>
  <text>
    <p>Approximately 3,200 words</p>
    <p>SOUTH CAROLINA WRITERS' PROJECT</p>
    <p>LIFE HISTORY</p>
    <p>TITLE: MISS SALLIE'S COOK</p>
    <p>Date of First Writing  March 2 , 1939</p>
    <p>Name of Person Interviewed  Annie Squire (Negro)</p>
    <p>Fictitious Name  Ruby Childs</p>
    <p>Street Address  1222 Barnwell Street </p>
    <p>Place  Columbia, S. C.</p>
    <p>Occupation  Cook</p>
    <p/>
    <p>Name of Writer  Verner Lea</p>
    <p>Name of Reviser  State Office</p>
    <p/>
    <p>On approaching my destination, I heard a conversation taking place</p>
    <p>between Ruby and her neighbor, which ran something like this: "Sister</p>
    <p>Jasper, was you at the Ebenezer Baptist, Sunday night gone?"</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Ruby, I ain't been to that church since the argument I told you 'bout.</p>
    <p>What's more, I'm thinkin' 'bout joinin' up wid the Methodist. Anybody 'cuse</p>
    <p>me of short changing the plate, I figure they's all crooks. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Ef I'd had a piece o' extra change I would o' been glad to give 'em</p>
    <p>the whole quarter.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Well, when I put my quarter in the plate, I took out fifteen cent</p>
    <p>chance. Brother Sikes argue me up and down. He stood there and let all</p>
    <p>the congregation hear him call me a thief and a liar. Said after I put</p>
    <p>in the twenty-five cent, I didn't take our a dime and a nickle, but 'stead,</p>
    <p>I took back the quarter, and ten cent beside.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I told him he's so crooked he oughter sleep on a corkscrew. Then</p>
    <p>I put on my coat and switched out, and don't aim to never go back."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Well, what I mean to tell you, Sister Jasper, there was sho' some</p>
    <p>cuttin' up Sunday night gone.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Everybody was settin' there quiet-like, and Parson Brown was leadin'</p>
    <p>in prayer. All of a sudden we heard the awfullest goin's on just outside</p>
    <p>the church door. Such a hollering, cussin', and carryin' on you never did</p>
    <p>hear. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"First thing you know, Parson Brown's boy come splittin' up the aisle</p>
    <p>cryin' to the top o' his voice, and a-holdin' on to his ear. He run up to</p>
    <p>his pa, grab him round the legs, and holler and cry 'til he near 'bout broke</p>
    <p>up the meetin'.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Him and dat little sinner, Coon, got to arguin' over a bottle o' pop.</p>
    <p>Finally, they got to fightin', and Coon near 'bout chewed Jake's ear off.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I don't see what makes Jake hang around Coon so much, 'cause they</p>
    <p>ain't nothin' but trouble when them two gets together.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"But you know that preacher turn it all off so smooth-like. He say,</p>
    <p>'Set down, Son. I'll anoint your soul, and your ear will be all right.'</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"He had done already choose his text, but he 'pologised to the congregation. </p>
    <p>He told 'em he was awful embarrassed about Jake and Coon, but boys</p>
    <p>would be boys. And seein' what had jus' took place, he was gonna preach on</p>
    <p>peace. Keepin' the peace.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"He preached one o' the finest sermons I ever hear. He sent one</p>
    <p>o' the ushers out to get Coon. But Coon done lit out up a alley wid the</p>
    <p>bottle o' pop. He was makin' tracks for home.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I been a member o' that church for many a year, but that was 'bout</p>
    <p>the best piece o' preachin' I ever hear Parson Brown put out yet.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Jake, he jus' set there, with tears in his eyes, like the spirit was</p>
    <p>comin' on him. He's a puny little fellow, and Coon ain't got no right to</p>
    <p>be always jumpin' on him.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>As this dialogue came to an end, I arose from my temporary seat on</p>
    <p>the steps. Walking around the side of the house, I found Ruby busily engaged </p>
    <p>in hanging out clothes. As she turned and saw me, her greeting was</p>
    <p>one of genuine welcome.</p>
    <p/>
    <p> "How you, Mis' Polly? Lord, child, I ain't had a chance to clean my</p>
    <p>house yet. Take this chair on the porch. We'll jus' set here in the sun."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>Although I had known Ruby for a number of years, and she had often</p>
    <p>helped me in various ways in my house, our acquaintance had never gone beyond </p>
    <p>the surface.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>She is a typical Negro: fat, good-natured, and very black, with lips</p>
    <p>that resemble toy balloons. Her optimism is a trait worthy of note. Just</p>
    <p>one of Ruby's ridiculous remarks will cast a rosy glow, where formerly all</p>
    <p>was blue. She is always dressed in a blue uniform and white apron, with</p>
    <p>the proverbial rag tied around her kinky black head. Her perpetual grin</p>
    <p>displays three prominent gold teeth. Though thirty-five years old,</p>
    <p>she sticks to her socks, winter and summer. Sometimes, in very cold</p>
    <p>weather, she wears hose. But even then, the socks must come on, too.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Mis' Polly, you'll be thinkin' I'm a trifling housekeeper. But I</p>
    <p>had to get these clothes out. I generally keeps my three rooms right tidy.</p>
    <p>I woulder been through, but Sister Jasper been sick. I had to pass her</p>
    <p>the news over the back fence, 'cause she can't get out. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Jus' me and my brother Bud live here. He works on a W.P.A. job and</p>
    <p>pays half the rent and half o' everything. Ever now and then he buys me</p>
    <p>a dress or hat or some sort o' little gift for a surprise. He's one more</p>
    <p>good boy. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"No, God! I ain't got no husband. And what's more, I don't want one.</p>
    <p>I had one o' them things once. But I sho' ain't lookin' for no more.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I don't like to think and talk about them days, Mis' Polly. When I</p>
    <p>do, I gets a misery in my head. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I was born in St. Matthews, South Carolina. Ma died when I was four</p>
    <p>years old. My pa was Amos Giles, and he wan't nothin' to brag on, either.</p>
    <p>When I was eleven, me and Pa and Bud come to Columbia. Pa got a job at the</p>
    <p>Blume Lumber Company.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"We done pretty well for awhile. But it wan't long 'til Pa got to</p>
    <p>drinkin', goin' out nights and keepin' bad company. 'Seem like he start</p>
    <p>hoppin' on me for any little thing. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I was little, but I tried to do the best I know how. I'd stay home,</p>
    <p>cook his meals, and wash his and Bud's clothes. But jus' seem like didn't</p>
    <p>nothin' suit him no more. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"All that time, I was tryin' to get a little education, too. The most</p>
    <p>I ever got, though, was jus' a inklin' of readin' and writin'. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Pa was all the time after me about gettin' out and findin' work.</p>
    <p>look like heap o' times he try to be good to me. But he jus' couldn't help   </p>
    <p>bein' mean. Sometimes, he act jus' like Satan was backin' him up.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"One night he jus' fuss and wrangle wid me half the night. The</p>
    <p>next day when I come from school, he was settin' on the porch. I set</p>
    <p>down on the doorstep and never said nothin'. After while, he say: 'Ain't</p>
    <p>you hungry?" </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Reckon he thought I'd have a nerve to eat his food. He got up,</p>
    <p>walked back in the kitchen, and brought me a big plate o' collards, corn</p>
    <p>bread, and sweet potatoes. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Seem like after I ate, I feel kinder sorry for him. So I got up,</p>
    <p>went inside, cleaned up the house good, and ironed him a shirt and a pair</p>
    <p>o' blue jeans. Then I build up the fire and got his supper hot and lit the</p>
    <p>lamp and called him to come eat. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"When he come in, he was lit up like a church. I didn't say nothin'.</p>
    <p>But he hadn't hardly set down, before he got to abusin' me for everything</p>
    <p>he could think of. Call me lazy and triflin' and good for nothin'. Keep</p>
    <p>wantin' to know how come I don't get me a job like Bud.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Course it's true Bud did get a job. But after he got it, Pa made it</p>
    <p>so hot for him he lef' home. Anyhow, Pa talk and cuss so I couldn't stand</p>
    <p>it no longer. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"After while I say: 'I'm sorry Pa, I'll leave home. I'll go on back</p>
    <p>to St. Matthews. I'll go stay with Aunt Lizzie. She's gettin old, maybe</p>
    <p>I can be of some service to her. I can feed her pig, and wash, and relieve </p>
    <p>her of some o' her work. Do enough so I won't feel imposin' on nobody.' </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Pa got up, staggered over to the shelf, and took his last drink o'</p>
    <p>brandy. Then he went to bed." </p>
    <p/>
    <p>Ruby sat alone, with tear dimmed-eyes, and thought. Finally, she</p>
    <p>retrieved a worn and battered suitcase from under the bed. She dusted</p>
    <p>it off and began packing her worldly goods, which consisted of little more</p>
    <p>than a few torn and tattered garments. This done, she, too, retired.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>She would sleep until day, then go to the garage where Bud worked.</p>
    <p>He would find her a way to Aunt Lizzie's. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>The following morning, Amos awoke to an irregular ticking of an</p>
    <p>ancient and battered timepiece, which he found on this occasion most</p>
    <p>annoying to his head. He had a mind to shout for Ruby. Maybe she could</p>
    <p>do something to ease his misery. But he didn't hear Ruby moving about the</p>
    <p>house, as was her custom of a morning. As the fog began to lift, and his</p>
    <p>brain showed signs of normal functioning, he recollected drowsily, "Poor</p>
    <p>Ruby, maybe she ain't here anymore. What was that she said last night</p>
    <p>about leaving?" </p>
    <p/>
    <p>Dressing himself with jittery, nervous hands, he went into the kitchen.</p>
    <p>Instead of the warmth of the cook stove, and the aroma of good, hot coffee,</p>
    <p>everything was cold, bare, and lifeless. On the table he found a note.</p>
    <p>With trembling fingers he opened and read the following: "Dear Pa, when</p>
    <p>you reads this, I'll be on my way to Aunt Lizzie's. Take care of yourself.</p>
    <p>I hopes you make out all right. Ruby." </p>
    <p/>
    <p>As Amos struggled with the fire in the cook stove and prepared his</p>
    <p>frugal breakfast, he began to think that Ruby wasn't such a bad girl after</p>
    <p>all. He reproached himself for his mean and low-life ways, saying to himself, </p>
    <p>"I'll write her a letter and tell her I'm sorry and want her to come</p>
    <p>on back. She's just thirteen years old. Too young to be out on her own.</p>
    <p>Yes, I'll write poor little Rube a letter."     </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"After I lef', I got to goin' with a man right smart older than me.</p>
    <p>Be seem like a nice man, and we kept company right regular. He kept after</p>
    <p>me to marry him. He tell me how good he would be to me and how he'd make</p>
    <p>up for all the trouble I'd had at home. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Well, long 'bout Christmas time, I let his persuadin' ways and big</p>
    <p>talk do the devilment. I wasn't but fourteen years old. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"We got us a room in a roomin' house and lived together four months</p>
    <p>to the day. He picked up and lef' me high and dry, and me with a unborn</p>
    <p>child. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Seem like me bein' young, I jus' cry day and night. I didn't know</p>
    <p>what to do, me with no job and no nothin'. The people in the house treat</p>
    <p>me kind for awhile. I guess they was sorry for me.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I'd go out every day and pick a little cotton. But seem like that</p>
    <p>didn't pay me nothin' hardly. The people in the house got to howlin' for</p>
    <p>their room rent. I near 'bout went crazy. I jus' didn't have no heart for</p>
    <p>nothin'. Many a time I come near to perishin'. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I figured I'd better go on back to Aunt Lizzie, 'cause it was gettin'</p>
    <p>most time.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I prayed the lord to soften her heart, to see to it that she'd forgive</p>
    <p>me for skippin' off with that bastard. She told me he wan't up to no good.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I got there late one Saturday afternoon. Bein' scared and timid-like,</p>
    <p>I knock on the door easy. When she open it, she put her hands on her fat</p>
    <p>hips and jus' look at me long and hard. Then she say, 'chickens always comes</p>
    <p>home to roost. But you'll sho' have to find you another roostin' place. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"She say I made my bed, and in it I'd have to lie. Then my feet jus'</p>
    <p>come out from under me. I dropped on the doorstep and near 'bout sob my</p>
    <p>heart out. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"She went back in and slam the door. Lef' me settin' there 'bout</p>
    <p>a hour. Then she come back and hand me a dipper of cold spring water. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"'Drink this, then come on in the cook room and get you some supper.</p>
    <p>If you walked all the way, I guess you most famished, and wore out, too.</p>
    <p>I got spoon bread, come nice spareribs, and a pot o' rutabagas.'"</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"With this evidence of Aunt Lizzie's big, kind heart and relenting</p>
    <p>spirit, Ruby dried her tears. She followed her meekly into the kitchen.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"'Set down and eat now. No use cryin' over spilt milk.'</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"The very next day my poor little youngun was born. But jus' live</p>
    <p>two hours. You see it was too previous.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"My own mother couldn't a been better to me than Aunt Lizzie. She</p>
    <p>was so good and kind. I lay there with tears in my eyes. I made up my</p>
    <p>mind if the Lord spared me I'd repay her.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"It was her goodness to me that made me see everything different-like.</p>
    <p>"When I got able, I relieved her of all the work I could. I learned to</p>
    <p>sew, and would keep her clothes patched. One time Bud sent me a little</p>
    <p>money, and I bought her a dress.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"God bless her! She's dead now, but I know she res' in heavenly</p>
    <p>peace.            </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"When I was seventeen, I got a letter from Bud sayin' Pa was dead.</p>
    <p>I come on back to Columbia. I got me a good job as cook. I cooked for</p>
    <p>that family five years. Then they moved to Charleston. I've done different </p>
    <p>things. I had me a job with the W.P.A. for awhile. I raked up</p>
    <p>leaves and trash in Valley Park. But I've cooked mostly all my life. I'm</p>
    <p>cookin' for a fine family of folks now. I been workin' for Mrs. Sallie </p>
    <p>Jenkins for three years. Mis' Sallie sho' good to me. She give me</p>
    <p>clothes and food and lets me off ever other Sunday. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"These people is God-like. They goes to church ever Sunday, and</p>
    <p>to prayer meetin', too. You never soe 'em set down to eat without sayin'</p>
    <p>a blessin'. They got two fine head o' chillun. Just as nice and polite</p>
    <p>as any I ever see. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"You know Mis' Sallio is forewoman of a sewin' room project. She</p>
    <p>must have a sight in that room. I laughs at the things she tells me</p>
    <p>sometime.  </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"She say ever since she boen there, she hafter get up and make this</p>
    <p>same speech ever mornin':  </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"'Now, Ladies, there is to be no smoking, chewin', or dippin' on the</p>
    <p>project. Anybody caught disobeyin' these rules will be cut off.' </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"But Mis' Sallie so good, she makes sho' not to catch 'em. She sho'</p>
    <p>had to shut her eyes one time, though. It was a Monday mornin', and she</p>
    <p>wasn't feelin' so good. Reckon her nerves was jus' shot. She called the</p>
    <p>nurse and told her to go through all the machine drawers. Told the ladies</p>
    <p>to jus' set still. When the nurse got to old Mis' Minnie Grime's machine,</p>
    <p>that old lady got to shakin' like a leaf. Made out one of the drawers was</p>
    <p>stuck. But the nurse took it and give it a jerk. She found Mrs. Grimes'</p>
    <p>tobacco and, what's more, a jar o' tobacco juice. Mis' Minnie jus' cried</p>
    <p>and carried on, and Mis' Sallie didn't have the heart to do nothin' to the</p>
    <p>poor soul. She been chewin' all her life. Reckon that's 'bout all the</p>
    <p>pleasure she gets. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Mis' Sallie said she use to start the day off by readin' the Scripture </p>
    <p>and sayin' the Lord's Prayer. Seem like that done 'em all good. But </p>
    <p>she got orders from headquarters to cut it out. Said they was there</p>
    <p>to work and not to pray. There wasn't no time for such as that. If they</p>
    <p>didn't turn out two and three pair o' pants a day, all the prayin' in the</p>
    <p>world wouldn't bind their jobs. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Mis' Sallie hate it so when they make 'em quit prayin'. She said</p>
    <p>that look so ungodly. No wonder people gettin' so tough, and jus' bankslidin' </p>
    <p>all the time.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"My road ain't been clear sailin', but I'm tryin' to improve my ways. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I say go forward. If you can't go forward, it's better to balk like</p>
    <p>a mule in a creek. Just stand still and think over the thing awhile. First</p>
    <p>thing you know, you goin' straight. But for God's sake don't go backwards.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Mis' Sallie worryin' her head 'bout this relief now. She say they</p>
    <p>gonna cut off a heap of 'em. Well, I hope they don't cut her off. If they</p>
    <p>cuts her off, then I'll get cut off, too. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Bud, say he hear talk o' cuttin' out his project. What will the</p>
    <p>people do? That's like wreckin' the ship in midstream befo' it gets where</p>
    <p>it's goin'.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Well, all I can say is trust in the Lord and pray. The Scripture say</p>
    <p>prayer will sho' take us where we goin'. And I'm bound for the Promise Land."      </p>
  </text>
</history>
