<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../lifehistory.xsl" ?>
<history>
  <title>Untitled</title>
  <reflink>https://dc.lib.unc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/03709/id/1105</reflink>
  <meta>
    <item>
      <key>Date</key>
      <val>1936-02-27</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Location</key>
      <val>Jacksonville, Florida</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Interviewee</key>
      <val>W. C. B. Sollee (white; male)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Writer</key>
      <val>Rose Shepherd (white; female)</val>
    </item>
  </meta>
  <text>
    <p>Rose Shephred</p>
    <p>February 27, 1936</p>
    <p>Interview # 23.</p>
    <p>&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;</p>
    <p>Mr. W. C. B. Pollee,</p>
    <p>(Resident of Jacksonville since the early 80's).</p>
    <p>2608 Park St.</p>
    <p>Jacksonville, Florida.</p>
    <p>Mr. Sollee came to Jacksonville from Savannah, Georgia, in the early 80's, about 1833 or 1884, shortly after his father's death. Jacksonville was then nothing more than a small country village, with a population of from 12,000 to 15,000. In the Winter, visitors from the north and east swelled this number to 50,000 or 80,000.</p>
    <p>Mr. Sollee says: "Our transportation facilities at that time were very meager. There were throe Railroads operating in Jacksonville: The Plant System, the F. R. &amp; N. Ry. from &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, and a short line from Fernandina to Jacksonville. Our visitors from the Atlantic States via the Sea, took a train in to the Jacksonville Depot, which was located at what is now near the feet of Washington Street, where Hogans\Creek empties into 'the. St.. Johns River.</p>
    <p>"There were no paved streets in Jacksonville. The only side walks were on Bay Street, and a few plank walks on Forsyth Street, Most of the buildings on Forsyth Street were just shacks. Main Street, then known as "Pine Street," was the business section running north to Forsyth Street, while the eastern &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; was Ocean street, and the western, Julia Street. The majority of the retail stores were on the north side of Bat street, with the wholesale district on the south side next to</p>
    <p>&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;</p>
    <p>"On people came to Jacksonville in those early days and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;ough Florida, their only means of transportation was &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; Johns River, the Bays and the Post Line of Steamboats operating from Jacksonville to Sanford. Of the Bay steamers, the H. T. Bays Line Boat was called "The Sylvan Glen" while the post &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; only passenger steamer was called "The Sylvan Glen" while the post &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; only passenger steamer was called "the John Sylvester."</p>
    <p>They also called at Palatka and other intermediate points.</p>
    <p>&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; first Railroad line we had out of Jacksonville was about 1885, then a corporation was formed and the narrow-gauge railroad was &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; from Jacksonville to St. Augustine, known as the Jacksonville St. Augustine and Halifax River Railroad." There for a ferry operating across the St. Johns River at that time to connect with that Railroad.</p>
    <p>The &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; part of 1886, the J. T. and K. W. Railroad was opened for traffic between Jacksonville and Palatka. That was broad-gauge railroad. After the latter road was built, thousands of tourists would take that road to Palatka and connect there with the narrow-gauge railroad known as the Florida-Southern, operating between Palatka and Brooksville through the intermediate points of Leesburg, Waldo, Ocala, and other terms.</p>
    <p>"Other tourists who desired to go direct to the source of the St. Johns River to Sanford, took the Steamers from Palatka. In the other hand, there were thousands of tourists who wished to visit the "Ancient City" of the St. Augustine, who took the train from South Jacksonville direct to St. Augustine and after spends &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; a while there, would take the narrow-gauge railroad from the Augustine to a little settlement on the eastern banks &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; Tocoz." There they would connect with the stea&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; further south to Sanford. A good many visitors also took stages down to the Halifax and Indian River Sections.</p>
    <p>"About this period there was another little railroad running from Sanford to Titusville. From Titusville, they took a boat down the Indian River to Cocoa, Melbourne, and other points in that part. Most of the transportation was by small vessels called "Smocks."</p>
    <p>DEVELOPMENT OF THE &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;</p>
    <p>"About 1886, a narrow-gauge railroad was built from Sanford to Tampas, known as the South Florida Railroad. A branch line from plant City to Bartow was built, and another branch line from Lakeland to connect with the Florida-Southern at Leesburg.</p>
    <p>ORANGE CULTURE</p>
    <p>"The nearest orange growing center to Jacksonville was at Mandarin. There were a good many groves around Homosassa, West of Ocals, with &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; few groves of note along the Ocklawaha River which was navigated by small storn-wheeler boats about 33 feet or 40 feet long. The Ocklawaha was full of stamps, snags and other impedi&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;nts. When these small steamers had to negotiate a bend which was very abrupt, a man would be placed in the stern and another in the bow of the boat and they would throw a rose around a stump. In this manner the boat was pulled around a sharp bend of the river. These boats operated between these towns on down to Silver Springs.</p>
    <p>"Along the present line of the Atlantic Coast Line Railway between Palatka and DeLand, there were several very fine orange groves, also in the Seville and Pomona sections, and through the surrounding territory. Most of the prominent groves in Florida about this date were along the Indian River - points like Merritt Island, Cocoa, and Rockledge. Orange from this section at that time were world famous. There were also orange groves of prominence in that is known as the "Lake Region," around the present cities of Orlando, Winter Park, Winter Haven Lake City.</p>
    <p>Growers in those days had considerable trouble in getting their &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;it to market, and many living in the interior of the State the northern Markets, or to Tampa from which point they had to ship by boats going around the Peninsula.</p>
    <p>One of the biggest industries at that time along the Indian River was the pineapple business. Thousands and thousamds &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; were shipped to various marts - North, East and West.</p>
    <p>JACKSONVILLE IN THE EARLY 80's.</p>
    <p>"In the early 80's there were only a few hotels of any prominence in Jacksonville - the Windsor, the St. James, (the present location of Cohen Bros. Store) the Carleton House East Bay Street, and the Everett, on the corner of Julia and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; There were a great number of small semi-hotels and roaming houses for the accommodation of tourists.</p>
    <p>"There were no parks at that time except "Hemming Park, which was not the beauty spot it is today. There were a few walks transversing the Park, and the board sidewalks all &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; the block. Along the edge for ornamental purposes were a row of "sour" orange trees. The fruit was large and luscious looking, but not fit to eat.</p>
    <p>"There were two street car lines, one of which operated from the south end of Main Street (or Pine Street as it was known then) out to about the present site of the water-works. These cars would accommodate from 12 to 15 persons and were &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;. There was no paving on Pine Street. There &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; few &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; walks as far as Adams Street, but beyond that &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; was nothing but sand - Bay Street the same way. In 1887 bay Street was paved with cypress blocks 6" to 7" in diameter, which was "City fathers" of that day took considerable pride, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; it was not very satisfactory.</p>
    <p>&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;OF THE Y.M.C.A</p>
    <p>"In the latter part of 1886, the young men and boys of &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; got together and organized the Young Mens' Christian association. I was one of the original organizers, and we did &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; for the purpose of aiding these in Sedentary occupations and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; ines of work, who felt the need to some systematic &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; culture. We were so successful that is the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of 1387, we had a membership of around 700. We &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; New York City and secured a physical instructor. The &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; third floors over the establishment of the S. B. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; Hardware Company on Pine Street, opposite Furchgott's were secured for our quarters. The second floor was occupied by reading and writing rooms, executive offices, reception &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; while the third floor was splendidly equipped as a &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; met three times a week - Mondays, Wednesdays and Fridays, receiving practical instructions in physical culture, which I few one can say saved my life, as at the beginning. I was considerably under weight -110 lbs., and in three months had gained twenty pounds. After training, we would give exhibits during the tourist season at the old Park Theatre - where the western Union Building now stores.</p>
    <p>NEGRO POLICE OFFICERS.</p>
    <p>"In the early days Florida's Republican majority installed negro police officers in Jacksonville. The collector was a negro, and we had a negro judge of the Police Court. We boys used to play all manner of tricks on the negro policemen.</p>
    <p>"I well remember that just before the yellow fever epidemic of 1888, when I would go calling &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; evening - it was in the Fall, in September - great flying black beetles were very annoying, striking one in the face on alighting on the clothing, and many of the other citizens predicated they were the forerunner of some &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;</p>
    <p>"When the yellow plague was declared epidemic, people left Jacksonville by the hundreds. They went down to the old Plant System Depot - located at that is now the foot of the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; the trains pulled out they were jummed to the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; refugees - packing the platforms, hanging on to the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and even clambering up on the tops of the cars. In &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; the residences of my friends, which I went through &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; secure, I found food in vessels ready to cook, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; partially emptied and left wide open, and other &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of the panic-stricken to palace. Jacksonville was practically &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; But when the call for help for the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; the response was instant - friends sent money &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; supplies, physicians and nurses, who &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; on duty, many of them making the supreme &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; Borter, the State Wealth Officer, from Key West &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and took change, and then there was Doctor Neal Mitchell's home &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; Peninsular Life Building now stands, corner of Forsyth the Julie Streets, and Dr. Porter's office was in the Aragon Hotel.</p>
    <p>As depot where the provisions, medicines, clothing and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;necessary supplies were stored was in a warehouse at the foot &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; Street, towards the River, Sometime in October, when the fever had been raging for several weeks, some of the colored citizenry in the Hansontown section, got the idea of making a raid on the supply house, and went down about a thousand strong to press their demands, and help themselves. In order to protect the warehouse, the authorities had the Wilson Battery, a local protective association, under the direct com&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; George C. Wilson, go to the premises; and while a great many of these volunteers had left the city at the beginning of the epidemic, those who remained gathered valiantly around their Captain with slugs, shot and ten-penny nails. This information was destroyed to the insurgents, who were further informed that &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; would be instantaneous with the first move in the direction from supplies. Thus peace prevailed, and what looked &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; the beginning of a bad riot was averted, and the colored men &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; back to their homes after being assured that in due &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; they would receive their apportionment of clothing, medicines, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and other supplies.</p>
    <p>AMUSEMENTS AND SOCIAL ACTIVITIES. (During the 80's).</p>
    <p>"In this period there were in Jacksonville about thirty couple - &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; young people - or the some social status, who &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; up &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; parties, one of the principal sources of &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; being horse-back riding. There were quite a number of &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; every stables in the city, and so many of the girls &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; proprietors specialized in fine riding horses, so that satisfactory mounts were always available at short notice. Often 15 or &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; would gather for a canter over the roads around Jacksonville, the principal route being the old "Ten-Mike" drive out Pine from Bay Street, around the Cemetery, over Falley &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; to town, which was exactly 10 miles.</p>
    <p>"Again &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;could gather at the boat-house at the foot of Washington &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and row up the St. Johns River in the evening, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; as far as 10 miles. He had plenty of musical &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and the boats would be lashed together and we would sing and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; back town in the moonlight. We were sure to be in &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; homes before midnight.</p>
    <p>Sometimes during the summer time, we would engage a small steam-boats and give a moonlight excursion to Mayport, where we would land and dance for an hour on &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; There were no improvements and no developments at the Beaches, and nothing at Mayport but a Back and a medium-sized dancing pavilion.</p>
    <p>Other times we would go to Green Cove, Springs, Magnolia, or Orange Park, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; achiever destination was decided by popular vote. We always had plenty of chaperones - this was an &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; Parents never &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; letting their young &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; these excursions, because they knew every social &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; would be provided and their comfort lacked after - &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; ster and his wife were members of our parties, en&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; simple pleasures.</p>
    <p>&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; one time there was an ambitious Hotel opened &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; known as Burnside, a small hosterly of about 14 rooms, where I held forth as clerk. But it was a very matter of fact place as compared &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;ficent hotels &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; who &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; before was nothing to do but take a dip and walk for &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; while on the beach, and a very short while at that, an &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; quited, were present in large numbers and most annoying.</p>
    <p>In 1889, I went to Savannah, after the yellow fever sp&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; not return to Jacksonville until after the big &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; 1901.</p>
    <p>"It &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; been my pleasure to wi&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;ess the development of Jacksonville into a city compatible with the best of its size anywhere. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; to also see South Jacksonville come up from a small village of 300 residents to its present attractive attainments and expansion into well laid-out suburbs with magni&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;ioert homes.</p>
  </text>
</history>
