<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../lifehistory.xsl" ?>
<history>
  <title>Sally's Premonition</title>
  <reflink>https://dc.lib.unc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/03709/id/1116</reflink>
  <meta>
    <item>
      <key>Date</key>
      <val>1939-01-05</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Location</key>
      <val>Columbia, South Carolina</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Occupations</key>
      <val>cook</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Interviewee</key>
      <val>Estelle Williams (black; female)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Pseudonym</key>
      <val>Sallie Jones</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Writer</key>
      <val>Verner Lea (white; female)</val>
    </item>
  </meta>
  <text>
    <p>Approximately 3,500 words</p>
    <p>SOUTH CAROLINA WRTIER' PROJECT</p>
    <p>LIFE HISTORY</p>
    <p>TITLE:  SALLY'S PREMONITION</p>
    <p>Date of First Writing  January 5, 1939</p>
    <p>Name of Person Interviewed   Estelle Williams</p>
    <p>Fictitious Name   Sally Jones</p>
    <p>Street Address  1706 Thompson Street</p>
    <p>Place  Columbia, South Carolina</p>
    <p>Occupation  Cook</p>
    <p>Name of Writer  Verner Lea</p>
    <p>Name of Revisor   State Office </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Miss Polly, you 'member dat boy I told you 'bout dat was so nice</p>
    <p>to me durin' de Fair? Well, on my way home yesterday, I met him up to</p>
    <p>de fillin' station. Said he was on his way down here to see me. His</p>
    <p>name is Joe. I didn't know him at first, he was so dressed up. I</p>
    <p>fixin' to pass him by, when he reach out his hand and say, 'It's me,</p>
    <p>Sally. Dis is Joe.' </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"He's a sight in dis world. He 'companied me on home, and we set</p>
    <p>and talked a long time. He told me all 'bout his old auntie. You know</p>
    <p>he been livin' wid her ever since he was five year old. Joe say she done</p>
    <p>a sight o' wranglin' when he mention comin' back to Columbia. Say he sho'</p>
    <p>had to work his head and lead up to dis town easy-like. Aunt Lizzie</p>
    <p>think his trip to de State Fair ruint him. She say she never was one for</p>
    <p>turnin' chillun loose in de city. She holds de country is de place for</p>
    <p>chillun. Say all dey ever gets out o' de city is high falutin' airs and</p>
    <p>notions. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"So Joe he jes' honor and wait on her and try to keep her pleased</p>
    <p>'til he felt safe to tell her his plans. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"He weeded a patch o' ground for her and got taters and onions and</p>
    <p>de like planted. Ever time she'd tell him to grab de hoe and sing, he</p>
    <p>would sho' do it. He say he got so in de habit o' singin' 'til he most</p>
    <p>sing in his sleep:</p>
    <p/>
    <p>Nothin' to live for</p>
    <p>Jes' one time to die;</p>
    <p>Nigger does de work</p>
    <p>White folks gits de pie.</p>
    <p>Spare me dear Lord,</p>
    <p>For some o' dat dessert;</p>
    <p>Den I don't give a d - - -</p>
    <p>Ef I do git hurt.   </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"He say Aunt Lizzie brag on his choppin' and singin' so, he figgered</p>
    <p>de time was 'bout right to tell her his aims. So late de other evenin'</p>
    <p>she told him to run down de road and git some 'bacco, and when he come back</p>
    <p>dey would eat. He say she 'pear like she wus in right good spirits; so,</p>
    <p>after dey et, he tell her he's got a little confidence he wants to tell her. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"When he told her dat, she got the notion he had done bin tuk up. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"He laugh, and say, 'No, ma'am, it ain't nothin' like dat. Jes' a</p>
    <p>plan I been aimin' to tell you ever since I come from Columbia.' Aunt</p>
    <p>Lizzie say: 'Now here you go talkin' 'bout dat place agin. For de good</p>
    <p>Lord's sake, tell me what's down dere you so crazy 'bout. Ain't we got</p>
    <p>de same things 'round here or 'bouts? What is it, son? I'm tired o'</p>
    <p>you sittin' dere beatin' 'bout de bush.' </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Den he told her 'bout meetin' me down here at de Fair, and he jes'</p>
    <p>couldn't get no res' for studyin' 'bout me. Told her I was smart and had</p>
    <p>a job cookin', and he like my sparklin' eyes and straight black hair,</p>
    <p>'cause it shine so pretty. He told me, when he saw me yesterday, to come</p>
    <p>stan' up side him, 'cause he'd told Aunt Lizzie I jos' come under his arm,</p>
    <p>and he want to see wuz he tellin' de truth. He carries on a sight o'</p>
    <p>foolishness.  </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Aunt Lizzie told him ef he couldn't get no res', and didn't aim to</p>
    <p>give her none, to stop down to Sudie's and see would she stay wid her while</p>
    <p>he's gone. He say when he walked through de field Sa'day, carryin' his old</p>
    <p>worn-out suitcase, he had a reg'lar lump in his throat. He felt like he</p>
    <p>wuz gonna choke when he looked back and waved at Aunt Lizzie and Fudie.</p>
    <p>They wuz standin' in de door of de little shack, and watched him out o'</p>
    <p>sight. He say dey look so low in spirits he holler back and say:</p>
    <p/>
    <p>'Nothin' to live for</p>
    <p>Jus' one time to die.'</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"'Bout twenty minutes after he got to de big road, a man come along</p>
    <p>on a truck and rode him all de way to town. Joe say people sho' is in a</p>
    <p>hurry to git where dey's goin' in dis town. He first thought dey wus</p>
    <p>another fair down here.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"He say he been thinkin' 'bout me ever since de las' time he see me.</p>
    <p>He starts workin' at de fillin' station Monday. Mr. Jones, de operator,</p>
    <p>say he'll pay him five dollars a week and let him sleep on a cot joinin'</p>
    <p>de station. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"What I wants to tell you, Joe wants me to marry him after he's</p>
    <p>been there long enough to save a little money. He say it'll be nice for</p>
    <p>us to take a little honeymoon. Least long as de money las'. He say he</p>
    <p>ain't never see anybody he'd ruther take for his lawful wife. I b'lieves</p>
    <p>I do love him, Miss Polly. Course he do carry on a heap o' foolishness,</p>
    <p>but I can tell he's a good boy. I thinks he'll be good to me. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"He say when de preacher marries us, he reckon he'll think we's de</p>
    <p>long and de short. Joe, he's over six feet high. But I likes a tall man. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I told him it make me mighty proud what he say 'bout me. Dat I'd</p>
    <p>ask you 'bout it, 'cause you wuz always good to 'vise me. I told him I</p>
    <p>'spect you'd like to see him so's to pass judgment. Den if you likes his</p>
    <p>ways, we plan to marry three weeks from dis comin' Sa'day." </p>
    <p/>
    <p>After a honeymoon of four days, Sally showed up an animated and</p>
    <p>happy bride.  </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Miss Polly, dere wan't but one thing to upset our pleasure. When</p>
    <p>Joe come as far as de fillin' station wid me dis mornin', Mr. Jones say</p>
    <p>he done got somebody else on de job. He say Joe had business to let him</p>
    <p>know his plans. Course, dis worry Joe pow'ful bad, so he out scratchin'</p>
    <p>for a job now. I tell him jes' work his head and do de bes' he can 'til</p>
    <p>his luck hit him. He's a expert crap shooter, but he tell me a fellow</p>
    <p>can't win les' he can rattle a little change in his pocket, so I let him</p>
    <p>have fifty cents. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"He say he gonna keep huntin' til he find work. He's proud, ef he</p>
    <p>is poor. And he don't want me workin' and him doin' nothin'. he say ef</p>
    <p>it take all de shoe leather off both his foots, he's gonna walk and coax</p>
    <p>'em to give him work 'til he gits it. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Twan't much later'n dat when Joe come in de kitchen and say,'Sally,</p>
    <p>I hear heap o' talk 'bout some work de Government's puttin' out. Dey</p>
    <p>calls it C.W.A. Whatever dat is. Dey gonna plant eighty-five acres near</p>
    <p>de Veterans' Hospital in cabbages, beans, taters, onions, squash, cucumbers </p>
    <p>en 'bout everthing you ever hear tell of. They calls that a project. </p>
    <p>Den dey aims to give all dis stuff to de poor folks, black and</p>
    <p>white, what can't buy rashions.'  </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Joe say he been down to see de foreman, and dat de foreman seem to</p>
    <p>like him when he told him he could plow en everthing. He told Joe to come</p>
    <p>back tomorrow, dat he 'blieve he can 'sign him on dat relief work. Joe</p>
    <p>told him ef he jus' 'sign him, he'd sho' give him more relief den he ever</p>
    <p>hope to git. He laugh en say he de one givin' de relief, dat Joe wan't. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"And, Miss Polly, Joe got dat relief job. He sho' was proud. Dey</p>
    <p>pay him two dollars and forty cent a day, five and a half days a week. De</p>
    <p>foreman say it 'pear like he got more sense dan heap uv 'em. And bein's</p>
    <p>he's such a fine plowhand, dey pays him more. De mule he plows is name</p>
    <p>Kate. He say his de only language dat mule can understand. He keep 'em</p>
    <p>all laughin' wid his mule talk en singin'. He res' his elbows on his plow</p>
    <p>handle, and sing:</p>
    <p/>
    <p>See dat peckerwood</p>
    <p>Settin' on de rail</p>
    <p>Learnin' how to figger</p>
    <p>All fer de white man</p>
    <p>Nothin' fer de nigger.  </p>
    <p/>
    <p>Den dey all laughs en jokes, en works harder den ever. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Miss Polly, Joe say when dey pays off on de project, he'll give me</p>
    <p>de money to go see Nattie. She de only sister I got. I got a letter from</p>
    <p>her. She comin' down here Tuesday week, and she want me to go back wid her    </p>
    <p>for a few days. Ef you can spare me, I could come on back Sunday."</p>
    <p/>
    <p>But on the night before Sally was to return, I heard a faint knock</p>
    <p>on my door. A thin, scantily clad little Negro girl was admitted. It</p>
    <p>was Sue, Sally's only child, whose advent into the world was a matter</p>
    <p>that concerned no one but her mother. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Miss Polly, Pa got shot. Ma say please let her come over here and</p>
    <p>spend de night. She say she'll sleep on de floor o' jes' anywhere. She</p>
    <p>jes' grieve and holler so. She say she can't stay in dat house by herse'f</p>
    <p>tonight." </p>
    <p/>
    <p>When Sally arrived, she was indeed an object of pity. Tears were</p>
    <p>streaming down her cheeks, and neither word nor deed seemed to comfort</p>
    <p>her. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Miss Polly, I can't stay dere. I can't! I can't. I'll die ef I</p>
    <p>stay in dat house tonight. I hates it." </p>
    <p/>
    <p>In her misery and grief, she beat on her head and breast, calling repeatedly </p>
    <p>on the Lord. Then, in a fit of utter exhaustion, she sank to the</p>
    <p>floor and related the following:</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Miss Polly, me and Nattie had heap o' pleasure visitin' 'round</p>
    <p>'mongst de neighbors. We went out to meetin' one night, and I was jes'</p>
    <p>nat'ually enjoyin' my visit. But dis mornin' I woke up wid a curious kind</p>
    <p>o' feelin'. I told Nattie I better git on back. I jes' couldn't get shed</p>
    <p>o' dat feelin' what kept tellin' me to come on back home. What you 'spose</p>
    <p>cause dat, Miss Polly?  </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Nattie, she tell me to git dem crazy notions out o' my head. Said</p>
    <p>I was jes' 'maginin' and hearin' things. Say I come to stay 'til Sunday,</p>
    <p>and to make myse'f satisfied. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"But dere wan't no way in de world I could get shed o' dat feelin'</p>
    <p>to come home. Nattie wuz plumb outdone wid me when I lef'. When I reach</p>
    <p>here, Joe wuz settin' in a chair by de fire. He say: "How come you come</p>
    <p>back? Thought you say you aim to stay till Sunday?'</p>
    <p/>
    <p>When I told him how come I come home, he most killed hisse'f</p>
    <p>laughin', and said" 'We got paid off on de project today. You buil' up a</p>
    <p>fire in de cook stove, and I'll run down to de store and git us a chicken </p>
    <p>fer supper.'  </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I pulled off my good clothes and soon had a fire 'goin' and de pot</p>
    <p>boilin'. Den I set down to wait for him and de chicken. Seven o'clock</p>
    <p>come and went. When eight o'clock struck, I begin to git uneasy. I</p>
    <p>thought 'bout de sign what wus give me up to Nattie's house. You know</p>
    <p>Joe's little dog name Fox? Dat dog was layin' dere by de fire sound</p>
    <p>asleep. After while, he tuk to shakin' same as he had a chill. Den he</p>
    <p>start growlin', and keep growlin' a little louder. Den he jump up and</p>
    <p>run up to me and bark and bark, jes' like he want to tell me sumpin'. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"All of a sudden I hear somebody call me. I stood up and saw de</p>
    <p>shadow of a man flyin' up de alley to my house. He say: 'Joe's shot.</p>
    <p>Come quick, and I'll take you to him.' </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Miss Polly, seem like everthing jes' went black. I run in a daze</p>
    <p>to where he was at, wid Fox right behin' me. He was layin' dere wid de</p>
    <p>street light shinin' on him. I dropped down by his side and put my hand</p>
    <p>on his heart. But de life had done gone out. I call and call him, but</p>
    <p>he never did answer. In his hand he was holdin' de parcel wid de</p>
    <p>chicken in it.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"De cruelest policeman come up and grab me by de shoulder and say:</p>
    <p>'Don't you know dead people can't talk. All o' you git out o' de way and</p>
    <p>go on 'bout your business.' Den he give poor little Fox a kick, eon say,</p>
    <p>'If somebody don't git dis dog out de way, he's gonna git shot, too.'</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Look like dey didn't let Joe git cold good 'fo he was shoved in a</p>
    <p>ambulance and took to de Funeral Home. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Ef it jes' hadn't been for dat drunken brawl in dat roomin' house,</p>
    <p>Joe never would o' been kilt. Two mens got to wranglin' over de same</p>
    <p>woman. Roy Jones grab a pistol, and de other man run out de house. Den</p>
    <p>Roy, he shoot through de window and hit my Joe.  </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Oh, Jesus, I don't know what I'm gonna do. Joe didn't have no inshoance. </p>
    <p>I don't know how we gonna bury him. Dat undertaker say when</p>
    <p>people don't have money for de coffin en everthing, dey jes' takes 'em</p>
    <p>out and burns 'em.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>The next morning the foreman of the project came in and said:</p>
    <p>'Sally, I've just come from the Welfare Board. They will contribute fifteen</p>
    <p>dollars. The men on the project are making a donation, and, with</p>
    <p>what you have, we can get Joe buried all right.'</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Oh, Jesus, I sho' is grateful. Now, Miss Polly, ef you jes' let</p>
    <p>me stay here 'til dey buries him, and jes' go long wid me, de Lord will</p>
    <p>sho' bless you. </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"I got a right pretty black dress and veil one o' de ladies in de</p>
    <p>church give me." </p>
    <p/>
    <p>Tuesday morning, after the project workers and others had gathered</p>
    <p>for the funeral, a small figure draped in black entered. She was a symbol </p>
    <p>of perfect composure. But as the first notes of "Nearer My God to</p>
    <p>Thee" were heard and the preacher began his chant and eulogy of the deceased, </p>
    <p>she threw all restraint to the winds.      </p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Oh, Lordy, there he. Oh! Lordy, I see's him. There he is. Oh!</p>
    <p>Jesus, how come you take my Joe? There he. Oh! Lordy." </p>
    <p/>
    <p>Annie, supporting her and stroking her shoulder was heard to say:</p>
    <p>'Sally, brace up, child, don't carry on so. You'll make yourself downright </p>
    <p>sick. Brace yourself. Here comes de foreman. Can't nobody hear</p>
    <p>what de preacher sayin'. And I know he gonna talk pretty 'bout Joe.</p>
    <p>You knows you want to hear de singin' and prayin.' 'Sides they's got</p>
    <p>to git through wid dis buryin'. Two days been los' 'count o' that bed</p>
    <p>o' rock dem gravediggers struck. And the mens has to git back to de</p>
    <p>project. Now you do as Annie say, and brace yourse'f.' </p>
    <p/>
    <p>About eight o'clock Joe started on his last earthly journey. The</p>
    <p>cold was intense; the ground frozen. Finally, eight white pallbearers</p>
    <p>lowered his last remains into a grave dug in Potter's Field.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>I glanced out of my window, to see a transformed Sally approach</p>
    <p>the house. She was leaning on the arm of a sympathetic Negro man.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Miss Polly, dat 'bout the finest car I ever see, what I went de</p>
    <p>buryin' in. Dat undertaker man so nice. He hold my hand and say he</p>
    <p>pow'ful sorry 'bout my trouble. I jes' couldn't he'p but laugh when he</p>
    <p>say I sho' make a good lookin' widow."    </p>
    <p/>
    <p>About a week after the funeral, Sally began to complain of a misery</p>
    <p>in her head, and said: "Miss Polly, seem lak I can't do much good</p>
    <p>stayin' here. I can't sleep nights, and I ain't able to git my mind set</p>
    <p>on anything. 'Bout de bes' thing for me and Sue to do is to go to</p>
    <p>Nattie's. I'm gonna git me a nerve tonic, and see can't I git to feelin'</p>
    <p>right. Den I'll be back. I never will forgit all you done for me." </p>
    <p/>
    <p>Four years later I walked in Silver's Dime Store, and there stood</p>
    <p>Sally. On seeing me, she manifested surprise and embarrassment, as she</p>
    <p>released the arm of a tall, light-colored Negro. They were standing at</p>
    <p>the jewelry counter. Sally was trying on first one ring, then another.</p>
    <p>She no longer wore her look of distress and widow's mourning. Instead,</p>
    <p>she was decked out in one of the stylish pancake-shaped hats, which</p>
    <p>reposed on her left ear, a red dress and coat, and black suede pumps.</p>
    <p>Gold earrings and beads completed her costume. The face powder which</p>
    <p>had been applied a little too generously gave her an ashy look as she</p>
    <p>greeted me.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Oh! Miss Polly, I'm sho' glad to see you. I sho' have talked</p>
    <p>and thought 'bout all of you. Dis my cousin from up de country where</p>
    <p>Nattie live. He come to see de Christmas in Columbia." Both displayed</p>
    <p>large, very white teeth is a broad grin exchanged between them.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Annie give me your message. Yes'm, she told me, and I'm sho'</p>
    <p>comin' to see you durin' de Christmas. How's all your girls? Well,</p>
    <p>you look for me, 'cause I'm sho' comin'. I wants to hear all 'bout</p>
    <p>you all."    </p>
    <p/>
    <p>Three weeks later I heard a faint knock on my door. Sally came</p>
    <p>in timidly and handed me one of her bright red geraniums that she grew</p>
    <p>in a tomato can.    </p>
    <p/>
    <p>Always eager to help, she performed first one little odd job, then</p>
    <p>another. Finally she sat down, and over a cup of hot coffee in the</p>
    <p>kitchen, her mood became reminiscent.</p>
    <p/>
    <p>"Miss Polly, you know it's 'zactly four years gone dis month since</p>
    <p>I los' Joe. I sho' miss him. I wish de good Lord could o' spared him,</p>
    <p>but He know best. You know dat boy I was in company wid in de dime</p>
    <p>store? He's a good boy, and we been keepin' company for some time.</p>
    <p>Seems like I got so lonely stayin' by myself all de time, We went 'round</p>
    <p>to de magistrate's office and got married dat same afternoon. His name is</p>
    <p>Rufus Allen. He's got steady vork at a filling station. Makes six dollars </p>
    <p>a week. He also picks up a little change in tips, too. I'm maid at a</p>
    <p>boardin' house on Lady Street. De work ain't so confining, and I get</p>
    <p>four dollars a week. So if Rufus jes' keep on like he's doin' now,</p>
    <p>I know we will get along all right. I know he's been true to me so far.</p>
    <p>But you see we jes' been married a month.    </p>
    <p/>
    <p>**********</p>
    <p>JJC </p>
  </text>
</history>
