<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../lifehistory.xsl" ?>
<history>
  <title>Cannon-ball in Tree on Grounds of Harriett Beecher Stowe Home in Mandarin</title>
  <reflink>https://dc.lib.unc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/03709/id/1096</reflink>
  <meta>
    <item>
      <key>Date</key>
      <val>1936-11-30</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Location</key>
      <val>Jacksonville, Florida</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Community</key>
      <val>Mandarin</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Interviewee</key>
      <val>Ruth J. Banes (white; female)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Writer</key>
      <val>Rose Shepherd (white; female)</val>
    </item>
  </meta>
  <text>
    <p>No. 137</p>
    <p>November 30, 1936.</p>
    <p>HISTORICAL - "War Between the States"</p>
    <p>Mrs. Ruth J. (Bardin) Banes,</p>
    <p>Mitchell Bldg.,</p>
    <p>Jacksonville, Florida.</p>
    <p>SUBJECT: - Cannon-ball in tree on grounds of Harriett Beecher Stowe home in Mandarin</p>
    <p>"The town of Mandarin was never shelled, bombarded or &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; at any time during the War between the States.</p>
    <p>"I have heard my mother and grand-mother, the wife of James James, one of the earlier settlers of mandarin, say that when word was received early in the month of March, 1862, that a large force was on its way to occupy the City of Jacksonville, there was great consternation and considerable trepidation as to what was the best policy to &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, if such a situation presented itself.</p>
    <p>"It did develop that several Federal gunboats crossed St. Johns bar on the evening of March 11, 1862, anchoring in the River, and the next morning steamed up to the harbor of Jacksonville, the flagship "Mahaska" leading the squadron - four gunboats - "Ottawa," "Pembina," "Seneca" and the "Isaac Smith" - with two transports bearing troops, Guns were fired all along the route. The woods resounding and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; time and time again with the frequent reports, spreading the alarm &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; the plantation owners along the River that the Federals were on their way to take over the City of Jacksonville.</p>
    <p>"When opposite Mandarin, shots were fired, and the cannon-ball &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; lodged in the tree on the Harriett Beecher Stone place that is, it &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; one of the trees around which the Stowe home was &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; in 1867 was a stray shot, as the guns were trained high in the air, and the ball &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; fell, lodging in the crotch of the tree.</p>
    <p>"There was no &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; of Jacksonville. The squadron came to anchor in the harbor, the officers were put ashore, and the taking over of the City was a very tame affair, since all the available men had &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; for duty and were away, some far away in Virginia and Mississippi, and other Southern States where the fighting was heaviest, some &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; troops were scattered over the State, but the Mayor of Jacksonville, H. H. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; had issued a proclamation advising non-resistance previous to the arrival of the enemy, and the few citizens who had not refugeed, made all possible haste to get to the interior, in anticipation of &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; long occupation by the Federals.</p>
    <p>"My family, the Bardins, had already gone to St. Augustine, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; their farm in charge of a faithful old negro, Stephen, who stayed there for the duration of the War, raising &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;, attending to his hogs, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and chickens, without molestation. This was the Mott place on &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; creek - a Spanish grant just over the line in St. Johns County, later sold to General Loring, and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; from - him by my grand-father, Barlin. The James's remained on their place, known as the Plummer Grant." "Grand-mother James secured a pass from the Federal Commandant to visit her relatives in St. Augustine a few days after the third occupation of Jacksonville and there she remained with her children until peace was restored. I have this pass giving her permission to leave - Post Pass No. 536 dated February &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; 1864, signed by F. M. Sweet, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; and Acting Provost Marshall."</p>
  </text>
</history>
