<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../lifehistory.xsl" ?>
<history>
  <title>Untitled</title>
  <reflink>https://dc.lib.unc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/03709/id/1101</reflink>
  <meta>
    <item>
      <key>Date</key>
      <val>1937-09-10</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Location</key>
      <val>Jacksonville, Florida</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Interviewee</key>
      <val>Katherine Fitzgerald (white; female)</val>
    </item>
    <item>
      <key>Writer</key>
      <val>Rose Shepherd (white; female)</val>
    </item>
  </meta>
  <text>
    <p>F. c.</p>
    <p>Rose Shepherd</p>
    <p>Interview No. 113</p>
    <p>September 10, 193&amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;</p>
    <p>HISTORICAL - Jacksonville</p>
    <p>Mrs. Katherine (Wilson) Fitzgerald</p>
    <p>San Juline Apartments, No. 2,</p>
    <p>1623 Riverside-ave,</p>
    <p>Jacksonville, Florida.</p>
    <p>Mrs. Katherine (Wilson) Fitzgerald, sister of J. Y. Wilson, was born and raised in Duval County, and is not families with Nassau County or Fernandina history.</p>
    <p>She says: "My grand-mother and my mother were natives of Duval County. My father, George Simpson Wilson, came from the north of Ireland in 1855 and was married in Jacksonville to my mother, Catherine Anne Maria Maxey, of Pablo Beach. My grand-father Maxey had a grant of land at Pablo from the Spanish Government, recorded in the land office at St. Augustine, and later certified by the English Government.</p>
    <p>My father, George S. Wilson and my uncle, James Young Wilson, for whom my brother is named, had a grocery store on East/Bay-st., near Main-st. My father was a soldier during the Confederacy and returned to his business in Jacksonville afterwards.</p>
    <p>FIRE IN DOWN-TOWN JACKSONVILLE on August 17, 1891:</p>
    <p>"On the above date there was an immense fire broke out around midnight in the crockery store of &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;by a Knight on East Bay-st. near main-st., a comparatively new building of four stories. Some excelsior used in packing caught fire from carelessness of some sort near the elevator shaft, &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;in a few minutes the building was a mass of flames. &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;ned by a considerable breeze, it swept Northward, across Forsyth-st. to the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;(Smith) Hotel on the site of the present building by that same &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;. As the windle Hotel became gutted by the flames, the walls fell to &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;the crush set off a large quantity of dynamite stored there &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;C. B. Smith, who dealt in this merchandise, selling it to farmers for &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;blasting out stumps.</p>
    <p>"A tremendous explosion followed, which broke all the windows in the neighborhood, blew out doors, and our home on Adams-st. on the opposite side of the block occupied by the windle hotel, being in the path &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;flames was, consumed in short order with all of our belongings and &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;valuable family records. One book was saved, containing accounts &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;to my father in the grocery business, which resulted in his &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; hundred dollars worth of outstanding bills, which he otherwise &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; had no record of.</p>
    <p>"This was nine years previous to the big fire of 1901, and the &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt;and historical records we possessed that survived the first &amp;lt;text not clear&amp;gt; lost in the second."</p>
  </text>
</history>
